^ (Ps. 119:1-176) Happy are those who are blameless* in their way, Who walk in the law of Jehovah.  2 Happy are those who observe his reminders, Who search for him with all their heart.  3 They practice no unrighteousness; They walk in his ways.  4 You have commanded That your orders be carefully kept.  5 If only I could remain steadfast* So as to observe your regulations!  6 Then I would not be put to shame When I consider all your commandments.  7 I will praise you with an upright heart When I learn your righteous judgments.  8 I will observe your regulations. May you never utterly forsake me.  9 How can a young man keep his path clean? By keeping on guard according to your word. 10 With my whole heart I seek you. Do not let me stray from your commandments. 11 In my heart I treasure up your saying So that I may not sin against you. 12 May you be praised, O Jehovah; Teach me your regulations. 13 With my lips I declare All the judgments that you have spoken. 14 I rejoice over your reminders More than over all other valuable things. 15 I will ponder over* your orders And keep my eyes on your paths. 16 I am fond of your statutes. I will not forget your word. 17 Deal kindly with your servant, So that I may live and observe your word. 18 Open my eyes so that I may see clearly The wonderful things from your law. 19 I am but a foreigner in the land. Do not hide your commandments from me. 20 I am* consumed with longing For your judgments at all times. 21 You rebuke the presumptuous, The cursed ones who stray from your commandments. 22 Remove from me* scorn and contempt, For I have observed your reminders. 23 Even when princes sit together and speak against me, Your servant ponders over* your regulations. 24 I am fond of your reminders; They are my advisers. 25 I lie* prostrate in the dust. Preserve me alive according to your word. 26 I told you of my ways, and you answered me; Teach me your regulations. 27 Make me understand the meaning* of your orders, So that I may ponder over* your wonderful works. 28 I have* been sleepless from grief. Strengthen me according to your word. 29 Remove from me the way of deception, And favor me with your law. 30 The way of faithfulness I have chosen. I recognize that your judgments are right. 31 I cling to your reminders. O Jehovah, do not let me be disappointed.* 32 I will eagerly pursue* the way of your commandments Because you make room for it in my heart.* 33 Teach me, O Jehovah, the way of your regulations, And I will follow it to the end. 34 Give me understanding, So that I may observe your law And keep it with my whole heart. 35 Guide me* in the pathway of your commandments, For in it I take delight. 36 Incline my heart to your reminders, Not to selfish gain.* 37 Turn my eyes away from looking at what is worthless; Preserve me alive in your way. 38 Fulfill your promise* to your servant, So that you may be feared.* 39 Remove the disgrace that I dread, For your judgments are good. 40 See how I long for your orders. Preserve me alive in your righteousness. 41 May I experience your loyal love, O Jehovah, Your salvation in harmony with your promise;* 42 Then I will reply to the one taunting me, For I put my trust in your word. 43 Do not utterly remove the word of truth from my mouth, For I have hoped in* your judgment. 44 I will keep your law constantly, Forever and ever. 45 And I will walk about in a place of safety,* For I search for your orders. 46 I will speak about your reminders in front of kings, And I will not be ashamed. 47 I am fond of your commandments, Yes, I love them. 48 I will raise my hands to your commandments, which I love, And I will ponder over* your regulations. 49 Remember your word* to your servant, Through which you give me hope.* 50 This is my comfort in my affliction, For your saying has preserved me alive. 51 The presumptuous utterly scorn me, But I do not deviate from your law. 52 I remember your judgments from of old, O Jehovah, And I find comfort in them. 53 I am seized with burning rage because of the wicked, Who forsake your law. 54 Your regulations are songs to me Wherever I dwell.* 55 During the night I remember your name, O Jehovah, So that I may keep your law. 56 This has been my practice Because I have observed your orders. 57 Jehovah is my portion; I have promised to keep your words. 58 I appeal to you* with all my heart; Show me favor according to your promise.* 59 I have examined my ways, In order to turn my feet back to your reminders. 60 I hurry and do not delay To keep your commandments. 61 The ropes of the wicked surround me, But your law I do not forget. 62 At midnight I get up to give you thanks For your righteous judgments. 63 I am a friend of all who fear you And of those who keep your orders. 64 Your loyal love, O Jehovah, fills the earth; Teach me your regulations. 65 You have dealt well with your servant, O Jehovah, according to your word. 66 Teach me good sense and knowledge, For I have put my trust in your commandments. 67 Before I was afflicted, I used to go astray,* But now I keep your saying. 68 You are good and your works are good. Teach me your regulations. 69 The presumptuous smear me with lies, But I observe your orders with all my heart. 70 Their heart is insensitive,* But I am fond of your law. 71 It is good that I have been afflicted, So that I may learn your regulations. 72 The law that you have proclaimed is good for me, More so than thousands of pieces of gold and silver. 73 Your hands made me and formed me. Give me understanding, So that I may learn your commandments. 74 Those who fear you see me and rejoice, For your word is my hope.* 75 I know, O Jehovah, that your judgments are righteous And that you have afflicted me in your faithfulness. 76 May your loyal love please comfort me, According to the promise* you made to your servant. 77 Show me mercy, so that I may keep living, For I am fond of your law. 78 May the presumptuous be put to shame, For they wrong me without cause.* But I will ponder over* your orders. 79 Let those who fear you return to me, Those who know your reminders. 80 May my heart be blameless in following your regulations, So that I may not be put to shame. 81 I long for* your salvation, For your word is my hope.* 82 My eyes long for your saying While I say: “When will you comfort me?” 83 For I am like a skin bottle dried up in the smoke, But your regulations I do not forget. 84 How many days must your servant wait? When will you bring judgment against those persecuting me? 85 The presumptuous dig pits for me, Those who defy your law. 86 All your commandments are trustworthy. Men persecute me without cause; help me! 87 They almost exterminated me from the earth, But I did not abandon your orders. 88 Preserve me alive because of your loyal love, So that I may keep the reminders you have spoken. 89 Forever, O Jehovah, Your word will remain in the heavens. 90 Your faithfulness is through all generations. You have firmly established the earth, so that it continues to stand. 91 By your judgments they* remain until today, For they are all your servants. 92 If I had not been fond of your law, I would have perished in my affliction. 93 I will never forget your orders, Because by them you have preserved me alive. 94 I belong to you; save me, Because I have searched for your orders. 95 The wicked wait to destroy me, But I give close attention to your reminders. 96 I have seen a limit to all perfection, But your commandment has no limit.* 97 How I do love your law! I ponder over* it all day long. 98 Your commandment makes me wiser than my enemies, Because it is with me forever. 99 I have more insight than all my teachers, Because I ponder over* your reminders. 100 I act with more understanding than older men, Because I observe your orders. 101 I refuse to walk on any evil path, So that I may keep your word. 102 I do not turn aside from your judgments, For you have instructed me. 103 How sweet your sayings are to my palate, More so than honey to my mouth! 104 By your orders I act with understanding. That is why I hate every false path. 105 Your word is a lamp to my foot, And a light for my path. 106 I have sworn an oath, and I will carry it out, To observe your righteous judgments. 107 I have been greatly afflicted. O Jehovah, preserve me alive according to your word. 108 Please take pleasure in my voluntary offerings of praise,* O Jehovah, And teach me your judgments. 109 My life is in constant danger,* But I have not forgotten your law. 110 The wicked have set a trap for me, But I have not strayed from your orders. 111 I take your reminders as my permanent possession,* For they are the joy of my heart. 112 I have resolved* to obey your regulations At all times, down to the last. 113 I hate the halfhearted ones,* But I love your law. 114 You are my shelter and my shield, For your word is my hope.* 115 Stay away from me, you evil men, So that I may observe the commandments of my God. 116 Support me as you promised,* So that I may keep living; Do not let my hope turn into disappointment.* 117 Support me that I may be saved; Then I will always concentrate on your regulations. 118 You reject all those who stray from your regulations, For they are false and deceitful. 119 You discard all the wicked of the earth as if they were worthless dross. That is why I love your reminders. 120 The dread of you makes my body* tremble; I am in fear of your judgments. 121 I have done what is just and righteous. Do not abandon me to my oppressors! 122 Guarantee the welfare of your servant; May the presumptuous not oppress me. 123 My eyes have grown weary waiting for your salvation And for your righteous promise.* 124 Show your loyal love to your servant, And teach me your regulations. 125 I am your servant; give me understanding, So that I may know your reminders. 126 The time has come for Jehovah to act, For they have broken your law. 127 That is why I love your commandments More than gold, even fine* gold. 128 Therefore, I consider every instruction* from you to be right; I hate every false path. 129 Your reminders are wonderful. That is why I observe* them. 130 The disclosure of your words brings light, Giving understanding to the inexperienced. 131 I open my mouth wide and sigh,* Because I long for your commandments. 132 Turn to me and show me favor, In keeping with your judgment toward those loving your name. 133 Guide my steps safely* by your saying; May nothing wicked dominate me. 134 Rescue* me from oppressive men, And I will keep your orders. 135 Make your face shine* upon your servant, And teach me your regulations. 136 Tears stream down from my eyes Because people do not keep your law. 137 You are righteous, O Jehovah, And your judgments are fair. 138 The reminders you give are righteous And completely reliable. 139 My zeal consumes me, Because my adversaries have forgotten your words. 140 Your saying is thoroughly refined, And your servant loves it. 141 I am insignificant and despised; Yet, I have not forgotten your orders. 142 Your righteousness is an eternal righteousness, And your law is truth. 143 Though distress and difficulty come upon me, I remain fond of your commandments. 144 The righteousness of your reminders is eternal. Give me understanding, so that I may keep living. 145 I call with my whole heart. Answer me, O Jehovah. Your regulations I will observe. 146 I call on you; save me! I will keep your reminders. 147 I have been awake before dawn* to cry for help, For your words are my hope.* 148 My eyes open before the night watches, So that I can ponder over* your saying. 149 Do listen to my voice because of your loyal love. O Jehovah, preserve me alive according to your justice. 150 Those who engage in shameful conduct* come near; They are far away from your law. 151 You are near, O Jehovah, And all your commandments are truth. 152 Long ago I learned about your reminders, That you have established them to last forever. 153 Look on my affliction and rescue me, For I have not forgotten your law. 154 Defend me* and rescue me; Preserve me alive in harmony with your promise.* 155 Salvation is far away from the wicked, For they have not searched for your regulations. 156 Your mercy is great, O Jehovah. Preserve me alive in harmony with your justice. 157 My persecutors and my adversaries are many; But I have not deviated from your reminders. 158 I look on the treacherous with loathing, Because they do not keep your saying. 159 See how I love your orders! O Jehovah, preserve me alive because of your loyal love. 160 The very essence of your word is truth, And all your righteous judgments endure forever. 161 Princes persecute me for no cause, But my heart stands in awe of your words. 162 I rejoice over your saying Like someone who finds great spoil. 163 I hate falsehood—I detest it— I love your law. 164 Seven times a day I praise you Because of your righteous judgments. 165 Abundant peace belongs to those who love your law; Nothing can make them stumble.* 166 I hope for your acts of salvation, O Jehovah, And I observe your commandments. 167 I keep* your reminders, And I love them dearly. 168 I observe your orders and your reminders, For you are aware of all that I do. 169 May my cry for help reach you, O Jehovah. According to your word, make me understand. 170 May my request for favor come before you. Save me, as you have promised.* 171 May my lips overflow with praise, For you teach me your regulations. 172 May my tongue sing about your saying, For all your commandments are righteous. 173 May your hand be ready to help me, Because I choose to obey your orders. 174 I long for your salvation, O Jehovah, And I am fond of your law. 175 Let me* live so that I may praise you; May your judgments be my help. 176 I have strayed like a lost sheep. Search for your servant, For I have not forgotten your commandments.

Or “who keep integrity.”

Lit., “O that my ways were firmly established.”

Or “study.”

Or “My soul is.”

Lit., “Roll away from upon me.”

Or “studies.”

Or “My soul lies.”

Lit., “way.”

Or “study.”

Or “My soul has.”

Or “be put to shame.”

Lit., “will run.”

Or possibly, “you make my heart have the confidence.”

Or “Make me walk.”

Or “to profits.”

Or “saying.”

Or possibly, “Which is made to those who fear you.”

Or “saying.”

Or “I wait for.”

Or “a roomy place.”

Or “study.”

Or “promise.”

Or “For which you made me wait.”

Or “In the house where I dwell as a foreigner.”

Or “I soften (seek the smile of) your face.”

Or “saying.”

Or “I was sinning by mistake.”

Lit., “unfeeling, like fat.”

Or “I wait for your word.”

Or “saying.”

Or possibly, “with lies.”

Or “study.”

Or “My soul pines for.”

Or “I wait for your word.”

That is, all his creative works.

Lit., “is very broad.”

Or “study.”

Or “study.”

Lit., “the voluntary offerings of my mouth.”

Or “My soul is in my hand constantly.”

Or “my eternal heritage.”

Lit., “have inclined my heart.”

Or “men of divided heart.”

Or “I wait for your word.”

Or “according to your saying.”

Or “be put to shame.”

Lit., “flesh.”

Or “saying.”

Or “refined.”

Or “order.”

Or “my soul observes.”

Lit., “pant.”

Or “Make my steps steady.”

Lit., “Redeem.”

Or “smile.”

Or “in the morning twilight.”

Or “I wait for your words.”

Or “study.”

Or “in obscene conduct.”

Or “Conduct my legal case.”

Or “saying.”

Or “For them there is no stumbling block.”

Or “My soul keeps.”

Or “according to your saying.”

Or “my soul.”

^ (Ps. 119:1-176) Happy are those who are blameless* in their way, Who walk in the law of Jehovah.  2 Happy are those who observe his reminders, Who search for him with all their heart.  3 They practice no unrighteousness; They walk in his ways.  4 You have commanded That your orders be carefully kept.  5 If only I could remain steadfast* So as to observe your regulations!  6 Then I would not be put to shame When I consider all your commandments.  7 I will praise you with an upright heart When I learn your righteous judgments.  8 I will observe your regulations. May you never utterly forsake me.  9 How can a young man keep his path clean? By keeping on guard according to your word. 10 With my whole heart I seek you. Do not let me stray from your commandments. 11 In my heart I treasure up your saying So that I may not sin against you. 12 May you be praised, O Jehovah; Teach me your regulations. 13 With my lips I declare All the judgments that you have spoken. 14 I rejoice over your reminders More than over all other valuable things. 15 I will ponder over* your orders And keep my eyes on your paths. 16 I am fond of your statutes. I will not forget your word. 17 Deal kindly with your servant, So that I may live and observe your word. 18 Open my eyes so that I may see clearly The wonderful things from your law. 19 I am but a foreigner in the land. Do not hide your commandments from me. 20 I am* consumed with longing For your judgments at all times. 21 You rebuke the presumptuous, The cursed ones who stray from your commandments. 22 Remove from me* scorn and contempt, For I have observed your reminders. 23 Even when princes sit together and speak against me, Your servant ponders over* your regulations. 24 I am fond of your reminders; They are my advisers. 25 I lie* prostrate in the dust. Preserve me alive according to your word. 26 I told you of my ways, and you answered me; Teach me your regulations. 27 Make me understand the meaning* of your orders, So that I may ponder over* your wonderful works. 28 I have* been sleepless from grief. Strengthen me according to your word. 29 Remove from me the way of deception, And favor me with your law. 30 The way of faithfulness I have chosen. I recognize that your judgments are right. 31 I cling to your reminders. O Jehovah, do not let me be disappointed.* 32 I will eagerly pursue* the way of your commandments Because you make room for it in my heart.* 33 Teach me, O Jehovah, the way of your regulations, And I will follow it to the end. 34 Give me understanding, So that I may observe your law And keep it with my whole heart. 35 Guide me* in the pathway of your commandments, For in it I take delight. 36 Incline my heart to your reminders, Not to selfish gain.* 37 Turn my eyes away from looking at what is worthless; Preserve me alive in your way. 38 Fulfill your promise* to your servant, So that you may be feared.* 39 Remove the disgrace that I dread, For your judgments are good. 40 See how I long for your orders. Preserve me alive in your righteousness. 41 May I experience your loyal love, O Jehovah, Your salvation in harmony with your promise;* 42 Then I will reply to the one taunting me, For I put my trust in your word. 43 Do not utterly remove the word of truth from my mouth, For I have hoped in* your judgment. 44 I will keep your law constantly, Forever and ever. 45 And I will walk about in a place of safety,* For I search for your orders. 46 I will speak about your reminders in front of kings, And I will not be ashamed. 47 I am fond of your commandments, Yes, I love them. 48 I will raise my hands to your commandments, which I love, And I will ponder over* your regulations. 49 Remember your word* to your servant, Through which you give me hope.* 50 This is my comfort in my affliction, For your saying has preserved me alive. 51 The presumptuous utterly scorn me, But I do not deviate from your law. 52 I remember your judgments from of old, O Jehovah, And I find comfort in them. 53 I am seized with burning rage because of the wicked, Who forsake your law. 54 Your regulations are songs to me Wherever I dwell.* 55 During the night I remember your name, O Jehovah, So that I may keep your law. 56 This has been my practice Because I have observed your orders. 57 Jehovah is my portion; I have promised to keep your words. 58 I appeal to you* with all my heart; Show me favor according to your promise.* 59 I have examined my ways, In order to turn my feet back to your reminders. 60 I hurry and do not delay To keep your commandments. 61 The ropes of the wicked surround me, But your law I do not forget. 62 At midnight I get up to give you thanks For your righteous judgments. 63 I am a friend of all who fear you And of those who keep your orders. 64 Your loyal love, O Jehovah, fills the earth; Teach me your regulations. 65 You have dealt well with your servant, O Jehovah, according to your word. 66 Teach me good sense and knowledge, For I have put my trust in your commandments. 67 Before I was afflicted, I used to go astray,* But now I keep your saying. 68 You are good and your works are good. Teach me your regulations. 69 The presumptuous smear me with lies, But I observe your orders with all my heart. 70 Their heart is insensitive,* But I am fond of your law. 71 It is good that I have been afflicted, So that I may learn your regulations. 72 The law that you have proclaimed is good for me, More so than thousands of pieces of gold and silver. 73 Your hands made me and formed me. Give me understanding, So that I may learn your commandments. 74 Those who fear you see me and rejoice, For your word is my hope.* 75 I know, O Jehovah, that your judgments are righteous And that you have afflicted me in your faithfulness. 76 May your loyal love please comfort me, According to the promise* you made to your servant. 77 Show me mercy, so that I may keep living, For I am fond of your law. 78 May the presumptuous be put to shame, For they wrong me without cause.* But I will ponder over* your orders. 79 Let those who fear you return to me, Those who know your reminders. 80 May my heart be blameless in following your regulations, So that I may not be put to shame. 81 I long for* your salvation, For your word is my hope.* 82 My eyes long for your saying While I say: “When will you comfort me?” 83 For I am like a skin bottle dried up in the smoke, But your regulations I do not forget. 84 How many days must your servant wait? When will you bring judgment against those persecuting me? 85 The presumptuous dig pits for me, Those who defy your law. 86 All your commandments are trustworthy. Men persecute me without cause; help me! 87 They almost exterminated me from the earth, But I did not abandon your orders. 88 Preserve me alive because of your loyal love, So that I may keep the reminders you have spoken. 89 Forever, O Jehovah, Your word will remain in the heavens. 90 Your faithfulness is through all generations. You have firmly established the earth, so that it continues to stand. 91 By your judgments they* remain until today, For they are all your servants. 92 If I had not been fond of your law, I would have perished in my affliction. 93 I will never forget your orders, Because by them you have preserved me alive. 94 I belong to you; save me, Because I have searched for your orders. 95 The wicked wait to destroy me, But I give close attention to your reminders. 96 I have seen a limit to all perfection, But your commandment has no limit.* 97 How I do love your law! I ponder over* it all day long. 98 Your commandment makes me wiser than my enemies, Because it is with me forever. 99 I have more insight than all my teachers, Because I ponder over* your reminders. 100 I act with more understanding than older men, Because I observe your orders. 101 I refuse to walk on any evil path, So that I may keep your word. 102 I do not turn aside from your judgments, For you have instructed me. 103 How sweet your sayings are to my palate, More so than honey to my mouth! 104 By your orders I act with understanding. That is why I hate every false path. 105 Your word is a lamp to my foot, And a light for my path. 106 I have sworn an oath, and I will carry it out, To observe your righteous judgments. 107 I have been greatly afflicted. O Jehovah, preserve me alive according to your word. 108 Please take pleasure in my voluntary offerings of praise,* O Jehovah, And teach me your judgments. 109 My life is in constant danger,* But I have not forgotten your law. 110 The wicked have set a trap for me, But I have not strayed from your orders. 111 I take your reminders as my permanent possession,* For they are the joy of my heart. 112 I have resolved* to obey your regulations At all times, down to the last. 113 I hate the halfhearted ones,* But I love your law. 114 You are my shelter and my shield, For your word is my hope.* 115 Stay away from me, you evil men, So that I may observe the commandments of my God. 116 Support me as you promised,* So that I may keep living; Do not let my hope turn into disappointment.* 117 Support me that I may be saved; Then I will always concentrate on your regulations. 118 You reject all those who stray from your regulations, For they are false and deceitful. 119 You discard all the wicked of the earth as if they were worthless dross. That is why I love your reminders. 120 The dread of you makes my body* tremble; I am in fear of your judgments. 121 I have done what is just and righteous. Do not abandon me to my oppressors! 122 Guarantee the welfare of your servant; May the presumptuous not oppress me. 123 My eyes have grown weary waiting for your salvation And for your righteous promise.* 124 Show your loyal love to your servant, And teach me your regulations. 125 I am your servant; give me understanding, So that I may know your reminders. 126 The time has come for Jehovah to act, For they have broken your law. 127 That is why I love your commandments More than gold, even fine* gold. 128 Therefore, I consider every instruction* from you to be right; I hate every false path. 129 Your reminders are wonderful. That is why I observe* them. 130 The disclosure of your words brings light, Giving understanding to the inexperienced. 131 I open my mouth wide and sigh,* Because I long for your commandments. 132 Turn to me and show me favor, In keeping with your judgment toward those loving your name. 133 Guide my steps safely* by your saying; May nothing wicked dominate me. 134 Rescue* me from oppressive men, And I will keep your orders. 135 Make your face shine* upon your servant, And teach me your regulations. 136 Tears stream down from my eyes Because people do not keep your law. 137 You are righteous, O Jehovah, And your judgments are fair. 138 The reminders you give are righteous And completely reliable. 139 My zeal consumes me, Because my adversaries have forgotten your words. 140 Your saying is thoroughly refined, And your servant loves it. 141 I am insignificant and despised; Yet, I have not forgotten your orders. 142 Your righteousness is an eternal righteousness, And your law is truth. 143 Though distress and difficulty come upon me, I remain fond of your commandments. 144 The righteousness of your reminders is eternal. Give me understanding, so that I may keep living. 145 I call with my whole heart. Answer me, O Jehovah. Your regulations I will observe. 146 I call on you; save me! I will keep your reminders. 147 I have been awake before dawn* to cry for help, For your words are my hope.* 148 My eyes open before the night watches, So that I can ponder over* your saying. 149 Do listen to my voice because of your loyal love. O Jehovah, preserve me alive according to your justice. 150 Those who engage in shameful conduct* come near; They are far away from your law. 151 You are near, O Jehovah, And all your commandments are truth. 152 Long ago I learned about your reminders, That you have established them to last forever. 153 Look on my affliction and rescue me, For I have not forgotten your law. 154 Defend me* and rescue me; Preserve me alive in harmony with your promise.* 155 Salvation is far away from the wicked, For they have not searched for your regulations. 156 Your mercy is great, O Jehovah. Preserve me alive in harmony with your justice. 157 My persecutors and my adversaries are many; But I have not deviated from your reminders. 158 I look on the treacherous with loathing, Because they do not keep your saying. 159 See how I love your orders! O Jehovah, preserve me alive because of your loyal love. 160 The very essence of your word is truth, And all your righteous judgments endure forever. 161 Princes persecute me for no cause, But my heart stands in awe of your words. 162 I rejoice over your saying Like someone who finds great spoil. 163 I hate falsehood—I detest it— I love your law. 164 Seven times a day I praise you Because of your righteous judgments. 165 Abundant peace belongs to those who love your law; Nothing can make them stumble.* 166 I hope for your acts of salvation, O Jehovah, And I observe your commandments. 167 I keep* your reminders, And I love them dearly. 168 I observe your orders and your reminders, For you are aware of all that I do. 169 May my cry for help reach you, O Jehovah. According to your word, make me understand. 170 May my request for favor come before you. Save me, as you have promised.* 171 May my lips overflow with praise, For you teach me your regulations. 172 May my tongue sing about your saying, For all your commandments are righteous. 173 May your hand be ready to help me, Because I choose to obey your orders. 174 I long for your salvation, O Jehovah, And I am fond of your law. 175 Let me* live so that I may praise you; May your judgments be my help. 176 I have strayed like a lost sheep. Search for your servant, For I have not forgotten your commandments.

Or “who keep integrity.”

Lit., “O that my ways were firmly established.”

Or “study.”

Or “My soul is.”

Lit., “Roll away from upon me.”

Or “studies.”

Or “My soul lies.”

Lit., “way.”

Or “study.”

Or “My soul has.”

Or “be put to shame.”

Lit., “will run.”

Or possibly, “you make my heart have the confidence.”

Or “Make me walk.”

Or “to profits.”

Or “saying.”

Or possibly, “Which is made to those who fear you.”

Or “saying.”

Or “I wait for.”

Or “a roomy place.”

Or “study.”

Or “promise.”

Or “For which you made me wait.”

Or “In the house where I dwell as a foreigner.”

Or “I soften (seek the smile of) your face.”

Or “saying.”

Or “I was sinning by mistake.”

Lit., “unfeeling, like fat.”

Or “I wait for your word.”

Or “saying.”

Or possibly, “with lies.”

Or “study.”

Or “My soul pines for.”

Or “I wait for your word.”

That is, all his creative works.

Lit., “is very broad.”

Or “study.”

Or “study.”

Lit., “the voluntary offerings of my mouth.”

Or “My soul is in my hand constantly.”

Or “my eternal heritage.”

Lit., “have inclined my heart.”

Or “men of divided heart.”

Or “I wait for your word.”

Or “according to your saying.”

Or “be put to shame.”

Lit., “flesh.”

Or “saying.”

Or “refined.”

Or “order.”

Or “my soul observes.”

Lit., “pant.”

Or “Make my steps steady.”

Lit., “Redeem.”

Or “smile.”

Or “in the morning twilight.”

Or “I wait for your words.”

Or “study.”

Or “in obscene conduct.”

Or “Conduct my legal case.”

Or “saying.”

Or “For them there is no stumbling block.”

Or “My soul keeps.”

Or “according to your saying.”

Or “my soul.”

^ (Pss. 120:0-134:3) A Song of the Ascents.* 120 I called to Jehovah in my distress, And he answered me.  2 O Jehovah, rescue me* from lying lips And from the deceitful tongue.  3 What will He do to you, and how will He punish you,* You deceitful tongue?  4 With sharp arrows of a warrior And burning coals of broomwood.  5 Woe to me, for I have lived as a foreigner in Meʹshech! I have been dwelling among the tents of Keʹdar.  6 I have* been dwelling far too long With those who hate peace.  7 I am for peace, but when I speak, They are for war.

A Song of the Ascents. 121 I raise my eyes to the mountains. From where will my help come?  2 My help comes from Jehovah, The Maker of heaven and earth.  3 He will never allow your foot to slip.* The One guarding you will never be drowsy.  4 Look! He will never be drowsy nor go to sleep, The One guarding Israel.  5 Jehovah is guarding you. Jehovah is the shade at your right hand.  6 By day the sun will not strike you, Nor the moon by night.  7 Jehovah will guard you against all harm. He will guard your life.*  8 Jehovah will guard you in all you do* From now on and forever.

A Song of the Ascents. Of David. 122 I rejoiced when they said to me: “Let us go to the house of Jehovah.”  2 And now our feet are standing Within your gates, O Jerusalem.  3 Jerusalem is built as a city That is joined together as one.  4 The tribes have gone up to it, The tribes of Jah,* According to the reminder to Israel, To give thanks to the name of Jehovah.  5 For thrones for judgment were set up there, Thrones of the house of David.  6 Ask for the peace of Jerusalem. Those who love you, O city, will be secure.  7 May peace continue within your ramparts,* Security within your fortified towers.  8 For the sake of my brothers and my companions I will say: “May there be peace within you.”  9 For the sake of the house of Jehovah our God, I will seek good for you.

A Song of the Ascents. 123 To you I raise my eyes, You who are enthroned in the heavens.  2 As the eyes of servants look to the hand of their master, And the eyes of a servant girl to the hand of her mistress, So our eyes look to Jehovah our God Until he shows us favor.  3 Show us favor, O Jehovah, show us favor, For we have had our full share of contempt.  4 We have had our full share of* ridicule from the self-assured And the contempt of the arrogant.

A Song of the Ascents. Of David. 124 “If Jehovah had not been with us” —Let Israel now say—  2 “If Jehovah had not been with us When men rose up to attack us,  3 Then they would have swallowed us up alive When their anger was burning against us.  4 Then the waters would have washed us away, The torrent would have swept over us.*  5 The raging waters would have overwhelmed us.*  6 May Jehovah be praised, For he has not given us as prey to their teeth.  7 We are* like a bird that escaped From the hunter’s trap; The trap was broken, And we escaped.  8 Our help is in the name of Jehovah, The Maker of heaven and earth.”

A Song of the Ascents. 125 Those who trust in Jehovah Are like Mount Zion, which cannot be shaken But endures forever.  2 Just as mountains surround Jerusalem, So Jehovah surrounds his people From now on and forever.  3 The scepter of wickedness will not remain upon the land allotted to the righteous, So that the righteous do not turn to doing* what is wrong.  4 Do good, O Jehovah, to those who are good, To those who are upright in heart.  5 As for those who turn aside to their crooked ways, Jehovah will remove them along with the wrongdoers. May there be peace upon Israel.

A Song of the Ascents. 126 When Jehovah gathered back the captives of Zion, We thought we were dreaming.  2 At that time our mouth was filled with laughter And our tongue with a joyful shout. At that time they said among the nations: “Jehovah has done great things for them.”  3 Jehovah has done great things for us, And we are overjoyed.  4 Do gather back* our captives, O Jehovah, Like streams in the Negʹeb.*  5 Those sowing seed with tears Will reap with a joyful shout.  6 The one who does go out, though weeping, Carrying his bag of seed, Will surely return with a joyful shout, Carrying in his sheaves.

A Song of the Ascents. Of Solomon. 127 Unless Jehovah builds the house, It is in vain that its builders work hard on it. Unless Jehovah guards the city, It is in vain that the guard stays awake.  2 It is in vain that you rise up early, That you stay up late, That you toil for your food, Since he provides for his loved ones while giving them sleep.  3 Look! Sons* are an inheritance from Jehovah; The fruit of the womb is a reward.  4 Like arrows in the hand of a mighty man, So are the sons of one’s youth.  5 Happy is the man who fills his quiver with them. They will not be put to shame, For they will speak with enemies in the city gate.

A Song of the Ascents. 128 Happy is everyone who fears Jehovah, Who walks in His ways.  2 You will eat what your hands worked hard to produce. You will be happy and will enjoy prosperity.  3 Your wife will be like a fruitful vine within your house; Your sons will be like shoots of an olive tree around your table.  4 Look! That is how the man who fears Jehovah Will be blessed.  5 Jehovah will bless you from Zion. May you see Jerusalem prosper all the days of your life  6 And see the sons of your sons. May there be peace upon Israel.

A Song of the Ascents. 129 “Since my youth they have constantly attacked me” —Let Israel now say—  2 “Since my youth they have constantly attacked me; But they have not defeated me.  3 Plowmen have plowed across my back; They have made their furrows long.”  4 But Jehovah is righteous; He has cut up the ropes of the wicked.  5 They will be put to shame and will retreat in disgrace, All those who hate Zion.  6 They will become like grass on the rooftops That withers before it is pulled up,  7 That cannot fill the reaper’s hand Nor the arms of the one gathering sheaves.  8 Those passing by will not say: “May the blessing of Jehovah be upon you; We bless you in the name of Jehovah.”

A Song of the Ascents. 130 From the depths I call to you, O Jehovah.  2 O Jehovah, hear my voice. May your ears pay attention to my pleas for help.  3 If errors were what you watch,* O Jah,* Then who, O Jehovah, could stand?  4 For with you there is true forgiveness, So that you may be held in awe.*  5 I hope in Jehovah, my whole being* hopes in him; I wait for his word.  6 I eagerly wait* for Jehovah, More than watchmen wait for the morning, Yes, more than watchmen wait for the morning.  7 Let Israel keep waiting for Jehovah, For Jehovah is loyal in his love, And he has great power to redeem.  8 He will redeem Israel from all their errors.

A Song of the Ascents. Of David. 131 O Jehovah, my heart is not haughty, Nor are my eyes lofty; Nor do I aspire to things too great, Or to things that are beyond me.  2 No, but I have calmed and quieted my soul* Like a weaned child with its mother; I am* contented like a weaned child.  3 Let Israel wait for Jehovah From now on and forever.

A Song of the Ascents. 132 O Jehovah, remember David And all his suffering;  2 How he swore to Jehovah, How he vowed to the Powerful One of Jacob:  3 “I will not go into my tent, my home. I will not lie upon my couch, my bed;  4 I will not allow my eyes to sleep, Nor my eyelids to slumber  5 Until I find a place for Jehovah, A fine residence* for the Powerful One of Jacob.”  6 Look! We heard about it in Ephʹra·thah; We found it in the fields of the forest.  7 Let us come into his residence;* Let us bow down at his footstool.  8 Rise up, O Jehovah, to come to your resting-place, You and the Ark of your strength.  9 May your priests be clothed with righteousness, And may your loyal ones shout joyfully. 10 For the sake of David your servant, Do not reject* your anointed one. 11 Jehovah has sworn to David; He will surely not go back on his word: “One of your offspring,* I will place on your throne. 12 If your sons keep my covenant And my reminders that I teach them, Their sons too Will sit on your throne forever.” 13 For Jehovah has chosen Zion; He has desired it for his dwelling place: 14 “This is my resting-place forever; Here I will dwell, for this is my desire. 15 I will richly bless it with provisions; I will satisfy its poor with bread. 16 Its priests I will clothe with salvation, And its loyal ones will shout joyfully. 17 There I will make the strength* of David grow. I have prepared a lamp for my anointed one. 18 I will clothe his enemies with shame, But the crown* on his head will flourish.”

A Song of the Ascents. Of David. 133 Look! How good and how pleasant it is For brothers to dwell together in unity!  2 It is like fine oil poured on the head That runs down the beard, Aaron’s beard, And runs down onto the collar of his garments.  3 It is like the dew of Herʹmon That descends on the mountains of Zion. That is where Jehovah decreed his blessing —Life everlasting.

A Song of the Ascents. 134 Praise Jehovah, All you servants of Jehovah, You who stand in the house of Jehovah during the nights.  2 Raise your hands in holiness* And praise Jehovah.  3 May Jehovah, the Maker of heaven and earth, Bless you from Zion.

See Glossary.

Or “my soul.”

Lit., “and what will He add to you?”

Or “My soul has.”

Or “totter.”

Or “soul.”

Lit., “your going out and your coming in.”

“Jah” is a shortened form of the name Jehovah.

Or “fortified walls.”

Or “Our soul has had more than enough.”

Or “our soul.”

Or “our soul.”

Or “Our soul is.”

Or “turn their hands to.”

Or “restore.”

Or “wadis in the south.”

Or “Children.”

Or “keep track of.”

“Jah” is a shortened form of the name Jehovah.

Lit., “be feared.”

Or “my soul.”

Or “My soul eagerly waits.”

Or “myself.” See Glossary.

Or “My soul is.”

Or “A grand tabernacle.”

Or “his grand tabernacle.”

Lit., “turn back the face of.”

Lit., “of the fruit of your womb.”

Lit., “horn.”

Or “diadem.”

Or possibly, “in the sanctuary.”

^ (Pss. 127:1-129:8) Unless Jehovah builds the house, It is in vain that its builders work hard on it. Unless Jehovah guards the city, It is in vain that the guard stays awake.  2 It is in vain that you rise up early, That you stay up late, That you toil for your food, Since he provides for his loved ones while giving them sleep.  3 Look! Sons* are an inheritance from Jehovah; The fruit of the womb is a reward.  4 Like arrows in the hand of a mighty man, So are the sons of one’s youth.  5 Happy is the man who fills his quiver with them. They will not be put to shame, For they will speak with enemies in the city gate.

A Song of the Ascents. 128 Happy is everyone who fears Jehovah, Who walks in His ways.  2 You will eat what your hands worked hard to produce. You will be happy and will enjoy prosperity.  3 Your wife will be like a fruitful vine within your house; Your sons will be like shoots of an olive tree around your table.  4 Look! That is how the man who fears Jehovah Will be blessed.  5 Jehovah will bless you from Zion. May you see Jerusalem prosper all the days of your life  6 And see the sons of your sons. May there be peace upon Israel.

A Song of the Ascents. 129 “Since my youth they have constantly attacked me” —Let Israel now say—  2 “Since my youth they have constantly attacked me; But they have not defeated me.  3 Plowmen have plowed across my back; They have made their furrows long.”  4 But Jehovah is righteous; He has cut up the ropes of the wicked.  5 They will be put to shame and will retreat in disgrace, All those who hate Zion.  6 They will become like grass on the rooftops That withers before it is pulled up,  7 That cannot fill the reaper’s hand Nor the arms of the one gathering sheaves.  8 Those passing by will not say: “May the blessing of Jehovah be upon you; We bless you in the name of Jehovah.”

Or “Children.”

^ ***sn song 33 Fear Them Not!***

Song 33

Fear Them Not!

(Matthew 10:28)

1. Ever onward, O my people,

Let the Kingdom tidings go.

Tremble not before our foe.

Let all lovers of truth know

That my reigning Son, Christ Jesus,

To the earth has cast the foe,

Soon to bind the Devil, Satan,

Letting all his victims go.

(CHORUS)

Fear them not, O my beloved,

Though their boasting threats may fly.

I will keep my faithful servant

As the apple of my eye.

2. Even though your foes are many,

Though they threaten and revile,

Though they flatter and they smile,

To mislead and to beguile.

Fear them not, my faithful warriors,

Nor their persecution’s heat,

For I will preserve the faithful

Till the vict’ry is complete.

(CHORUS)

Fear them not, O my beloved,

Though their boasting threats may fly.

I will keep my faithful servant

As the apple of my eye.

3. Never fear you are forgotten;

I am still your strength and shield.

Though you die upon the field,

Even death to me will yield.

Fear them not who kill the body

But cannot destroy the soul.

To the end may you be faithful;

I will bring you to your goal!

(CHORUS)

Fear them not, O my beloved,

Though their boasting threats may fly.

I will keep my faithful servant

As the apple of my eye.

(See also [Deut. 32:10;][Neh. 4:14;][Ps. 59:1;][83:2, 3].)

^ (Matt. 10:28) And do not become fearful of those who kill the body but cannot kill the soul;* rather, fear him who can destroy both soul and body in Ge·henʹna.*

Or “life,” that is, life prospects.

See Glossary.

^ (Deut. 32:10) He found him in a wilderness land And in an empty, howling desert. He protectively encircled him, took care of him, And safeguarded him as the pupil of his eye.

^ (Neh. 4:14) When I saw their fear, I immediately rose and said to the nobles and the deputy rulers and the rest of the people: “Do not be afraid of them. Remember Jehovah, who is great and awe-inspiring; and fight for your brothers, your sons and daughters, your wives and homes.”

^ (Ps. 59:1) Rescue me from my enemies, O my God; Protect me from those rising up against me.

^ (Ps. 83:2, 3) For look! your enemies are in an uproar; Those who hate you act arrogantly.*  3 With cunning they secretly plot against your people; They conspire against your treasured ones.*

Or “raise their heads.”

Lit., “concealed ones.”

^ ***w04 12/15 p. 12 Jehovah Is Our Helper***

An Unfailing Source of Help

3. To which mountains may the psalmist have raised his eyes, and why?

3 The psalmist began by pointing to Jehovah’s creatorship as a basis for confidence: “I shall raise my eyes to the mountains. From where will my help come? My help is from Jehovah, the Maker of heaven and earth.” (Psalm 121:1, 2) The psalmist did not raise his eyes to just any mountain. When these words were recorded, Jehovah’s temple was situated in Jerusalem. That city, located high in the mountains of Judah, was Jehovah’s figurative place of dwelling. ([Psalm 135:21]) The psalmist may have raised his eyes to the mountains of Jerusalem on which Jehovah’s temple was built, confidently looking to Jehovah for help. Why was the psalmist so sure that Jehovah could help him? Because He is “the Maker of heaven and earth.” In effect, the psalmist was saying, ‘Surely there is nothing that can prevent the all-powerful Creator from helping me!’—[Isaiah 40:26].

^ par. 3 (Ps. 121:1, 2) I raise my eyes to the mountains. From where will my help come?  2 My help comes from Jehovah, The Maker of heaven and earth.

^ par. 3 (Ps. 135:21) May Jehovah be praised from Zion, The One residing in Jerusalem. Praise Jah!

^ par. 3 (Isa. 40:26) “Lift up your eyes to heaven and see. Who has created these things? It is the One who brings out their army by number; He calls them all by name. Because of his vast dynamic energy and his awe-inspiring power, Not one of them is missing.

^ ***w04 12/15 pp. 12-13 Jehovah Is Our Helper***

4. How did the psalmist show that Jehovah is ever alert to the needs of his people, and why is that a comforting thought?

4 The psalmist next explained that Jehovah is ever alert to the needs of his servants: “He cannot possibly allow your foot to totter. The One guarding you cannot possibly be drowsy. Look! He will not be drowsy nor go to sleep, he that is guarding Israel.” (Psalm 121:3, 4) It is not possible for God to allow those trusting in him “to totter” or to experience a fall from which they cannot recover. (Proverbs 24:16) Why not? Because Jehovah is like a wide-awake shepherd guarding his sheep. Is that not a comforting thought? Not for a moment will he close his eyes to the needs of his people. Day and night they are the objects of his vigilance.

^ par. 4 (Ps. 121:3, 4) He will never allow your foot to slip.* The One guarding you will never be drowsy.  4 Look! He will never be drowsy nor go to sleep, The One guarding Israel.

Or “totter.”

^ par. 4 (Prov. 24:16) For the righteous one may fall seven times, and he will get up again, But the wicked will be made to stumble by calamity.

^ ***w04 12/15 p. 13 Jehovah Is Our Helper***

5. Why is Jehovah said to be at the “right hand”?

5 Confident that Jehovah is the loyal Protector of his people, the psalmist wrote: “Jehovah is guarding you. Jehovah is your shade on your right hand. By day the sun itself will not strike you, nor the moon by night.” (Psalm 121:5, 6) For a traveler on foot in the Middle East, a place of shade would provide welcome protection from the blazing sun. Jehovah is like a shade to his people, protecting them from the scorching heat of calamity. Note that Jehovah is said to be at the “right hand.” In ancient warfare, the soldier’s right hand was to some extent unprotected by the shield, which was held in the left hand. A loyal friend might provide protection by standing and fighting at the soldier’s right. Like such a friend, Jehovah loyally stands beside his worshipers, ever ready to help them.

6, 7. (a) How does the psalmist assure us that Jehovah will never stop helping his people? (b) Why can we share the psalmist’s confidence?

6 Will Jehovah ever stop helping his people? The very notion is inconceivable. The psalmist concluded: “Jehovah himself will guard you against all calamity. He will guard your soul. Jehovah himself will guard your going out and your coming in from now on and to time indefinite.” (Psalm 121:7, 8) Note that the writer shifted the emphasis from the present to the future. Earlier, in Ps 121 verse 5, the psalmist said: “Jehovah is guarding you.” But in these verses, the psalmist wrote: “Jehovah himself will guard you.” True worshipers are thus assured that Jehovah’s help will extend into the future. No matter where they go, no matter what calamity they face, they will never be outside the reach of his helping hand.—Proverbs 12:21.

7 Indeed, the writer of [Psalm 121] was confident that the almighty Creator watches over his servants with the gentleness of a caring shepherd and the vigilance of an alert guard. We have every reason to share the psalmist’s confidence, for Jehovah does not change. ([Malachi 3:6]) Does this mean that we will always receive physical protection? No, but as long as we look to him as our Helper, he will safeguard us against all things that could bring us spiritual harm. It is only natural to ask, ‘How does Jehovah help us?’ Let us examine four ways in which he does so. In this article, we will discuss how he aided his servants in Bible times. In the next article, we will consider how he helps his people today.

^ par. 5 (Ps. 121:5, 6) Jehovah is guarding you. Jehovah is the shade at your right hand.  6 By day the sun will not strike you, Nor the moon by night.

^ par. 6 (Ps. 121:7, 8) Jehovah will guard you against all harm. He will guard your life.*  8 Jehovah will guard you in all you do* From now on and forever.

Or “soul.”

Lit., “your going out and your coming in.”

^ par. 6 (Ps. 121:5) Jehovah is guarding you. Jehovah is the shade at your right hand.

^ par. 6 (Prov. 12:21) No harm will befall the righteous one, But the wicked will have their fill of calamity.

^ par. 7 (Ps. 121:0-8) A Song of the Ascents. 121 I raise my eyes to the mountains. From where will my help come?  2 My help comes from Jehovah, The Maker of heaven and earth.  3 He will never allow your foot to slip.* The One guarding you will never be drowsy.  4 Look! He will never be drowsy nor go to sleep, The One guarding Israel.  5 Jehovah is guarding you. Jehovah is the shade at your right hand.  6 By day the sun will not strike you, Nor the moon by night.  7 Jehovah will guard you against all harm. He will guard your life.*  8 Jehovah will guard you in all you do* From now on and forever.

Or “totter.”

Or “soul.”

Lit., “your going out and your coming in.”

^ par. 7 (Mal. 3:6) “For I am Jehovah; I do not change.* And you are sons of Jacob; you have not yet come to your finish.

Or “I have not changed.”

^ ***w06 9/1 p. 15 par. 4 Highlights From Book Five of Psalms***

123:2—What is the point of the illustration about the eyes of servants? Servants and maidservants look toward the hand of a master or a mistress for two reasons: to determine his or her wishes and to receive protection and life’s necessities. Similarly, we look to Jehovah in order to discern his will and to gain his favor.

^ par. 4 (Ps. 123:2) As the eyes of servants look to the hand of their master, And the eyes of a servant girl to the hand of her mistress, So our eyes look to Jehovah our God Until he shows us favor.

^ ***w06 9/1 p. 16 par. 3 Highlights From Book Five of Psalms***

133:1-3. The unity of Jehovah’s people is soothing, wholesome, and refreshing. We should not disrupt it by engaging in faultfinding, quarreling, or complaining.

^ par. 3 (Ps. 133:1-3) Look! How good and how pleasant it is For brothers to dwell together in unity!  2 It is like fine oil poured on the head That runs down the beard, Aaron’s beard, And runs down onto the collar of his garments.  3 It is like the dew of Herʹmon That descends on the mountains of Zion. That is where Jehovah decreed his blessing —Life everlasting.

^ ***fg lesson 8***

Satan claimed that no one would serve Jehovah out of unselfish love. Would you like to disprove that lie? You can! God’s patience allows all of us to show whether we favor rule by God or rule by man. We indicate our choice by the way we live.—Read Job 1:8-12; Proverbs 27:11.

^ par. 6 (Job 1:8-12) And Jehovah said to Satan: “Have you taken note of* my servant Job? There is no one like him on the earth. He is an upright man of integrity,* fearing God and shunning what is bad.” 9 At that Satan answered Jehovah: “Is it for nothing that Job has feared God? 10 Have you not put up a protective hedge around him and his house and everything he has? You have blessed the work of his hands, and his livestock has spread out in the land. 11 But, for a change, stretch out your hand and strike everything he has, and he will surely curse you to your very face.” 12 Then Jehovah said to Satan: “Look! Everything that he has is in your hand.* Only do not lay your hand on the man himself!” So Satan went out from the presence* of Jehovah.

Lit., “set your heart upon.”

Or “a blameless and upright man.”

Or “under your control.”

Lit., “face.”

^ par. 6 (Prov. 27:11) Be wise, my son, and make my heart rejoice, So that I can make a reply to him who taunts me.

^ ***sn song 114 God’s Own Book—A Treasure***

Song 114

God’s Own Book—A Treasure

([Proverbs 2:1])

1. There is a book that by its many pages,

Brings peace and joy and hope to humankind.

Its wondrous thoughts are charged with such great power;

It brings life to the “dead,” sight to the “blind.”

That precious book is God’s own Holy Bible.

Its words were penned by men whom God inspired,

By men who truly loved their God Jehovah,

And by his holy spirit they were fired.

2. They wrote a record true of God’s creations,

How by his might this universe appeared.

They also told how man at first was sinless

But how his Paradise then disappeared.

They further told about a certain angel

Who challenged God and spurned his sov’reignty.

That challenge led to sin and man’s great sorrow,

But soon will come Jehovah’s victory.

3. Today we live in times of joy unbounded.

God’s Kingdom now is here with Christ as Lord.

This is the day Jehovah grants salvation

To all who come to him in full accord.

Within his book are found these cheerful tidings;

A sacred banquet feast on which to feed.

It offers peace beyond all human thinking;

This Living Treasure beckons all to read.

(See also [2 Tim. 3:16;][2 Pet. 1:21].)

^ (Prov. 2:1) My son, if you accept my sayings And treasure up my commandments,

^ (2 Tim. 3:16) All Scripture is inspired of God and beneficial for teaching, for reproving, for setting things straight,* for disciplining in righteousness,

Or “correcting.”

^ (2 Pet. 1:21) For prophecy was at no time brought by man’s will, but men spoke from God as they were moved* by holy spirit.

Lit., “carried along; borne along.”

^ ***ia pp. 205-208 Conclusion***

Conclusion

“Be imitators of those who through faith and patience inherit the promises.”—[HEBREWS 6:12].

1, 2. Why is it vital that we build faith now? Illustrate.

FAITH. It is a beautiful word, one that names a very appealing quality. However, when we come across that word, we would do well to think of another one: “Urgent!” After all, if we do not have faith, we urgently need to acquire it. And if we do have faith, we urgently need to protect and nourish it. Why?

2 Imagine that you are traversing a vast desert. You are in critical need of water. When you find some, you have to protect it from the sun. Then you need to be able to replenish your supply so that it will last you until you arrive at your destination. Today, we all live in a spiritual desert, a world where genuine faith—like that water—is rare and tends to evaporate quickly unless it is protected and replenished. Our need is pressing; just as we cannot live without water, we cannot survive spiritually without faith.—[Rom. 1:17].

3. What has Jehovah provided to help us build faith, and what are two things that we need to remember to do?

3 Jehovah knows how urgently we need faith, and he knows how hard it is to build and maintain faith today. No doubt, that is why he has provided examples for us to imitate. Jehovah inspired the apostle Paul to write: “Be imitators of those who through faith and patience inherit the promises.” ([Heb. 6:12]) And that is why Jehovah’s organization has encouraged us to work hard to imitate the examples of faithful men and women, such as those we have considered in these pages. What, though, should we do now? Let us remember two things: (1) We need to keep strengthening our faith; (2) we need to keep our hope clearly in mind.

4. How has Satan proved to be an enemy of faith, yet why should we not despair?

4 Keep strengthening your faith. Faith has a great enemy—Satan. The ruler of the world has turned this system of things into a kind of desert that is hostile to faith. He is far stronger than we are. Should we despair of developing and strengthening our faith? Never! Jehovah is the great Friend of all who seek genuine faith. He assures us that with Him on our side, we can oppose the Devil and even send him fleeing from us! ([Jas. 4:7]) We oppose him by taking time each day to strengthen our faith and build it up. How?

5. How did the Bible’s faithful men and women acquire their faith? Explain.

5 As we have seen, the Bible’s men and women of faith were not born faithful. They became living proof that faith is a product of Jehovah’s holy spirit. (Gal. 5:22, 23) They prayed for help, and Jehovah kept strengthening their faith as a result. Let us do as they did, never forgetting that Jehovah gives his spirit generously to those who ask for it and who work in harmony with their prayers. ([Luke 11:13]) Is there more that we can do?

6. How can we gain the most benefit from our study of Bible accounts?

6 In this book, we have discussed only a few examples of outstanding faith. There are many, many others! (Read Hebrews 11:32.) Each one—in its own way—offers a rich field for prayerful, heartfelt study. If we merely rush through Bible accounts about people of faith, we will not firmly establish our own faith. To benefit fully from our reading, we need to spend time digging into the context and the background of Bible accounts. If we always remember that those imperfect men and women had “feelings like ours,” their examples will become more real to us. ([Jas. 5:17]) With empathy, we can imagine how they might have felt as they faced challenges and problems similar to our own.

7-9. (a) How might some of the men and women of faith in Bible times have felt about worshipping Jehovah in the way that we do today? (b) Why should we strengthen our faith by actions?

7 We also fortify our faith through our actions. After all, “faith without works is dead.” ([Jas. 2:26]) Just imagine how the men and women we have discussed would rejoice if they were assigned to do the kind of work that Jehovah has asked us to do today!

8 For example, what if Abraham had been told that he could worship Jehovah, not at crude altars of stone erected in the wilderness, but among organized groups of fellow worshippers in pleasant Kingdom Halls and at large conventions, where the promises that he saw only “afar off” are discussed and explained in glorious detail? (Read Hebrews 11:13.) And what if Elijah had been told that his work involved, not executing wicked Baal prophets while he was trying to serve Jehovah under the rule of a wicked apostate king, but peacefully visiting people to deliver a message of comfort and hope? Really, would not the Bible’s men and women of faith have jumped at the chance to worship Jehovah as we do today?

9 So let us keep strengthening our faith by actions. As we do so, we will be making practical application of the examples of men and women of faith found in God’s inspired Word. As mentioned in the Introduction, we will come to feel ever closer to them as friends. However, such friendships may soon become far more substantial.

10. What joy will we have in Paradise?

10 Keep your hope clearly in mind. Faithful men and women have always drawn strength from their God-given hope. Do you? For example, imagine the joy of meeting faithful servants of God as they return to life in the “resurrection of . . . the righteous.” (Read Acts 24:15.) What are some questions that you would like to ask them?

11, 12. In the new world, what questions might you ask of (a) Abel? (b) Noah? (c) Abraham? (d) Ruth? (e) Abigail? (f) Esther?

11 When you meet Abel, will you be eager to ask him what his parents were like? Or you might ask: “Did you ever speak to those cherubs guarding the way to Eden? Did they answer?” What about Noah? You might ask him: “Were you ever frightened of the Nephilim? How did you care for all those animals during that year in the ark?” If you meet Abraham, you might ask: “Did you have any contact with Shem? Who taught you about Jehovah? Was it hard to leave Ur?”

12 Likewise, consider some questions you might want to ask the faithful women who are resurrected. “Ruth, what moved you to become a worshipper of Jehovah?” “Abigail, were you afraid to tell Nabal about how you had helped David?” “Esther, what happened to you and Mordecai after the story in the Bible ended?”

13. (a) What kind of questions might resurrected ones have for you? (b) How do you feel about the prospect of meeting faithful men and women of ancient times?

13 Of course, those faithful men and women may be brimming with questions for you too. What a thrill to tell them about the climactic last days and how Jehovah blessed his people during hard times! No doubt they will be deeply moved to learn how Jehovah fulfilled all his promises. In those days to come, it will no longer be a challenge to make God’s loyal servants in the Bible record come to life in our minds. They will be there with us, in Paradise! So keep doing everything you can now to make those people real to you. Keep imitating their faith. May you enjoy serving Jehovah along with them as your dear friends forever!

^ (Heb. 6:12) so that you may not become sluggish, but be imitators of those who through faith and patience inherit the promises.

^ par. 2 (Rom. 1:17) For in it God’s righteousness is being revealed by faith and for faith, just as it is written: “But the righteous one will live by reason of faith.”

^ par. 3 (Heb. 6:12) so that you may not become sluggish, but be imitators of those who through faith and patience inherit the promises.

^ par. 4 (Jas. 4:7) Therefore, subject yourselves to God; but oppose the Devil, and he will flee from you.

^ par. 5 (Gal. 5:22, 23) On the other hand, the fruitage of the spirit is love, joy, peace, patience,* kindness, goodness, faith, 23 mildness, self-control. Against such things there is no law.

Or “long-suffering.”

^ par. 5 (Luke 11:13) Therefore, if you, although being wicked, know how to give good gifts to your children, how much more so will the Father in heaven give holy spirit to those asking him!”

^ par. 6 (Heb. 11:32) And what more will I say? For time will fail me if I go on to relate about Gidʹe·on, Baʹrak, Samson, Jephʹthah, David, as well as Samuel and the other prophets.

^ par. 6 (Jas. 5:17) E·liʹjah was a man with feelings like ours, and yet when he prayed earnestly for it not to rain, it did not rain on the land for three years and six months.

^ par. 7 (Jas. 2:26) Indeed, just as the body without spirit* is dead, so also faith without works is dead.

Or “breath.”

^ par. 8 (Heb. 11:13) In faith all of these died, although they did not receive the fulfillment of the promises; but they saw them from a distance and welcomed them and publicly declared that they were strangers and temporary residents in the land.

^ par. 10 (Acts 24:15) And I have hope toward God, which hope these men also look forward to, that there is going to be a resurrection of both the righteous and the unrighteous.

^ ***sn song 119 Come! Be Refreshed***

Song 119

Come! Be Refreshed

(Hebrews 10:24, 25)

1. We live in a world that is wayward and lost;

The way of our God is not known.

We need sure direction to safeguard our steps;

We cannot succeed on our own.

Our meetings refresh us and brighten our hope;

They help us build faith in our God.

They move us with words that incite to fine deeds,

They give us the strength to go on.

We’ll never forsake what Jehovah commands;

His will is what we want to do.

Our meetings instruct us in ways that are right;

Our love for the truth they renew.

2. Jehovah is keenly aware of our needs;

His counsel by us should be heard.

To buy out the time for occasions to meet

Shows wisdom and trust in his Word.

By wholesome instruction from God-fearing men,

We learn how our faith can be shown.

With loving support from our fam’ly of faith,

We know that we’re never alone.

So as we look forward to much better times,

We’ll meet with the ones whom we love.

And here at these meetings we’ll learn how to live

With wisdom that comes from above.

(See also [Ps. 37:18;][140:1;][Prov. 18:1;][Eph. 5:16;][Jas. 3:17].)

^ (Heb. 10:24, 25) And let us consider* one another so as to incite* to love and fine works, 25 not forsaking our meeting together, as some have the custom, but encouraging one another, and all the more so as you see the day drawing near.

Or “be concerned about; pay attention to.”

Or “motivate; stir up.”

^ (Ps. 37:18) Jehovah is aware of what the blameless go through,* And their inheritance will last forever.

Lit., “the days of the blameless.”

^ (Ps. 140:1) Rescue me, O Jehovah, from evil men; Protect me from violent men,

^ (Prov. 18:1) Whoever isolates himself pursues his own selfish desires; He rejects* all practical wisdom.

Or “shows contempt for.”

^ (Eph. 5:16) making the best use of your time,* because the days are wicked.

Lit., “buying out the appointed time.”

^ (Jas. 3:17) But the wisdom from above is first of all pure, then peaceable, reasonable, ready to obey, full of mercy and good fruits, impartial, not hypocritical.

^ (Pss. 135:1-141:10) Praise Jah!* Praise the name of Jehovah; Offer praise, you servants of Jehovah,  2 You who are standing in the house of Jehovah, In the courtyards of the house of our God.  3 Praise Jah, for Jehovah is good. Sing praises* to his name, for it is pleasant.  4 For Jah has chosen Jacob for himself, Israel for his special property.*  5 For I well know that Jehovah is great; Our Lord is greater than all other gods.  6 Jehovah does everything he pleases to do In heaven and on earth, in the seas and all the depths.  7 He causes clouds* to ascend from the ends of the earth; He makes lightning for* the rain; He brings the wind out of his storehouses.  8 He struck down the firstborn of Egypt, Both man and beast.  9 He sent signs and miracles among you, O Egypt, Against Pharʹaoh and all his servants. 10 He struck down many nations And killed mighty kings 11 —Siʹhon the king of the Amʹor·ites, Og the king of Baʹshan, And all the kingdoms of Caʹnaan. 12 He gave their land as an inheritance, An inheritance to Israel his people. 13 O Jehovah, your name endures forever. O Jehovah, your fame* endures for all generations. 14 For Jehovah will defend* his people, And he will feel compassion* for his servants. 15 The idols of the nations are silver and gold, The work of human hands. 16 A mouth they have, but they cannot speak; Eyes, but they cannot see; 17 Ears they have, but they cannot hear. There is no breath in their mouth. 18 The people who make them will become just like them, As will all those who trust in them. 19 O house of Israel, praise Jehovah. O house of Aaron, praise Jehovah. 20 O house of Leʹvi, praise Jehovah. You who fear Jehovah, praise Jehovah. 21 May Jehovah be praised from Zion, The One residing in Jerusalem. Praise Jah!

136 Give thanks to Jehovah, for he is good; His loyal love endures forever.  2 Give thanks to the God of gods, For his loyal love endures forever.  3 Give thanks to the Lord of lords, For his loyal love endures forever.  4 He alone does great wonders, For his loyal love endures forever.  5 He skillfully made* the heavens, For his loyal love endures forever.  6 He spread out the earth over the waters, For his loyal love endures forever.  7 He made the great lights, For his loyal love endures forever,  8 The sun to rule over the day, For his loyal love endures forever,  9 The moon and the stars to rule over the night, For his loyal love endures forever. 10 He struck down Egypt’s firstborn, For his loyal love endures forever. 11 He brought Israel out from their midst, For his loyal love endures forever, 12 With a mighty hand and an outstretched arm, For his loyal love endures forever. 13 He split the Red Sea in two,* For his loyal love endures forever. 14 He caused Israel to pass through the middle of it, For his loyal love endures forever. 15 He shook off Pharʹaoh and his army into the Red Sea, For his loyal love endures forever. 16 He led his people through the wilderness, For his loyal love endures forever. 17 He struck down great kings, For his loyal love endures forever. 18 He killed mighty kings, For his loyal love endures forever, 19 Siʹhon the king of the Amʹor·ites, For his loyal love endures forever, 20 And Og the king of Baʹshan, For his loyal love endures forever. 21 He gave their land as an inheritance, For his loyal love endures forever, 22 An inheritance to Israel his servant, For his loyal love endures forever. 23 He remembered us when we were low, For his loyal love endures forever. 24 He kept rescuing us from our adversaries, For his loyal love endures forever. 25 He gives food to every living thing,* For his loyal love endures forever. 26 Give thanks to the God of the heavens, For his loyal love endures forever.

137 By the rivers of Babylon, there we sat. We wept when we remembered Zion.  2 Upon the poplar trees in her* midst, We hung our harps.  3 For there our captors asked us for a song, Those mocking us wanted amusement: “Sing for us one of the songs of Zion.”  4 How can we sing the song of Jehovah On foreign soil?  5 If I should forget you, O Jerusalem, Let my right hand be forgetful.*  6 Let my tongue stick to my palate If I do not remember you, If I do not place Jerusalem above My greatest reasons for rejoicing.  7 Remember, O Jehovah, What the Eʹdom·ites said on the day Jerusalem fell: “Tear it down! Tear it down to its foundations!”  8 O daughter of Babylon, who is soon to be devastated, Happy will be the one who rewards you With the treatment you inflicted on us.  9 Happy will be the one who seizes your children And dashes them against the rocks.

Of David. 138 I will praise you with all my heart. In the face of other gods, I will sing praises.*  2 I will bow down toward your holy temple,* And I will praise your name Because of your loyal love and your faithfulness. For you have magnified your saying and your name above everything else.*  3 On the day I called, you answered me; You made me bold* and strong.  4 All the kings of the earth will praise you, O Jehovah, For they will have heard the promises you have spoken.  5 They will sing about the ways of Jehovah, For the glory of Jehovah is great.  6 Though Jehovah is high, he takes note of the humble, But the haughty he knows only from a distance.  7 Even when I walk in the midst of danger, you will preserve me alive. You stretch out your hand against the anger of my enemies; Your right hand will save me.  8 Jehovah will accomplish all things in my behalf. O Jehovah, your loyal love endures forever; Do not forsake the works of your hands.

For the director. Of David. A melody. 139 O Jehovah, you have searched through me, and you know me.  2 You know when I sit down and when I rise up. You discern my thoughts from afar.  3 You observe* me when I travel and when I lie down; You are familiar with all my ways.  4 There is not a word on my tongue, But look! O Jehovah, you already know it well.  5 Behind and before me, you surround me; And you lay your hand upon me.  6 Such knowledge is beyond my comprehension.* It is too high for me to reach.*  7 Where can I escape from your spirit, And where can I run away from your face?  8 If I were to ascend to heaven, you would be there, And if I were to make my bed in the Grave,* look! you would be there.  9 If I would fly away with the wings of the dawn To reside by the most remote sea, 10 Even there your hand would lead me And your right hand would take hold of me. 11 If I say: “Surely darkness will conceal me!” Then the night around me would become light. 12 Even the darkness would not be too dark for you, But night would be as bright as the day; Darkness is the same as light to you. 13 For you produced my kidneys; You kept me screened off* in my mother’s womb. 14 I praise you because in an awe-inspiring way I am wonderfully made. Your works are wonderful, I know* this very well. 15 My bones were not hidden from you When I was made in secret, When I was woven in the depths of the earth. 16 Your eyes even saw me as an embryo; All its parts were written in your book Regarding the days when they were formed, Before any of them existed. 17 So to me, how precious your thoughts are! O God, how vast is the sum of them! 18 If I try to count them, they outnumber the grains of sand. When I awake, I am still with you.* 19 O God, if only you would slay the wicked! Then the violent* men would depart from me, 20 Those who say things against you with evil intent;* They are your adversaries who take up your name in a worthless way. 21 Do I not hate those who hate you, O Jehovah, And loathe those who revolt against you? 22 I have nothing but hatred for them; They have become real enemies to me. 23 Search through me, O God, and know my heart. Examine me, and know my anxious* thoughts. 24 See whether there is in me any harmful way, And lead me in the way of eternity.

For the director. A melody of David. 140 Rescue me, O Jehovah, from evil men; Protect me from violent men,  2 Those who scheme evil in their hearts And stir up conflict all day long.  3 They sharpen their tongue like that of a serpent; Venom of vipers is behind their lips. (Selah)  4 Protect me, O Jehovah, from the hands of the wicked; Safeguard me from violent men, Those who scheme to trip me.  5 The haughty ones hide a trap for me; With ropes they spread out a net beside the path. They set snares for me. (Selah)  6 I say to Jehovah: “You are my God. Listen, O Jehovah, to my pleas for help.”  7 O Jehovah the Sovereign Lord, my strong Savior, You shield my head in the day of battle.  8 Do not grant, O Jehovah, the desires of the wicked. Do not let their plots succeed, so that they are not exalted. (Selah)  9 May the heads of those surrounding me Be covered with the evil spoken by their lips. 10 May burning coals rain down on them. May they be hurled into the fire, Into deep pits,* never to rise again. 11 May the slanderer find no place on the earth.* May evil pursue men of violence and strike them down. 12 I know that Jehovah will defend the lowly And give justice to the poor. 13 Surely the righteous will give thanks to your name; The upright will dwell before your face.*

A melody of David. 141 O Jehovah, I call on you. Come quickly to help me. Do pay attention when I call to you.  2 May my prayer be as incense prepared before you, My uplifted hands like the evening grain offering.  3 Station a guard for my mouth, O Jehovah, Do set a watch over the door of my lips.  4 Do not let my heart incline to anything bad, To share in vile deeds with evil men; May I never feast on their delicacies.  5 Should the righteous one strike me, it would be an act of loyal love; Should he reprove me, it would be like oil on my head, Which my head would never refuse. My prayer will continue even during their calamities.  6 Though their judges are thrown down from the cliff, The people will pay attention to my words, for they are pleasant.  7 Just as when someone plows and breaks up the soil, So our bones have been scattered at the mouth of the Grave.*  8 But my eyes look to you, O Sovereign Lord Jehovah. In you I have taken refuge. Do not take away my life.*  9 Protect me from the jaws of the trap they have laid for me, From the snares of evildoers. 10 The wicked will fall into their own nets all together While I pass by safely.

Or “Hallelujah!” “Jah” is a shortened form of the name Jehovah.

Or “Make music.”

Or “treasured possession.”

Or “vapors.”

Or possibly, “makes sluices for.”

Or “name.” Lit., “memorial.”

Or “plead the cause of.”

Or “feel regret.”

Or “made with understanding.”

Lit., “into pieces.”

Lit., “all flesh.”

Referring to Babylon.

Or possibly, “wither.”

Or possibly, “In defiance of other gods, I will make music to you.”

Or “sanctuary.”

Or possibly, “you have magnified your saying above all your name.”

Or “bold in my soul.”

Lit., “measure.”

Or “is too amazing for me.”

Or “too much for me to fathom.”

Or “Sheol,” that is, the common grave of mankind. See Glossary.

Or possibly, “wove me together.”

Or “My soul knows.”

Or possibly, “I would still be counting them.”

Or “bloodguilty.”

Or “according to their idea.”

Or “disquieting.”

Or “Into watery pits.”

Or “in the land.”

Or “in your presence.”

Or “Sheol,” that is, the common grave of mankind. See Glossary.

Or “pour out my soul.”

^ (Ps. 139:1-24) O Jehovah, you have searched through me, and you know me.  2 You know when I sit down and when I rise up. You discern my thoughts from afar.  3 You observe* me when I travel and when I lie down; You are familiar with all my ways.  4 There is not a word on my tongue, But look! O Jehovah, you already know it well.  5 Behind and before me, you surround me; And you lay your hand upon me.  6 Such knowledge is beyond my comprehension.* It is too high for me to reach.*  7 Where can I escape from your spirit, And where can I run away from your face?  8 If I were to ascend to heaven, you would be there, And if I were to make my bed in the Grave,* look! you would be there.  9 If I would fly away with the wings of the dawn To reside by the most remote sea, 10 Even there your hand would lead me And your right hand would take hold of me. 11 If I say: “Surely darkness will conceal me!” Then the night around me would become light. 12 Even the darkness would not be too dark for you, But night would be as bright as the day; Darkness is the same as light to you. 13 For you produced my kidneys; You kept me screened off* in my mother’s womb. 14 I praise you because in an awe-inspiring way I am wonderfully made. Your works are wonderful, I know* this very well. 15 My bones were not hidden from you When I was made in secret, When I was woven in the depths of the earth. 16 Your eyes even saw me as an embryo; All its parts were written in your book Regarding the days when they were formed, Before any of them existed. 17 So to me, how precious your thoughts are! O God, how vast is the sum of them! 18 If I try to count them, they outnumber the grains of sand. When I awake, I am still with you.* 19 O God, if only you would slay the wicked! Then the violent* men would depart from me, 20 Those who say things against you with evil intent;* They are your adversaries who take up your name in a worthless way. 21 Do I not hate those who hate you, O Jehovah, And loathe those who revolt against you? 22 I have nothing but hatred for them; They have become real enemies to me. 23 Search through me, O God, and know my heart. Examine me, and know my anxious* thoughts. 24 See whether there is in me any harmful way, And lead me in the way of eternity.

Lit., “measure.”

Or “is too amazing for me.”

Or “too much for me to fathom.”

Or “Sheol,” that is, the common grave of mankind. See Glossary.

Or possibly, “wove me together.”

Or “My soul knows.”

Or possibly, “I would still be counting them.”

Or “bloodguilty.”

Or “according to their idea.”

Or “disquieting.”

^ ***sn song 59 To God We Are Dedicated!***

Song 59

To God We Are Dedicated!

(Matthew 16:24)

1. To Christ, by our God, Jehovah, we have been drawn

To be his disciples from now on.

From Jehovah’s lofty throne,

Light of truth has brightly shone.

In our hearts, our faith has grown;

Ourselves we agree to disown.

(CHORUS)

To God we are dedicated; This is our choice.

In him and in Jesus we now rejoice.

2. In prayer we have come before Jehovah to say

We’ll serve him forever and obey.

It’s a joy beyond compare,

One that we most gladly share,

As Jehovah’s name we bear,

And news of his Kingdom declare.

(CHORUS)

To God we are dedicated; This is our choice.

In him and in Jesus we now rejoice.

(See also [Ps. 43:3;][107:22;][John 6:44].)

^ (Matt. 16:24) Then Jesus said to his disciples: “If anyone wants to come after me, let him disown himself and pick up his torture stake* and keep following me.

See Glossary.

^ (Ps. 43:3) Send out your light and your truth. May these lead me; May they guide me to your holy mountain and to your grand tabernacle.

^ (Ps. 107:22) Let them offer the sacrifices of thanksgiving And declare his works with a joyful cry.

^ (John 6:44) No man can come to me unless the Father, who sent me, draws him, and I will resurrect him on the last day.

^ ***w07 6/15 p. 21 We Are “Wonderfully Made”***

1. Why do many thinking people credit God for earth’s wonders?

THE natural world is filled with wonderful creations. How did they come to be? Some believe that the answer can be found without referring to an intelligent Creator. Others hold that arbitrarily ruling out a Creator limits our ability to understand nature. They believe that earth’s creatures are far too complex, too varied and, you might say, too wonderful to have originated by chance. To many people, some scientists included, the evidence shows that the universe had a wise, powerful, and benevolent Maker.*

2. What moved David to praise Jehovah?

2 King David of ancient Israel was one who was convinced that a Maker deserves praise for His wonderful creations. Although David lived long before today’s scientific era, he perceived that he was surrounded by marvelous examples of God’s creative work. David needed only to consider his own makeup to be profoundly awed by God’s creative ability. “I shall laud you because in a fear-inspiring way I am wonderfully made,” he wrote. “Your works are wonderful, as my soul is very well aware.”—[Psalm 139:14].

3, 4. Why is it important for each of us to think seriously about Jehovah’s works?

3 David gained this strong conviction by thinking seriously. Today, school curriculums and the media are replete with faith-destroying theories about man’s origin. For us to have faith like that of David, we too must think seriously. We cannot afford to let others think for us, especially on such fundamental issues as the existence and role of a Creator.

4 Moreover, contemplating Jehovah’s works strengthens our appreciation for him and gives us confidence in his promises for the future. That, in turn, can motivate us to get to know Jehovah even better and to serve him. Let us therefore consider how modern science has confirmed David’s conclusion that we are “wonderfully made.”

^ par. 2 (Ps. 139:14) I praise you because in an awe-inspiring way I am wonderfully made. Your works are wonderful, I know* this very well.

Or “My soul knows.”

^ par. 1 See the June 22, 2004, issue of Awake! published by Jehovah’s Witnesses.

^ ***w07 6/15 pp. 22-23 We Are “Wonderfully Made”***

7, 8. (a) Describe an unborn baby’s early growth. (b) In what way is a developing baby “woven in the lowest parts of the earth”?

7 “My bones were not hidden from you when I was made in secret, when I was woven in the lowest parts of the earth.” ([Psalm 139:15]) The original cell divided, and the new cells continued to divide. Soon the cells began to differentiate, or specialize, to become nerve cells, muscle cells, skin cells, and so forth. Cells of the same type grouped together to form tissues and then organs. For instance, during the third week from conception, you began to develop a skeletal system. By the time you were just seven weeks old and only about an inch [2.5 cm] long, early forms of all 206 of your adult bones were in place, although they had not yet ossified, or turned into hard bone.

8 This amazing developmental process took place within your mother’s womb, hidden from human sight as if buried deep in the earth. Indeed, much about how we develop remains unknown to man. What, for example, activated specific genes in your cells to set in motion the process of differentiation? Science may eventually find out, but as David next observed, our Maker—Jehovah—has fully understood it all along.

9, 10. How is the formation of an embryo’s parts “down in writing” in God’s “book”?

9 “Your eyes saw even the embryo of me, and in your book all its parts were down in writing, as regards the days when they were formed and there was not yet one among them.” ([Psalm 139:16]) Your first cell contained the complete plan for your entire body. This plan guided your development during your nine months in the womb before birth and then through more than two decades of growth to adulthood. During this time, your body passed through many stages, all directed by the information programmed into that original cell.

10 David had no knowledge of cells and genes, being without even a microscope. But he correctly discerned that the development of his own body attested to advance planning. David may have had some knowledge of how embryos develop, so he could reason that each step must take place according to a preexisting design and timetable. In poetic language, he described this design as being “down in writing” in God’s “book.”

11. How did we come to have our physical characteristics?

11 Today, it is known that characteristics you inherited from your parents and forebears—such as your height, facial features, eye and hair color, and thousands of other traits—were determined by your genes. Each of your cells contains tens of thousands of genes, and each gene is part of a long chain made of DNA (deoxyribonucleic acid). Building instructions for your body are “written” in the chemical structure of your personal DNA. Every time your cells divide—to make new cells or to replace old cells—your DNA passes those instructions on, thereby keeping you alive and maintaining your basic appearance. What an outstanding example of the power and wisdom of our heavenly Maker!

^ par. 7 (Ps. 139:15) My bones were not hidden from you When I was made in secret, When I was woven in the depths of the earth.

^ par. 9 (Ps. 139:16) Your eyes even saw me as an embryo; All its parts were written in your book Regarding the days when they were formed, Before any of them existed.

^ ***w07 6/15 p. 23 We Are “Wonderfully Made”***

Our Unique Mind

12. What especially sets humans apart from animals?

12 “So, to me how precious your thoughts are! O God, how much does the grand sum of them amount to! Were I to try to count them, they are more than even the grains of sand.” (Psalm 139:17, 18a) Animals too are wonderfully made, and some possess certain senses and abilities that exceed those of humans. But God gave humans mental faculties that far surpass those of any animal. “As similar as we humans are in many ways to other species, we are unique among the earth’s life forms in our ability to use language and thought,” notes one science textbook. “We are also unique in our profound curiosity about ourselves: How are we put together physically? How were we formed?” These are questions that David likewise pondered.

13. (a) How could David meditate on God’s thoughts? (b) How can we follow David’s example?

13 Most important, in contrast with animals, we are unique in our ability to contemplate God’s thoughts.* This special gift is one of the ways that we are made “in God’s image.” ([Genesis 1:27]) David made good use of this gift. He meditated on the evidence of God’s existence and the good qualities reflected in the earth around him. David also had the early books of the Holy Scriptures, which contain revelations by God about himself and his works. These inspired writings helped David to understand God’s thoughts, personality, and purpose. Meditating on the Scriptures, on creation, and on God’s dealings with him moved David to praise his Maker.

^ par. 12 (Ps. 139:17, 18) So to me, how precious your thoughts are! O God, how vast is the sum of them! 18 If I try to count them, they outnumber the grains of sand. When I awake, I am still with you.*

Or possibly, “I would still be counting them.”

^ par. 13 (Gen. 1:27) And God went on to create the man in his image, in God’s image he created him; male and female he created them.

^ par. 13 The words of David at Psalm 139:18b seem to mean that if he spent all day until he fell asleep at night counting Jehovah’s thoughts, upon awakening in the morning, he would still have more to count.

^ (Ps. 139:18) If I try to count them, they outnumber the grains of sand. When I awake, I am still with you.*

Or possibly, “I would still be counting them.”

^ ***w06 9/1 p. 16 par. 8 Highlights From Book Five of Psalms***

139:17, 18. Has knowledge of Jehovah become pleasurable to us? (Proverbs 2:10) If so, we have found an inexhaustible fountain of delight. Jehovah’s thoughts “are more than even the grains of sand.” There will always be more to learn about him.

^ par. 8 (Ps. 139:17, 18) So to me, how precious your thoughts are! O God, how vast is the sum of them! 18 If I try to count them, they outnumber the grains of sand. When I awake, I am still with you.*

Or possibly, “I would still be counting them.”

^ par. 8 (Prov. 2:10) When wisdom enters your heart And knowledge becomes pleasant to your soul,*

See Glossary.

^ ***it-1 p. 783 Exodus***

So by a spectacular display of power Jehovah exalted his name and delivered Israel. Safe on the E shore of the Red Sea, Moses led the sons of Israel in a song, while his sister Miriam, the prophetess, took a tambourine in her hand and led all the women with tambourines and in dances, responding in song to the men. ([Ex 15:1,][20, 21]) A complete separation of Israel from their foes had been effected. When they went out from Egypt they were not allowed to suffer harm from man or beast; no dog even snarled at the Israelites or moved its tongue against them. ([Ex 11:7]) While the Exodus narrative does not mention that Pharaoh personally went into the sea with his military forces and was destroyed, [Psalm 136:15] does state that Jehovah “shook off Pharaoh and his military force into the Red Sea.”

^ (Ex. 15:1) At that time Moses and the Israelites sang this song to Jehovah: “Let me sing to Jehovah, for he has become highly exalted. The horse and its rider he has hurled into the sea.

^ (Ex. 15:20, 21) Then Mirʹi·am the prophetess, Aaron’s sister, took a tambourine in her hand, and all the women followed her with tambourines and with dances. 21 Mirʹi·am sang in response to the men: “Sing to Jehovah, for he has become highly exalted. The horse and its rider he has hurled into the sea.”

^ (Ex. 11:7) But not even a dog will bark* at the Israelites, at the men or their livestock, so that you may know that Jehovah can make a distinction between the Egyptians and the Israelites.’

Lit., “sharpen its tongue.”

^ (Ps. 136:15) He shook off Pharʹaoh and his army into the Red Sea, For his loyal love endures forever.

^ ***w15 4/15 p. 31 Why Disfellowshipping Is a Loving Provision***

Love and firmness are needed to produce the desired result. “Should the righteous one strike me, it would be an act of loyal love,” said the psalmist David, and “should he reprove me, it would be like oil on my head.” ([Ps. 141:5]) To illustrate: Imagine a hiker who succumbs to exhaustion on a cold winter day. He begins to suffer from hypothermia, and he feels drowsy. If he falls asleep in the snow, he will die. While waiting for a rescue party, his companion occasionally slaps him in the face to keep him awake. The slap may sting, but it could well save his life. Similarly, David recognized that a righteous person might need to give him painful correction for his own good.

^ (Ps. 141:5) Should the righteous one strike me, it would be an act of loyal love; Should he reprove me, it would be like oil on my head, Which my head would never refuse. My prayer will continue even during their calamities.

^ ***wp16 p. 16 What Does the Bible Say?***

What Does the Bible Say?

What is the Kingdom of God?

SOME PEOPLE BELIEVE that it represents the reign of God in a person’s heart; others think that it is the product of human efforts to bring world peace and brotherhood. What do you think?

WHAT THE BIBLE SAYS

“The God of heaven will set up a kingdom that will never be destroyed. . . . It will crush and put an end to all these [human] kingdoms.” ([Daniel 2:44]) God’s Kingdom is a real government.

WHAT ELSE WE LEARN FROM THE BIBLE

The Kingdom of God rules from heaven.—Matthew 10:7;[Luke 10:9].

God uses the Kingdom to accomplish his will in heaven and on earth.—[Matthew 6:10].

When will God’s Kingdom come?

WHAT WOULD YOU SAY?

No one knows

Soon

Never

WHAT THE BIBLE SAYS

“This good news of the Kingdom will be preached in all the inhabited earth for a witness to all the nations, and then the end will come.” (Matthew 24:14) Once the good news has been fully preached, the Kingdom will come to bring the present wicked system to an end.

WHAT ELSE WE LEARN FROM THE BIBLE

No one on earth knows exactly when God’s Kingdom will come.—Matthew 24:36.

Bible prophecy shows that the Kingdom will come soon.—Matthew 24:3,[7,][12].

For more information, see chapter 8 of this book, What Does the Bible Really Teach?, published by Jehovah’s Witnesses

Also available at www.jw.org

^ (Dan. 2:44) “In the days of those kings the God of heaven will set up a kingdom that will never be destroyed. And this kingdom will not be passed on to any other people. It will crush and put an end to all these kingdoms, and it alone will stand forever,

^ (Matt. 10:7) As you go, preach, saying: ‘The Kingdom of the heavens has drawn near.’

^ (Luke 10:9) and cure the sick ones in it and tell them: ‘The Kingdom of God has come near to you.’

^ (Matt. 6:10) Let your Kingdom come. Let your will take place, as in heaven, also on earth.

^ (Matt. 24:14) And this good news of the Kingdom will be preached in all the inhabited earth for a witness to all the nations, and then the end will come.

^ (Matt. 24:36) “Concerning that day and hour nobody knows, neither the angels of the heavens nor the Son, but only the Father.

^ (Matt. 24:3) While he was sitting on the Mount of Olives, the disciples approached him privately, saying: “Tell us, when will these things be, and what will be the sign of your presence* and of the conclusion of the system of things?”*

See Glossary.

Or “the age.” See Glossary.

^ (Matt. 24:7) “For nation will rise against nation and kingdom against kingdom, and there will be food shortages and earthquakes in one place after another.

^ (Matt. 24:12) and because of the increasing of lawlessness, the love of the greater number will grow cold.

^ ***wp16 p. 16 What Does the Bible Say?***

What Does the Bible Say?

What is the Kingdom of God?

SOME PEOPLE BELIEVE that it represents the reign of God in a person’s heart; others think that it is the product of human efforts to bring world peace and brotherhood. What do you think?

WHAT THE BIBLE SAYS

“The God of heaven will set up a kingdom that will never be destroyed. . . . It will crush and put an end to all these [human] kingdoms.” ([Daniel 2:44]) God’s Kingdom is a real government.

WHAT ELSE WE LEARN FROM THE BIBLE

The Kingdom of God rules from heaven.—Matthew 10:7;[Luke 10:9].

God uses the Kingdom to accomplish his will in heaven and on earth.—[Matthew 6:10].

When will God’s Kingdom come?

WHAT WOULD YOU SAY?

No one knows

Soon

Never

WHAT THE BIBLE SAYS

“This good news of the Kingdom will be preached in all the inhabited earth for a witness to all the nations, and then the end will come.” (Matthew 24:14) Once the good news has been fully preached, the Kingdom will come to bring the present wicked system to an end.

WHAT ELSE WE LEARN FROM THE BIBLE

No one on earth knows exactly when God’s Kingdom will come.—Matthew 24:36.

Bible prophecy shows that the Kingdom will come soon.—Matthew 24:3,[7,][12].

For more information, see chapter 8 of this book, What Does the Bible Really Teach?, published by Jehovah’s Witnesses

Also available at www.jw.org

^ (Dan. 2:44) “In the days of those kings the God of heaven will set up a kingdom that will never be destroyed. And this kingdom will not be passed on to any other people. It will crush and put an end to all these kingdoms, and it alone will stand forever,

^ (Matt. 10:7) As you go, preach, saying: ‘The Kingdom of the heavens has drawn near.’

^ (Luke 10:9) and cure the sick ones in it and tell them: ‘The Kingdom of God has come near to you.’

^ (Matt. 6:10) Let your Kingdom come. Let your will take place, as in heaven, also on earth.

^ (Matt. 24:14) And this good news of the Kingdom will be preached in all the inhabited earth for a witness to all the nations, and then the end will come.

^ (Matt. 24:36) “Concerning that day and hour nobody knows, neither the angels of the heavens nor the Son, but only the Father.

^ (Matt. 24:3) While he was sitting on the Mount of Olives, the disciples approached him privately, saying: “Tell us, when will these things be, and what will be the sign of your presence* and of the conclusion of the system of things?”*

See Glossary.

Or “the age.” See Glossary.

^ (Matt. 24:7) “For nation will rise against nation and kingdom against kingdom, and there will be food shortages and earthquakes in one place after another.

^ (Matt. 24:12) and because of the increasing of lawlessness, the love of the greater number will grow cold.

^ ***fg lesson 8***

Satan uses his power to promote immoral, harmful practices. When we reject such practices, some friends and relatives may ridicule or oppose us. (1 Peter 4:3, 4) So we face a choice. Will we associate with people who love God? Will we obey his wise and loving laws? If we do, we prove that Satan lied when he claimed that under pressure no one would do as God says.—Read 1 Corinthians 6:9, 10; 15:33.

^ par. 8 (1 Pet. 4:3, 4) For the time that has passed by is sufficient for you to have done the will of the nations when you carried on in acts of brazen conduct,* unbridled passions, overdrinking, wild parties,* drinking bouts, and lawless idolatries. 4 They are puzzled that you do not continue running with them in the same decadent course of debauchery, so they speak abusively of you.

Or “acts of shameless conduct.” Plural of the Greek a·selʹgei·a. See Glossary.

Or “revelries.”

^ par. 8 (1 Cor. 6:9, 10) Or do you not know that unrighteous people will not inherit God’s Kingdom? Do not be misled.* Those who are sexually immoral,* idolaters, adulterers, men who submit to homosexual acts, men who practice homosexuality,* 10 thieves, greedy people, drunkards, revilers,* and extortioners will not inherit God’s Kingdom.

Or “deceived.”

See Glossary, “Sexual immorality.”

Or “men who have sex with men.” Lit., “men who lie with men.”

Or “the verbally abusive.”

^ par. 8 (1 Cor. 15:33) Do not be misled. Bad associations spoil useful habits.*

Or “corrupt good morals.”

^ ***sn song 57 The Meditation of My Heart***

Song 57

The Meditation of My Heart

([Psalm 19:14])

1. The meditation of my heart,

The thoughts I ponder through the day—

May they be pleasing to you, Lord,

And keep me steadfast in your way.

When worries weigh upon my mind

And make me restless in the night,

Then may I meditate on you

And things I know to be upright.

2. Whatever things are chaste and true,

Whatever virtue there may be,

Whatever things well-spoken of—

May thoughts of these bring peace to me.

How precious are your thoughts, O God!

Beyond all counting is their sum.

So may I ponder your own words,

Absorbed in them may I become.

(See also [Ps. 49:3;][63:6;][139:17,][23;] Phil. 4:7, 8;[1 Tim. 4:15].)

^ (Ps. 19:14) May the words of my mouth and the meditation of my heart Be pleasing to you, O Jehovah, my Rock and my Redeemer.

^ (Ps. 49:3) My own mouth will speak wisdom, And the meditation of my heart will show understanding.

^ (Ps. 63:6) I remember you while upon my bed; I meditate on you during the watches of the night.

^ (Ps. 139:17) So to me, how precious your thoughts are! O God, how vast is the sum of them!

^ (Ps. 139:23) Search through me, O God, and know my heart. Examine me, and know my anxious* thoughts.

Or “disquieting.”

^ (Phil. 4:7, 8) and the peace of God that surpasses all understanding will guard your hearts and your mental powers* by means of Christ Jesus. 8 Finally, brothers, whatever things are true, whatever things are of serious concern, whatever things are righteous, whatever things are chaste,* whatever things are lovable, whatever things are well-spoken-of, whatever things are virtuous, and whatever things are praiseworthy, continue considering* these things.

Or “your minds; your thoughts.”

Or “pure.”

Or “thinking about; meditating on.”

^ (1 Tim. 4:15) Ponder over* these things; be absorbed in them, so that your advancement may be plainly seen by all people.

Or “Meditate on.”

^ ***bh p. 29 What Is God’s Purpose for the Earth?***

7. (a) Why did Adam and Eve die? (b) Why do all of Adam’s offspring grow old and die?

7 By using lies and trickery, Satan the Devil caused Adam and Eve to disobey God. (Genesis 2:17;[3:6]) As a result, they eventually died, as God had said they would if they disobeyed. (Genesis 3:17-19) Since Adam became imperfect when he sinned, all his offspring inherited sin from him. (Read Romans 5:12.) The situation might be illustrated with a pan used for baking bread. If the pan has a dent in it, what happens to each loaf of bread made in the pan? Each loaf has a dent, or an imperfection, in it. Similarly, each human has inherited a “dent” of imperfection from Adam. That is why all humans grow old and die.—[Romans 3:23].

^ par. 7 (Gen. 2:17) But as for the tree of the knowledge of good and bad, you must not eat from it, for in the day you eat from it you will certainly die.”

^ par. 7 (Gen. 3:6) Consequently, the woman saw that the tree was good for food and that it was something desirable to the eyes, yes, the tree was pleasing to look at. So she began taking of its fruit and eating it. Afterward, she also gave some to her husband when he was with her, and he began eating it.

^ par. 7 (Gen. 3:17-19) And to Adam* he said: “Because you listened to your wife’s voice and ate from the tree concerning which I gave you this command, ‘You must not eat from it,’ cursed is the ground on your account. In pain you will eat its produce all the days of your life. 18 It will grow thorns and thistles for you, and you must eat the vegetation of the field. 19 In the sweat of your face you will eat bread* until you return to the ground, for out of it you were taken. For dust you are and to dust you will return.”

Meaning “Earthling Man; Mankind; Humankind.”

Or “food.”

^ par. 7 (Rom. 5:12) That is why, just as through one man sin entered into the world and death through sin, and so death spread to all men because they had all sinned—.

^ par. 7 (Rom. 3:23) For all have sinned and fall short of the glory of God,

^ ***kr pp. 2-3 A Letter From the Governing Body***

A Letter From the Governing Body

Dear Fellow Kingdom Publisher:

PICTURE yourself as a member of the Brooklyn Bethel family on Friday morning, October 2, 1914. You are seated at your usual place at the breakfast table, awaiting the arrival of Brother C. T. Russell. Suddenly the door to the dining room opens and Brother Russell appears. He pauses for a moment, as is his custom, and greets the Bethel family with a cheery “Good morning, all.” But then, instead of immediately taking his place at the head of the table, he claps his hands and makes a thrilling announcement: “The Gentile Times have ended; their kings have had their day!” You can hardly contain your joy—you have been looking forward to this moment for a long time! Along with the rest of the Bethel family, you greet this exciting news with sustained, enthusiastic applause.

Many decades have passed since Brother Russell made that electrifying statement. What has the Kingdom accomplished since then? A great deal! Through the Kingdom arrangement, Jehovah has been progressively refining and training his people—from just a few thousand in 1914 to more than seven-and-a-half million today. How many ways have you personally benefited from such training?

Today we often hear our brothers say, “Jehovah’s celestial chariot is on the move!” and that is true. However, the fact is that since 1914, the celestial chariot, depicting the invisible part of Jehovah’s organization, has been moving at an extremely brisk pace, as a careful reading of this publication will demonstrate. With a view to getting the good news preached worldwide, Kingdom publishers have used a variety of innovative methods, including newspapers, information marches, picture presentations, testimony cards, phonographs, radio, and even the Internet.

With Jehovah’s blessing on the work, we are now able to publish our attractive Bible literature in more than 670 languages and to offer it to everyone without charge. Self-sacrificing volunteers assist in the construction of Kingdom Halls, Assembly Halls, and branch facilities, both in prosperous lands and in lands with limited resources. And when disaster strikes, loving brothers and sisters rush to the aid of those in the affected areas, proving that they truly are “born for times of distress.”—[Prov. 17:17].

At times, the clergy and other opposers frame “trouble in the name of the law,” but it is faith-strengthening to see how, time and again, their misguided efforts have turned out to be “for the advancement of the good news.”—[Ps. 94:20;][Phil. 1:12].

It is an honor for us to be associated with you, our fellow “domestics.” Please know that we love all of you very much. It is our prayer that the contents of this publication will help you to appreciate your spiritual heritage as never before.—[Matt. 24:45].

With every good wish, we are

Your brothers,

Governing Body of Jehovah’s Witnesses

^ (Prov. 17:17) A true friend shows love at all times, And is a brother who is born for times of distress.

^ (Ps. 94:20) Can a throne* of corruption be allied with you While it is framing trouble in the name of the law?*

Or “rulers; judges.”

Or “by decree.”

^ (Phil. 1:12) Now I want you to know, brothers, that my situation has actually turned out for the advancement of the good news,

^ (Matt. 24:45) “Who really is the faithful and discreet* slave whom his master appointed over his domestics, to give them their food at the proper time?

Or “wise.”

^ ***kr pp. 6-9 “Let Your Kingdom Come”***

1, 2. What words did Jehovah himself speak in the hearing of three of Jesus’ apostles, and how did they respond?

IF Jehovah God himself directed you to do something, how would you respond? No matter what he asked, would you not be eager to heed his direction? Surely you would!

2 Sometime after the Passover of 32 C.E., three of Jesus’ apostles—Peter, James, and John—had just such an experience. (Read Matthew 17:1-5.) Gathered with their Master on “a lofty mountain,” they saw in vision a preview of Jesus as a glorious heavenly King. The vision seemed so real that Peter tried to take part in it. While Peter was speaking, a cloud formed over them. Then Peter and his associates plainly heard what only a handful of humans have ever been privileged to hear—Jehovah’s own voice. After affirming that Jesus was his Son, Jehovah said pointedly: “Listen to him.” The apostles heeded that divine direction. They listened to what Jesus taught, and they urged others to do the same.—Acts 3:19-23;[4:18-20].

3. Why does Jehovah want us to listen to his Son, and what subject do we thus do well to examine?

3 Those words—“Listen to him”—were recorded in the Bible for our benefit. ([Rom. 15:4]) Why? Because Jesus is Jehovah’s spokesman and every time Jesus opened his mouth to teach, he shared what his Father wanted us to know. ([John 1:1,][14]) Since Jesus spoke more about God’s Kingdom, the heavenly Messianic government made up of Christ Jesus and his 144,000 corulers, than he did about any other subject, we do well to examine this vital subject carefully. (Rev. 5:9, 10;[14:1-3;][20:6]) First, though, let us examine why Jesus said so much about God’s Kingdom.

“Out of the Abundance of the Heart . . .”

4. How did Jesus indicate that the Kingdom is close to his heart?

4 The Kingdom is close to Jesus’ heart. Why can we say that? Because words are a window into the heart—that is, our words reveal what is truly important to us. Jesus himself said: “Out of the abundance of the heart the mouth speaks.” ([Matt. 12:34]) At every opportunity, Jesus opened his mouth to speak about the Kingdom. There are over 100 references to the Kingdom in the four Gospels, most of them in statements made by Jesus. He made the Kingdom the theme of his preaching, saying: “I must also declare the good news of the Kingdom of God to other cities, because for this I was sent.” ([Luke 4:43]) Even after his resurrection, Jesus continued to speak about the Kingdom to his disciples. ([Acts 1:3]) Surely Jesus’ heart overflowed with appreciation for the Kingdom, impelling him to speak about it.

5-7. (a) How do we know that the Kingdom is close to Jehovah’s heart? Illustrate. (b) How can we show that the Kingdom is close to our heart?

5 The Kingdom is close to Jehovah’s heart as well. How do we know that? Remember, Jehovah sent his only-begotten Son into the world; Jehovah is the source of everything that his Son said and taught. ([John 7:16;][12:49, 50]) Jehovah is also the source of everything that is recorded in the four Gospel accounts of Jesus’ life and ministry. Consider for a moment what that means.

Each of us does well to ask, ‘Is God’s Kingdom close to my heart?’

6 Imagine that you are putting together a family photo album. You have many photographs to choose from, but the album can hold only so many. What do you do? You choose which ones to include. In a sense, the Gospels are like a photo album that gives us a clear picture of Jesus. Jehovah did not inspire the Gospel writers to record everything that Jesus said and did while on earth. ([John 20:30;][21:25]) Instead, Jehovah’s spirit guided them in recording the words and deeds that help us to understand the purpose of Jesus’ ministry and what is most important to Jehovah. (2 Tim. 3:16, 17;[2 Pet. 1:21]) Since the Gospels are filled with Jesus’ teachings about God’s Kingdom, we may safely conclude that the Kingdom is close to Jehovah’s heart. Just think—Jehovah wants us to know what his Kingdom is all about!

7 Each of us does well to ask, ‘Is God’s Kingdom close to my heart?’ If it is, we will be eager to listen to what Jesus said and taught about that Kingdom—its importance and how and when it will come.

“Let Your Kingdom Come”—How?

8. How did Jesus sum up the importance of the Kingdom?

8 Consider the model prayer. With eloquent simplicity, Jesus summed up the importance of the Kingdom, showing what it will accomplish. That prayer consists of seven petitions. The first three concern Jehovah’s purposes—the sanctification of his name, the coming of his Kingdom, and the carrying out of his will on earth as in heaven. (Read Matthew 6:9, 10.) Those three petitions are closely related. The Messianic Kingdom is the instrument through which Jehovah will sanctify his name and carry out his will.

9, 10. (a) How will God’s Kingdom come? (b) What Bible promise do you long to see fulfilled?

9 How will God’s Kingdom come? When we pray, “Let your Kingdom come,” we are asking that the Kingdom take decisive action. When the Kingdom comes, it will exert its full power toward the earth. It will remove the present wicked system of things, including all man-made governments, and bring in a righteous new world. ([Dan. 2:44;][2 Pet. 3:13]) Then, under Kingdom rule, the entire earth will become a paradise. ([Luke 23:43]) Those in God’s memory will be brought back to life and reunited with their loved ones. (John 5:28, 29) Obedient humans will reach perfection and enjoy endless life. ([Rev. 21:3-5]) At last, earth will be in perfect harmony with heaven, reflecting the will of Jehovah God! Do you not long to see those Bible promises come true? Remember that every time you pray for God’s Kingdom to come, you are praying for those precious promises to be fulfilled.

10 It is clear that God’s Kingdom has not yet “come” to fulfill the model prayer. After all, man-made governments are still ruling and the righteous new world is not yet here. But there is good news. God’s Kingdom has been established, as we will discuss in the next chapter. Let us now examine what Jesus said as to when the Kingdom would be established and when it would come.

^ par. 2 (Matt. 17:1-5) Six days later Jesus took Peter and James and his brother John along and led them up into a lofty mountain by themselves. 2 And he was transfigured before them; his face shone as the sun, and his outer garments became brilliant* as the light. 3 And look! there appeared to them Moses and E·liʹjah conversing with him. 4 Then Peter said to Jesus: “Lord, it is fine for us to be here. If you wish, I will erect three tents here, one for you, one for Moses, and one for E·liʹjah.” 5 While he was still speaking, look! a bright cloud overshadowed them, and look! a voice out of the cloud said: “This is my Son, the beloved, whom I have approved. Listen to him.”

Or “white.”

^ par. 2 (Acts 3:19-23) “Repent, therefore, and turn around so as to get your sins blotted out, so that seasons of refreshing may come from Jehovah himself* 20 and he may send the Christ appointed for you, Jesus. 21 Heaven must hold this one within itself until the times of restoration of all things of which God spoke through the mouth of his holy prophets of old. 22 In fact, Moses said: ‘Jehovah* your God will raise up for you from among your brothers a prophet like me. You must listen to whatever he tells you. 23 Indeed, anyone* who does not listen to that Prophet will be completely destroyed from among the people.’

Lit., “from the face of Jehovah.” See App. A5.

See App. A5.

Or “any soul.”

^ par. 2 (Acts 4:18-20) With that they called them and ordered them not to say anything at all or to teach on the basis of the name of Jesus. 19 But in reply Peter and John said to them: “Whether it is right in the sight of God to listen to you rather than to God, judge for yourselves. 20 But as for us, we cannot stop speaking about the things we have seen and heard.”

^ par. 3 (Rom. 15:4) For all the things that were written beforehand were written for our instruction, so that through our endurance and through the comfort from the Scriptures we might have hope.

^ par. 3 (John 1:1) In the beginning was the Word, and the Word was with God, and the Word was a god.*

Or “was divine.”

^ par. 3 (John 1:14) So the Word became flesh and resided among us, and we had a view of his glory, a glory such as belongs to an only-begotten son from a father; and he was full of divine favor* and truth.

Or “of undeserved kindness.”

^ par. 3 (Rev. 5:9, 10) And they sing a new song, saying: “You are worthy to take the scroll and open its seals, for you were slaughtered and with your blood you bought people for God out of every tribe and tongue* and people and nation, 10 and you made them to be a kingdom and priests to our God, and they are to rule as kings over the earth.”

Or “language.”

^ par. 3 (Rev. 14:1-3) Then I saw, and look! the Lamb standing on Mount Zion, and with him 144,000 who have his name and the name of his Father written on their foreheads. 2 I heard a sound coming out of heaven like the sound of many waters and like the sound of loud thunder; and the sound that I heard was like singers who accompany themselves by playing on their harps. 3 And they are singing what seems to be a new song before the throne and before the four living creatures and the elders, and no one was able to master that song except the 144,000, who have been bought from the earth.

^ par. 3 (Rev. 20:6) Happy and holy is anyone having part in the first resurrection; over these the second death has no authority, but they will be priests of God and of the Christ, and they will rule as kings with him for the 1,000 years.

^ par. 4 (Matt. 12:34) Offspring of vipers, how can you speak good things when you are wicked? For out of the abundance of the heart the mouth speaks.

^ par. 4 (Luke 4:43) But he said to them: “I must also declare the good news of the Kingdom of God to other cities, because for this I was sent.”

^ par. 4 (Acts 1:3) After he had suffered, he showed himself alive to them by many convincing proofs. He was seen by them throughout 40 days, and he was speaking about the Kingdom of God.

^ par. 5 (John 7:16) Jesus, in turn, answered them and said: “What I teach is not mine, but belongs to him who sent me.

^ par. 5 (John 12:49, 50) For I have not spoken of my own initiative, but the Father who sent me has himself given me a commandment about what to say and what to speak. 50 And I know that his commandment means everlasting life. So whatever I speak, I speak just as the Father has told me.”

^ par. 6 (John 20:30) To be sure, Jesus also performed many other signs before the disciples, which are not written down in this scroll.

^ par. 6 (John 21:25) There are also, in fact, many other things that Jesus did, which if ever they were written in full detail, I suppose the world itself could not contain the scrolls written.

^ par. 6 (2 Tim. 3:16, 17) All Scripture is inspired of God and beneficial for teaching, for reproving, for setting things straight,* for disciplining in righteousness, 17 so that the man of God may be fully competent, completely equipped for every good work.

Or “correcting.”

^ par. 6 (2 Pet. 1:21) For prophecy was at no time brought by man’s will, but men spoke from God as they were moved* by holy spirit.

Lit., “carried along; borne along.”

^ par. 8 (Matt. 6:9, 10) “You must pray, then, this way: “‘Our Father in the heavens, let your name be sanctified.* 10 Let your Kingdom come. Let your will take place, as in heaven, also on earth.

Or “be held sacred; be treated as holy.”

^ par. 9 (Dan. 2:44) “In the days of those kings the God of heaven will set up a kingdom that will never be destroyed. And this kingdom will not be passed on to any other people. It will crush and put an end to all these kingdoms, and it alone will stand forever,

^ par. 9 (2 Pet. 3:13) But there are new heavens and a new earth that we are awaiting according to his promise, and in these righteousness is to dwell.

^ par. 9 (Luke 23:43) And he said to him: “Truly I tell you today, you will be with me in Paradise.”

^ par. 9 (John 5:28, 29) Do not be amazed at this, for the hour is coming in which all those in the memorial tombs will hear his voice 29 and come out, those who did good things to a resurrection of life, and those who practiced vile things to a resurrection of judgment.

^ par. 9 (Rev. 21:3-5) With that I heard a loud voice from the throne say: “Look! The tent of God is with mankind, and he will reside with them, and they will be his people. And God himself will be with them. 4 And he will wipe out every tear from their eyes, and death will be no more, neither will mourning nor outcry nor pain be anymore. The former things have passed away.” 5 And the One seated on the throne said: “Look! I am making all things new.” Also he says: “Write, for these words are faithful* and true.”

Or “trustworthy.”

^ ***sn song 30 Jehovah Begins His Rule***

Song 30

Jehovah Begins His Rule

(Revelation 11:15)

1. This is a glorious day. God’s rule is now under way.

He’s laid in Zion his Chief Cornerstone.

Let all now lift up the voice. Sing to our God, and rejoice.

Christ, Lord and Savior, has been placed upon His throne.

(CHORUS)

What will you bring, Jehovah’s Kingdom?

Triumph of truth and righteousness.

And bring what else, Jehovah’s Kingdom?

Eternal life and happiness.

Praise the Universal Sov’reign

For his love and faithfulness.

2. Christ now in power is here, And Armageddon is near.

Satan’s old system will soon pass away.

Now is the season to preach. Many there are yet to reach;

Time for the meek to take their stand for Him today.

(CHORUS)

What will you bring, Jehovah’s Kingdom?

Triumph of truth and righteousness.

And bring what else, Jehovah’s Kingdom?

Eternal life and happiness.

Praise the Universal Sov’reign

For his love and faithfulness.

3. God’s reigning Ruler we prize. Wondrous he is in our eyes.

He comes in God’s name; we bow to our King.

Enter the grand temple gate; God’s favor now supplicate.

Soon dawns that day when he rules over ev’rything.

(CHORUS)

What will you bring, Jehovah’s Kingdom?

Triumph of truth and righteousness.

And bring what else, Jehovah’s Kingdom?

Eternal life and happiness.

Praise the Universal Sov’reign

For his love and faithfulness.

(See also [2 Sam. 7:22;][Dan. 2:44;][Rev. 7:15].)

^ (Rev. 11:15) The seventh angel blew his trumpet. And there were loud voices in heaven, saying: “The kingdom of the world has become the Kingdom of our Lord and of his Christ, and he will rule as king forever and ever.”

^ (2 Sam. 7:22) That is why you are truly great, O Sovereign Lord Jehovah. There is no one like you, and there is no God except you; everything we have heard with our ears confirms this.

^ (Dan. 2:44) “In the days of those kings the God of heaven will set up a kingdom that will never be destroyed. And this kingdom will not be passed on to any other people. It will crush and put an end to all these kingdoms, and it alone will stand forever,

^ (Rev. 7:15) That is why they are before the throne of God, and they are rendering him sacred service day and night in his temple; and the One seated on the throne will spread his tent over them.

^ (Pss. 135:1-141:10) Praise Jah!* Praise the name of Jehovah; Offer praise, you servants of Jehovah,  2 You who are standing in the house of Jehovah, In the courtyards of the house of our God.  3 Praise Jah, for Jehovah is good. Sing praises* to his name, for it is pleasant.  4 For Jah has chosen Jacob for himself, Israel for his special property.*  5 For I well know that Jehovah is great; Our Lord is greater than all other gods.  6 Jehovah does everything he pleases to do In heaven and on earth, in the seas and all the depths.  7 He causes clouds* to ascend from the ends of the earth; He makes lightning for* the rain; He brings the wind out of his storehouses.  8 He struck down the firstborn of Egypt, Both man and beast.  9 He sent signs and miracles among you, O Egypt, Against Pharʹaoh and all his servants. 10 He struck down many nations And killed mighty kings 11 —Siʹhon the king of the Amʹor·ites, Og the king of Baʹshan, And all the kingdoms of Caʹnaan. 12 He gave their land as an inheritance, An inheritance to Israel his people. 13 O Jehovah, your name endures forever. O Jehovah, your fame* endures for all generations. 14 For Jehovah will defend* his people, And he will feel compassion* for his servants. 15 The idols of the nations are silver and gold, The work of human hands. 16 A mouth they have, but they cannot speak; Eyes, but they cannot see; 17 Ears they have, but they cannot hear. There is no breath in their mouth. 18 The people who make them will become just like them, As will all those who trust in them. 19 O house of Israel, praise Jehovah. O house of Aaron, praise Jehovah. 20 O house of Leʹvi, praise Jehovah. You who fear Jehovah, praise Jehovah. 21 May Jehovah be praised from Zion, The One residing in Jerusalem. Praise Jah!

136 Give thanks to Jehovah, for he is good; His loyal love endures forever.  2 Give thanks to the God of gods, For his loyal love endures forever.  3 Give thanks to the Lord of lords, For his loyal love endures forever.  4 He alone does great wonders, For his loyal love endures forever.  5 He skillfully made* the heavens, For his loyal love endures forever.  6 He spread out the earth over the waters, For his loyal love endures forever.  7 He made the great lights, For his loyal love endures forever,  8 The sun to rule over the day, For his loyal love endures forever,  9 The moon and the stars to rule over the night, For his loyal love endures forever. 10 He struck down Egypt’s firstborn, For his loyal love endures forever. 11 He brought Israel out from their midst, For his loyal love endures forever, 12 With a mighty hand and an outstretched arm, For his loyal love endures forever. 13 He split the Red Sea in two,* For his loyal love endures forever. 14 He caused Israel to pass through the middle of it, For his loyal love endures forever. 15 He shook off Pharʹaoh and his army into the Red Sea, For his loyal love endures forever. 16 He led his people through the wilderness, For his loyal love endures forever. 17 He struck down great kings, For his loyal love endures forever. 18 He killed mighty kings, For his loyal love endures forever, 19 Siʹhon the king of the Amʹor·ites, For his loyal love endures forever, 20 And Og the king of Baʹshan, For his loyal love endures forever. 21 He gave their land as an inheritance, For his loyal love endures forever, 22 An inheritance to Israel his servant, For his loyal love endures forever. 23 He remembered us when we were low, For his loyal love endures forever. 24 He kept rescuing us from our adversaries, For his loyal love endures forever. 25 He gives food to every living thing,* For his loyal love endures forever. 26 Give thanks to the God of the heavens, For his loyal love endures forever.

137 By the rivers of Babylon, there we sat. We wept when we remembered Zion.  2 Upon the poplar trees in her* midst, We hung our harps.  3 For there our captors asked us for a song, Those mocking us wanted amusement: “Sing for us one of the songs of Zion.”  4 How can we sing the song of Jehovah On foreign soil?  5 If I should forget you, O Jerusalem, Let my right hand be forgetful.*  6 Let my tongue stick to my palate If I do not remember you, If I do not place Jerusalem above My greatest reasons for rejoicing.  7 Remember, O Jehovah, What the Eʹdom·ites said on the day Jerusalem fell: “Tear it down! Tear it down to its foundations!”  8 O daughter of Babylon, who is soon to be devastated, Happy will be the one who rewards you With the treatment you inflicted on us.  9 Happy will be the one who seizes your children And dashes them against the rocks.

Of David. 138 I will praise you with all my heart. In the face of other gods, I will sing praises.*  2 I will bow down toward your holy temple,* And I will praise your name Because of your loyal love and your faithfulness. For you have magnified your saying and your name above everything else.*  3 On the day I called, you answered me; You made me bold* and strong.  4 All the kings of the earth will praise you, O Jehovah, For they will have heard the promises you have spoken.  5 They will sing about the ways of Jehovah, For the glory of Jehovah is great.  6 Though Jehovah is high, he takes note of the humble, But the haughty he knows only from a distance.  7 Even when I walk in the midst of danger, you will preserve me alive. You stretch out your hand against the anger of my enemies; Your right hand will save me.  8 Jehovah will accomplish all things in my behalf. O Jehovah, your loyal love endures forever; Do not forsake the works of your hands.

For the director. Of David. A melody. 139 O Jehovah, you have searched through me, and you know me.  2 You know when I sit down and when I rise up. You discern my thoughts from afar.  3 You observe* me when I travel and when I lie down; You are familiar with all my ways.  4 There is not a word on my tongue, But look! O Jehovah, you already know it well.  5 Behind and before me, you surround me; And you lay your hand upon me.  6 Such knowledge is beyond my comprehension.* It is too high for me to reach.*  7 Where can I escape from your spirit, And where can I run away from your face?  8 If I were to ascend to heaven, you would be there, And if I were to make my bed in the Grave,* look! you would be there.  9 If I would fly away with the wings of the dawn To reside by the most remote sea, 10 Even there your hand would lead me And your right hand would take hold of me. 11 If I say: “Surely darkness will conceal me!” Then the night around me would become light. 12 Even the darkness would not be too dark for you, But night would be as bright as the day; Darkness is the same as light to you. 13 For you produced my kidneys; You kept me screened off* in my mother’s womb. 14 I praise you because in an awe-inspiring way I am wonderfully made. Your works are wonderful, I know* this very well. 15 My bones were not hidden from you When I was made in secret, When I was woven in the depths of the earth. 16 Your eyes even saw me as an embryo; All its parts were written in your book Regarding the days when they were formed, Before any of them existed. 17 So to me, how precious your thoughts are! O God, how vast is the sum of them! 18 If I try to count them, they outnumber the grains of sand. When I awake, I am still with you.* 19 O God, if only you would slay the wicked! Then the violent* men would depart from me, 20 Those who say things against you with evil intent;* They are your adversaries who take up your name in a worthless way. 21 Do I not hate those who hate you, O Jehovah, And loathe those who revolt against you? 22 I have nothing but hatred for them; They have become real enemies to me. 23 Search through me, O God, and know my heart. Examine me, and know my anxious* thoughts. 24 See whether there is in me any harmful way, And lead me in the way of eternity.

For the director. A melody of David. 140 Rescue me, O Jehovah, from evil men; Protect me from violent men,  2 Those who scheme evil in their hearts And stir up conflict all day long.  3 They sharpen their tongue like that of a serpent; Venom of vipers is behind their lips. (Selah)  4 Protect me, O Jehovah, from the hands of the wicked; Safeguard me from violent men, Those who scheme to trip me.  5 The haughty ones hide a trap for me; With ropes they spread out a net beside the path. They set snares for me. (Selah)  6 I say to Jehovah: “You are my God. Listen, O Jehovah, to my pleas for help.”  7 O Jehovah the Sovereign Lord, my strong Savior, You shield my head in the day of battle.  8 Do not grant, O Jehovah, the desires of the wicked. Do not let their plots succeed, so that they are not exalted. (Selah)  9 May the heads of those surrounding me Be covered with the evil spoken by their lips. 10 May burning coals rain down on them. May they be hurled into the fire, Into deep pits,* never to rise again. 11 May the slanderer find no place on the earth.* May evil pursue men of violence and strike them down. 12 I know that Jehovah will defend the lowly And give justice to the poor. 13 Surely the righteous will give thanks to your name; The upright will dwell before your face.*

A melody of David. 141 O Jehovah, I call on you. Come quickly to help me. Do pay attention when I call to you.  2 May my prayer be as incense prepared before you, My uplifted hands like the evening grain offering.  3 Station a guard for my mouth, O Jehovah, Do set a watch over the door of my lips.  4 Do not let my heart incline to anything bad, To share in vile deeds with evil men; May I never feast on their delicacies.  5 Should the righteous one strike me, it would be an act of loyal love; Should he reprove me, it would be like oil on my head, Which my head would never refuse. My prayer will continue even during their calamities.  6 Though their judges are thrown down from the cliff, The people will pay attention to my words, for they are pleasant.  7 Just as when someone plows and breaks up the soil, So our bones have been scattered at the mouth of the Grave.*  8 But my eyes look to you, O Sovereign Lord Jehovah. In you I have taken refuge. Do not take away my life.*  9 Protect me from the jaws of the trap they have laid for me, From the snares of evildoers. 10 The wicked will fall into their own nets all together While I pass by safely.

Or “Hallelujah!” “Jah” is a shortened form of the name Jehovah.

Or “Make music.”

Or “treasured possession.”

Or “vapors.”

Or possibly, “makes sluices for.”

Or “name.” Lit., “memorial.”

Or “plead the cause of.”

Or “feel regret.”

Or “made with understanding.”

Lit., “into pieces.”

Lit., “all flesh.”

Referring to Babylon.

Or possibly, “wither.”

Or possibly, “In defiance of other gods, I will make music to you.”

Or “sanctuary.”

Or possibly, “you have magnified your saying above all your name.”

Or “bold in my soul.”

Lit., “measure.”

Or “is too amazing for me.”

Or “too much for me to fathom.”

Or “Sheol,” that is, the common grave of mankind. See Glossary.

Or possibly, “wove me together.”

Or “My soul knows.”

Or possibly, “I would still be counting them.”

Or “bloodguilty.”

Or “according to their idea.”

Or “disquieting.”

Or “Into watery pits.”

Or “in the land.”

Or “in your presence.”

Or “Sheol,” that is, the common grave of mankind. See Glossary.

Or “pour out my soul.”

^ ***be p. 253 pars. 3-4 Reasoning Manner***

Ask Questions. Jesus set an outstanding example in reasoning with people. He took into account their background and used illustrations that they would readily accept. He also made effective use of questions. This gave others opportunity to express themselves and revealed what was in their hearts. It also encouraged them to reason on the matter being considered.

A man versed in the Law asked Jesus: “Teacher, by doing what shall I inherit everlasting life?” Jesus could easily have given him the answer. But he invited the man to express himself. “What is written in the Law? How do you read?” The man answered correctly. Did his giving a correct answer end that discussion? Not at all. Jesus let the man continue, and a question that the man himself asked indicated that he was trying to prove himself righteous. He asked: “Who really is my neighbor?” Rather than give a definition, which the man might have disputed because of the prevailing Jewish attitude toward Gentiles and Samaritans, Jesus invited him to reason on an illustration. It was about a neighborly Samaritan who came to the aid of a traveler that had been robbed and beaten, whereas a priest and a Levite did not. With a simple question, Jesus made sure that the man got the point. Jesus’ manner of reasoning made the expression “neighbor” take on a meaning that this man had never before discerned. (Luke 10:25-37) What a fine example to imitate! Instead of doing all the talking yourself, in effect, thinking for your householder, learn how to use tactful questions and illustrations to encourage your listener to think.

^ par. 4 (Luke 10:25-37) Now look! a man versed in the Law stood up to test him and said: “Teacher, what do I need to do to inherit everlasting life?” 26 He said to him: “What is written in the Law? How do you read?” 27 In answer he said: “‘You must love Jehovah* your God with your whole heart and with your whole soul* and with your whole strength and with your whole mind’ and ‘your neighbor as yourself.’” 28 He said to him: “You answered correctly; keep doing this and you will get life.” 29 But wanting to prove himself righteous, the man said to Jesus: “Who really is my neighbor?” 30 In reply Jesus said: “A man was going down from Jerusalem to Jerʹi·cho and fell victim to robbers, who stripped him, beat him, and went off, leaving him half-dead. 31 Now by coincidence a priest was going down on that road, but when he saw him, he passed by on the opposite side. 32 Likewise, a Levite, when he came to the place and saw him, passed by on the opposite side. 33 But a certain Sa·marʹi·tan traveling the road came upon him, and at seeing him, he was moved with pity. 34 So he approached him and bandaged his wounds, pouring oil and wine on them. Then he mounted him on his own animal and brought him to an inn and took care of him. 35 The next day he took out two de·narʹi·i,* gave them to the innkeeper, and said: ‘Take care of him, and whatever you spend besides this, I will repay you when I return.’ 36 Who of these three seems to you to have made himself neighbor to the man who fell victim to the robbers?” 37 He said: “The one who acted mercifully toward him.” Jesus then said to him: “Go and do the same yourself.”

See App. A5.

See Glossary.

See App. B14.

^ ***be p. 238 pars. 1-2 Effective Use of Questions***

When we conduct Bible studies, we use a method that calls for participation by the student. Of course, the greater good is done if the student does not simply recite the printed answers. In a kindly tone, use auxiliary questions to reason with the student. On key thoughts, encourage him to use the Bible as the basis for his reply. You might also ask: “How does what we are discussing fit in with this other point that we have studied? Why is it important? How should it affect our lives?” Such a method is more effective than expressing your own convictions or giving an extended explanation yourself. In this way, you help the student to use his “power of reason” to worship God.—[Rom. 12:1].

If a student does not grasp a certain idea, be patient. He may be trying to compare what you are saying with what he has believed for many years. Approaching the subject from a different angle might help. Sometimes, however, very basic reasoning is needed. Make liberal use of the Scriptures. Use illustrations. Along with these, use simple questions that invite the person to reason on the evidence.

^ par. 1 (Rom. 12:1) Therefore, I appeal to you by the compassions of God, brothers, to present your bodies as a living sacrifice, holy and acceptable to God, a sacred service with your power of reason.

^ ***be p. 230 par. 4 Informative to Your Audience***

Adjust the pace of your delivery according to what your audience knows. If you include some details that are likely familiar to most, cover these fairly quickly. But slow down when presenting ideas that may be new to the majority of your listeners so that they can grasp these clearly.

^ ***be p. 226 pars. 4-5 Understandable to Others***

Even when you deal with deep material, simplicity of style can help make it easier to understand. How can simplicity be achieved? Do not overwhelm your audience with unnecessary details. Organize your material so that it complements your main points. Select your key scriptures carefully. Rather than rushing from one text to another, read and discuss these. Do not bury a good thought in a multitude of words.

When you conduct a home Bible study, apply those same principles. Do not try to explain all the details. Help the student to understand clearly the principal ideas. Later on, in personal study and at congregation meetings, he can fill in the details.

^ ***be p. 235 par. 3 Use of Assigned Material***

This training can also help you to conduct progressive home Bible studies. You will learn to focus attention on the study material instead of digressing from the subject by highlighting other things that may be interesting but not necessary to an understanding of the subject. Yet, if you get the spirit of this lesson, you will not become so rigid that you fail to provide added explanation that a student may require.

^ ***be p. 144 pars. 1-3 Use of Bible in Replying***

Our desire is to follow Jesus’ example. We have not personally heard God speak, as Jesus did. But the Bible is God’s Word. When we use it as the basis for our answers, we avoid drawing attention to ourselves. We show that instead of voicing the opinion of an imperfect human, we are firmly determined to let God have the say as to what is truth.—[John 7:18;][Rom. 3:4].

Of course, our desire is not merely to use the Bible but to do so in a way that will be most beneficial to our hearer. We want him to listen with an open mind. Depending on the attitude of the person, you could introduce Biblical thoughts by saying: “Don’t you agree that what really counts is what God says?” Or you could say: “Did you know that the Bible discusses that very question?” If you are speaking to someone who does not have respect for the Bible, you may need to use a somewhat different introduction. You could say: “Let me share this ancient prophecy with you.” Or you might say: “The book that is the most widely distributed in human history says this . . . ”

In some instances, you may choose simply to paraphrase a text. Where possible, however, it is best to open the Bible itself and read what it says. Show the scripture to the person in his own copy of the Bible whenever this is practical. This direct use of the Bible often has a powerful effect on people.—[Heb. 4:12].

^ par. 1 (John 7:18) Whoever speaks of his own originality is seeking his own glory; but whoever seeks the glory of the one who sent him, this one is true and there is no unrighteousness in him.

^ par. 1 (Rom. 3:4) Certainly not! But let God be found true, even if every man be found a liar, just as it is written: “That you might be proved righteous in your words and might win when you are being judged.”

^ par. 3 (Heb. 4:12) For the word of God is alive and exerts power and is sharper than any two-edged sword and pierces even to the dividing of soul* and spirit,* and of joints from the marrow, and is able to discern thoughts and intentions of the heart.

See Glossary.

See Glossary.

^ ***be p. 245 pars. 2-4 Illustrations From Familiar Situations***

Are you as careful as Jesus and Paul were in selecting illustrations and examples to use in your teaching? Do you consider the background and the daily activity of your listeners? Of course, there have been changes in the world since the first century. Many people have access to world news by means of television. Situations in foreign lands are often familiar to them. Where that is the case, it certainly is not amiss to draw on such news items for illustrations. Nevertheless, the things that touch people most deeply usually involve their personal lives—their home, their family, their work, the food they eat, the weather in their area.

If your illustration requires a lot of explanation, you may be talking about something that is not familiar to your audience. Such an illustration can easily overshadow the point of the instruction. As a result, the audience may remember your illustration but not the Scriptural truth that you were endeavoring to convey.

Instead of making complicated comparisons, Jesus used simple, everyday matters. He made use of little things to explain big things and easy things to make hard things plain. By making connections between everyday events and spiritual truths, Jesus helped people to grasp more readily the spiritual truths he was teaching and to remember these. What a fine example to follow!

^ ***be p. 238 pars. 3-5 Effective Use of Questions***

To Draw Out Inner Feelings. When people answer questions, they do not always reveal how they really feel. They may simply give the answers that they think you want. Discernment is needed. ([Prov. 20:5]) As Jesus did, you might ask: “Do you believe this?”—[John 11:26].

When many of Jesus’ disciples took offense at what he said and abandoned him, Jesus invited his apostles to express how they felt. He asked: “You do not want to go also, do you?” Peter put their feelings into words, saying: “Lord, whom shall we go away to? You have sayings of everlasting life; and we have believed and come to know that you are the Holy One of God.” ([John 6:67-69]) On another occasion, Jesus asked his disciples: “Who are men saying the Son of man is?” He followed this with a question that invited them to express what was in their own hearts. “You, though, who do you say I am?” In response, Peter said: “You are the Christ, the Son of the living God.”—Matt. 16:13-16.

When conducting a Bible study, you may find it beneficial to take a similar approach to certain issues. You might ask: “How do your classmates (or workmates) view this matter?” Then you might ask: “How do you feel about it?” When you know a person’s true feelings, this makes it possible for you as a teacher to be of the greatest help.

^ par. 3 (Prov. 20:5) The thoughts* of a man’s heart are like deep waters, But the discerning man draws them out.

Or “intentions.” Lit., “counsel.”

^ par. 3 (John 11:26) and everyone who is living and exercises faith in me will never die at all. Do you believe this?”

^ par. 4 (John 6:67-69) So Jesus said to the Twelve: “You do not want to go also, do you?” 68 Simon Peter answered him: “Lord, whom shall we go away to? You have sayings of everlasting life. 69 We have believed and have come to know that you are the Holy One of God.”

^ par. 4 (Matt. 16:13-16) When he had come into the region of Caes·a·reʹa Phi·lipʹpi, Jesus asked his disciples: “Who are men saying the Son of man is?” 14 They said: “Some say John the Baptist, others E·liʹjah, and still others Jeremiah or one of the prophets.” 15 He said to them: “You, though, who do you say I am?” 16 Simon Peter answered: “You are the Christ, the Son of the living God.”

^ ***be p. 259 par. 1 Effort to Reach the Heart***

Well-chosen questions can help you to draw out what is in someone’s heart. You might ask: “How do you feel about . . . ?” “What convinced you that . . . ?” “How would you react if . . . ?” Yet, be careful not to barrage people with questions. You might tactfully preface your questions with, “Do you mind if I ask . . . ?” Discovering what is in the heart is a painstaking task that cannot be rushed. In most cases trust must be built up over a period of time before a person is willing to reveal his inmost feelings. Even then, care must be exercised so that the person does not feel that you are asking about things that are not your business.—[1 Pet. 4:15].

^ par. 1 (1 Pet. 4:15) However, let none of you suffer as a murderer or a thief or a wrongdoer or a busybody in other people’s matters.

^ (Pss. 142:0-150:6) Masʹkil.* Of David when he was in the cave. A prayer. 142 With my voice I call to Jehovah for help; With my voice I plead with Jehovah for favor.  2 Before him I pour out my concern; Before him I tell about my distress  3 When my spirit* fails within me. Then you watch my roadway. In the path where I walk, They hide a trap for me.  4 Look at my right hand and see That no one cares about* me. There is nowhere I can flee; No one is concerned about me.*  5 I call to you, O Jehovah, for help. I say: “You are my refuge, All I have* in the land of the living.”  6 Pay attention to my cry for help, For I have been brought very low. Rescue me from my persecutors, For they are stronger than I am.  7 Bring me* out of the dungeon To praise your name. May the righteous gather around me Because you deal kindly with me.

A melody of David. 143 O Jehovah, hear my prayer; Listen to my plea for help. In your faithfulness and in your righteousness, answer me.  2 Do not enter into judgment with your servant, For no one living can be righteous before you.  3 For the enemy pursues me;* He has crushed my life into the ground. He has caused me to dwell in darkness like those long dead.  4 My spirit* is failing; My heart is numb within me.  5 I remember the days of old; I meditate on all your activity; I eagerly ponder over* the work of your hands.  6 I spread out my hands to you; I am* like a parched land that thirsts for you. (Selah)  7 Do answer me quickly, O Jehovah; My strength* has come to an end. Do not hide your face from me, Or I will be like those going down into the pit.*  8 Let me hear your loyal love in the morning, For I trust in you. Make known to me the way I should walk, For to you I turn.*  9 Rescue me from my enemies, O Jehovah. I seek your protection. 10 Teach me to do your will, For you are my God. Your spirit is good; May it lead me on level ground.* 11 For the sake of your name, O Jehovah, preserve me alive. In your righteousness, rescue me* from distress. 12 In your loyal love, put an end to* my enemies; Destroy all those harassing me,* For I am your servant.

Of David. 144 May Jehovah, my Rock, be praised, Who trains my hands for battle, My fingers for warfare.  2 He is my loyal love and my stronghold, My secure refuge* and my rescuer, My shield and the One in whom I have taken shelter, The One subduing peoples under me.  3 O Jehovah, what is man that you should notice him, The son of mortal man that you should pay attention to him?  4 Man resembles a mere breath; His days are like a passing shadow.  5 O Jehovah, lower* your heavens and descend; Touch the mountains and make them smoke.  6 Make lightning flash and scatter the enemy; Shoot your arrows and throw them into confusion.  7 Stretch out your hands from above; Rescue me and save me from the surging waters, From the hand* of the foreigners,  8 Whose mouths speak lies And who raise their right hand to swear to what is false.*  9 O God, I will sing to you a new song. I will sing praises* to you, accompanied by a ten-stringed instrument, 10 To the One who gives victory* to kings, The One rescuing his servant David from the deadly sword. 11 Rescue me and save me from the hand of the foreigners, Whose mouths speak lies And who raise their right hand to swear to what is false. 12 Then our sons will be like young plants that grow up quickly, Our daughters like corner pillars carved for a palace. 13 Our storehouses will overflow with every kind of produce; Our flocks in our fields will multiply by the thousands, by the tens of thousands. 14 Our cattle, heavy with young, will suffer no mishap* or miscarriage; There will be no cry of distress in our public squares. 15 Happy is the people for whom it is this way! Happy is the people whose God is Jehovah!

A praise of David. 145 I will exalt you, O my God the King, I will praise your name forever and ever.  2 All day long I will praise you; I will praise your name forever and ever.  3 Jehovah is great and most worthy of praise; His greatness is unsearchable.*  4 Generation after generation will praise your works; They will tell about your mighty acts.  5 Of the glorious splendor of your majesty they will speak And on your wonderful works I will meditate.  6 They will speak about your awe-inspiring deeds,* And I will declare your greatness.  7 They will bubble over as they recall your abundant goodness, And they will shout joyfully because of your righteousness.  8 Jehovah is compassionate* and merciful, Slow to anger and great in loyal love.  9 Jehovah is good to all, And his mercy is evident in all his works. 10 All your works will glorify you, O Jehovah, And your loyal ones will praise you. 11 They will proclaim the glory of your kingship And speak about your mightiness, 12 To make known to men your mighty acts And the glorious splendor of your kingship. 13 Your kingship is an eternal kingship, And your dominion endures throughout all generations. 14 Jehovah supports all who are falling And raises up all who are bowed down. 15 All eyes look hopefully to you; You give them their food in its season. 16 You open your hand And satisfy the desire of every living thing. 17 Jehovah is righteous in all his ways And loyal in all that he does. 18 Jehovah is near to all those calling on him, To all who call on him in truth.* 19 He satisfies the desire of those who fear him; He hears their cry for help, and he rescues them. 20 Jehovah guards all those who love him, But all the wicked he will annihilate. 21 My mouth will declare the praise of Jehovah; Let every living thing* praise his holy name forever and ever.

146 Praise Jah!* Let my whole being* praise Jehovah.  2 I will praise Jehovah all my life. I will sing praises* to my God as long as I live.  3 Do not put your trust in princes* Nor in a son of man, who cannot bring salvation.  4 His spirit* goes out, he returns to the ground; On that very day his thoughts perish.  5 Happy is the one who has the God of Jacob as his helper, Whose hope is in Jehovah his God,  6 The Maker of heaven and earth, Of the sea, and of all that is in them, The One who always remains faithful,  7 The One securing justice for those defrauded, The One giving bread to the hungry. Jehovah is releasing the prisoners.*  8 Jehovah is opening the eyes of the blind; Jehovah is raising up those bowed down; Jehovah loves the righteous.  9 Jehovah is protecting the foreign residents; He sustains the fatherless child and the widow, But he thwarts the plans of the wicked.* 10 Jehovah will be King forever, Your God, O Zion, for generation after generation. Praise Jah!*

147 Praise Jah!* It is good to sing praises* to our God; How pleasant and fitting it is to praise him!  2 Jehovah is building Jerusalem; He gathers together the dispersed ones of Israel.  3 He heals the brokenhearted; He binds up their wounds.  4 He counts the number of the stars; He calls all of them by name.  5 Our Lord is great and is mighty in power; His understanding is beyond measure.  6 Jehovah raises up the meek, But he hurls the wicked to the ground.  7 Sing to Jehovah with thanksgiving; Sing praises to our God, accompanied by the harp,  8 The One who covers the heavens with clouds, The One providing rain for the earth, The One making grass sprout on the mountains.  9 To the animals he gives food, To the young ravens that call out for it. 10 He does not delight in the power of the horse; Nor is he impressed by the strong legs of a man. 11 Jehovah finds pleasure in those who fear him, In those waiting for his loyal love. 12 Glorify Jehovah, O Jerusalem. Praise your God, O Zion. 13 He makes the bars of your city gates strong; He blesses your sons within you. 14 He brings peace to your territory; He satisfies you with the finest* wheat. 15 He sends his command to the earth; His word runs swiftly. 16 He sends the snow like wool; He scatters the frost just like ashes. 17 He hurls down his hailstones* like morsels of bread. Who can withstand his cold? 18 He sends out his word, and they melt. He makes his wind blow, and the waters flow. 19 He declares his word to Jacob, His regulations and judgments to Israel. 20 He has not done so with any other nation; They know nothing about his judgments. Praise Jah!*

148 Praise Jah!* Praise Jehovah from the heavens; Praise him in the heights.  2 Praise him, all his angels. Praise him, all his army.  3 Praise him, sun and moon. Praise him, all shining stars.  4 Praise him, O highest heavens* And waters above the heavens.  5 Let them praise the name of Jehovah, For he commanded, and they were created.  6 He keeps them established forever and ever; He has issued a decree that will not pass away.  7 Praise Jehovah from the earth, You great sea creatures and all deep waters,  8 You lightning and hail, snow and thick clouds, You storm wind, carrying out his word,  9 You mountains and all you hills, You fruit trees and all you cedars, 10 You wild animals and all you domestic animals, You creeping things and winged birds, 11 You kings of the earth and all you nations, You princes and all you judges of the earth, 12 You young men and young women,* Old men and young together.* 13 Let them praise the name of Jehovah, For his name alone is unreachably high. His majesty is above earth and heaven. 14 He will exalt the strength* of his people, For the praise of all his loyal ones, Of the sons of Israel, the people close to him. Praise Jah!*

149 Praise Jah!* Sing to Jehovah a new song; Praise him in the congregation of the loyal ones.  2 Let Israel rejoice in its Grand Maker; Let the sons of Zion be joyful in their King.  3 Let them praise his name with dancing And sing praises* to him, accompanied by the tambourine and the harp.  4 For Jehovah takes pleasure in his people. He adorns the meek with salvation.  5 Let the loyal ones exult in glory; Let them shout for joy upon their beds.  6 Let the songs praising God be in their throat, And a two-edged sword be in their hand,  7 To execute vengeance on the nations And punishment on the peoples,  8 To bind their kings with shackles And their nobles with iron fetters,  9 To execute the judgment written against them. This honor belongs to all his loyal ones. Praise Jah!*

150 Praise Jah!* Praise God in his holy place. Praise him in the expanse of* his strength.  2 Praise him for his mighty works. Praise him for his exceeding greatness.  3 Praise him with the sounding of the horn. Praise him with the stringed instrument and the harp.  4 Praise him with the tambourine and the circle dance. Praise him with strings and the flute.*  5 Praise him with ringing cymbals. Praise him with crashing cymbals.  6 Every breathing thing—let it praise Jah. Praise Jah!*

See Glossary.

Or “strength.”

Lit., “recognizes.”

Or “my soul.”

Lit., “My share.”

Or “my soul.”

Or “my soul.”

Or “strength.”

Or “study.”

Or “My soul is.”

Lit., “spirit.”

Or “grave.”

Or “For I lift up my soul to you.”

Or “in the land of uprightness.”

Or “my soul.”

Lit., “silence.”

Or “my soul.”

Or “secure height.”

Or “bend.”

Or “grip.”

Lit., “And their right hand is a right hand of falsehood.”

Or “make music.”

Or “salvation.”

Or “rupture.”

Or “beyond understanding.”

Or “power.”

Or “gracious.”

Or “in sincerity.”

Lit., “all flesh.”

Or “Hallelujah!” “Jah” is a shortened form of the name Jehovah.

Or “my soul.”

Or “make music.”

Or “nobles.”

Or “breath.”

Lit., “bound ones.”

Or “makes the way of the wicked crooked.”

Or “Hallelujah!” “Jah” is a shortened form of the name Jehovah.

Or “Hallelujah!” “Jah” is a shortened form of the name Jehovah.

Or “make music.”

Lit., “the fat of.”

Or “ice.”

Or “Hallelujah!” “Jah” is a shortened form of the name Jehovah.

Or “Hallelujah!” “Jah” is a shortened form of the name Jehovah.

Lit., “heavens of the heavens.”

Lit., “virgins.”

Or “Old and young together.”

Lit., “the horn.”

Or “Hallelujah!” “Jah” is a shortened form of the name Jehovah.

Or “Hallelujah!” “Jah” is a shortened form of the name Jehovah.

Or “make music.”

Or “Hallelujah!” “Jah” is a shortened form of the name Jehovah.

Or “Hallelujah!” “Jah” is a shortened form of the name Jehovah.

Or “the sky that bears witness to.”

Or “pipe.”

Or “Hallelujah!” “Jah” is a shortened form of the name Jehovah.

^ (Ps. 145:1-21) I will exalt you, O my God the King, I will praise your name forever and ever.  2 All day long I will praise you; I will praise your name forever and ever.  3 Jehovah is great and most worthy of praise; His greatness is unsearchable.*  4 Generation after generation will praise your works; They will tell about your mighty acts.  5 Of the glorious splendor of your majesty they will speak And on your wonderful works I will meditate.  6 They will speak about your awe-inspiring deeds,* And I will declare your greatness.  7 They will bubble over as they recall your abundant goodness, And they will shout joyfully because of your righteousness.  8 Jehovah is compassionate* and merciful, Slow to anger and great in loyal love.  9 Jehovah is good to all, And his mercy is evident in all his works. 10 All your works will glorify you, O Jehovah, And your loyal ones will praise you. 11 They will proclaim the glory of your kingship And speak about your mightiness, 12 To make known to men your mighty acts And the glorious splendor of your kingship. 13 Your kingship is an eternal kingship, And your dominion endures throughout all generations. 14 Jehovah supports all who are falling And raises up all who are bowed down. 15 All eyes look hopefully to you; You give them their food in its season. 16 You open your hand And satisfy the desire of every living thing. 17 Jehovah is righteous in all his ways And loyal in all that he does. 18 Jehovah is near to all those calling on him, To all who call on him in truth.* 19 He satisfies the desire of those who fear him; He hears their cry for help, and he rescues them. 20 Jehovah guards all those who love him, But all the wicked he will annihilate. 21 My mouth will declare the praise of Jehovah; Let every living thing* praise his holy name forever and ever.

Or “beyond understanding.”

Or “power.”

Or “gracious.”

Or “in sincerity.”

Lit., “all flesh.”

^ ***sn song 134 See Yourself When All Is New***

Song 134

See Yourself When All Is New

(Revelation 21:1-5)

1. Just see yourself, just see me too;

Just see us all in a world that is new.

Think how you’ll feel, how it will be,

To live in peace, to be truly free.

No evil one will then prevail;

Rule by our God cannot ever fail.

The time will have come for a new earthly start,

The song of our praises will pour out from our heart:

(CHORUS)

“Jehovah our God, how well you have done!

All things are new by the rule of your Son.

The fullness of our heart overflows in our song;

All glory and honor and praise to you belong.”

2. Now see yourself, and see me too;

And look ahead to a world that is new.

No sight we see, no sound we hear

Will cause alarm or give rise to fear.

All has come true, just as he said;

Now over mankind, his tent is spread.

He now shall awaken those sleeping in death;

Their voices will join us with ev’ry grateful breath:

(CHORUS)

“Jehovah our God, how well you have done!

All things are new by the rule of your Son.

The fullness of our heart overflows in our song;

All glory and honor and praise to you belong.”

(See also Ps. 37:10, 11;[Isa. 65:17;][John 5:28;][2 Pet. 3:13].)

^ (Rev. 21:1-5) And I saw a new heaven and a new earth; for the former heaven and the former earth had passed away, and the sea is no more. 2 I also saw the holy city, New Jerusalem, coming down out of heaven from God and prepared as a bride adorned for her husband. 3 With that I heard a loud voice from the throne say: “Look! The tent of God is with mankind, and he will reside with them, and they will be his people. And God himself will be with them. 4 And he will wipe out every tear from their eyes, and death will be no more, neither will mourning nor outcry nor pain be anymore. The former things have passed away.” 5 And the One seated on the throne said: “Look! I am making all things new.” Also he says: “Write, for these words are faithful* and true.”

Or “trustworthy.”

^ (Ps. 37:10, 11) Just a little while longer, and the wicked will be no more; You will look at where they were, And they will not be there. 11 But the meek will possess the earth, And they will find exquisite delight in the abundance of peace.

^ (Isa. 65:17) For look! I am creating new heavens and a new earth; And the former things will not be called to mind,* Nor will they come up into the heart.

Or “be remembered.”

^ (John 5:28) Do not be amazed at this, for the hour is coming in which all those in the memorial tombs will hear his voice

^ (2 Pet. 3:13) But there are new heavens and a new earth that we are awaiting according to his promise, and in these righteousness is to dwell.

^ ***w04 1/15 pp. 10-11 Jehovah’s Greatness Is Unsearchable***

‘I Will Exalt God the King’

3. (a) What view did David have of Israel’s kingship? (b) To what extent did David desire to praise Jehovah?

3 Although David was God’s appointed king, he viewed Jehovah as the true King of Israel. Said David: “Yours is the kingdom, O Jehovah, the One also lifting yourself up as head over all.” (1 Chronicles 29:11) And how David appreciated God as Ruler! “I will exalt you, O my God the King,” he sang, “and I will bless your name to time indefinite, even forever. All day long I will bless you, and I will praise your name to time indefinite, even forever.” (Psalm 145:1, 2) It was David’s desire to praise Jehovah God throughout the day and for all eternity.

4. [Psalm 145] exposes what false claims?

4 [Psalm 145] is a powerful answer to Satan’s claim that God is a selfish ruler who withholds freedom from his creatures. (Genesis 3:1-5) This psalm also exposes Satan’s lie that those who obey God do so only for what they can get out of it, not because they love God. ([Job 1:9-11;][2:4, 5]) Like David, true Christians today are supplying an answer to the Devil’s false charges. They treasure their hope of everlasting life under Kingdom rule because they desire to praise Jehovah throughout eternity. Already, millions have started to do so by exercising faith in Jesus’ ransom sacrifice and by serving Jehovah obediently out of love as his dedicated, baptized worshipers.—[Romans 5:8;][1 John 5:3].

^ par. 3 (1 Chron. 29:11) Yours, O Jehovah, are the greatness and the mightiness and the beauty and the splendor and the majesty,* for everything in the heavens and on the earth is yours. Yours is the kingdom, O Jehovah. You are the One exalting yourself as head over all.

Or “dignity.”

^ par. 3 (Ps. 145:1, 2) I will exalt you, O my God the King, I will praise your name forever and ever.  2 All day long I will praise you; I will praise your name forever and ever.

^ (Ps. 145:0-21) A praise of David. 145 I will exalt you, O my God the King, I will praise your name forever and ever.  2 All day long I will praise you; I will praise your name forever and ever.  3 Jehovah is great and most worthy of praise; His greatness is unsearchable.*  4 Generation after generation will praise your works; They will tell about your mighty acts.  5 Of the glorious splendor of your majesty they will speak And on your wonderful works I will meditate.  6 They will speak about your awe-inspiring deeds,* And I will declare your greatness.  7 They will bubble over as they recall your abundant goodness, And they will shout joyfully because of your righteousness.  8 Jehovah is compassionate* and merciful, Slow to anger and great in loyal love.  9 Jehovah is good to all, And his mercy is evident in all his works. 10 All your works will glorify you, O Jehovah, And your loyal ones will praise you. 11 They will proclaim the glory of your kingship And speak about your mightiness, 12 To make known to men your mighty acts And the glorious splendor of your kingship. 13 Your kingship is an eternal kingship, And your dominion endures throughout all generations. 14 Jehovah supports all who are falling And raises up all who are bowed down. 15 All eyes look hopefully to you; You give them their food in its season. 16 You open your hand And satisfy the desire of every living thing. 17 Jehovah is righteous in all his ways And loyal in all that he does. 18 Jehovah is near to all those calling on him, To all who call on him in truth.* 19 He satisfies the desire of those who fear him; He hears their cry for help, and he rescues them. 20 Jehovah guards all those who love him, But all the wicked he will annihilate. 21 My mouth will declare the praise of Jehovah; Let every living thing* praise his holy name forever and ever.

Or “beyond understanding.”

Or “power.”

Or “gracious.”

Or “in sincerity.”

Lit., “all flesh.”

^ par. 4 (Ps. 145:0-21) A praise of David. 145 I will exalt you, O my God the King, I will praise your name forever and ever.  2 All day long I will praise you; I will praise your name forever and ever.  3 Jehovah is great and most worthy of praise; His greatness is unsearchable.*  4 Generation after generation will praise your works; They will tell about your mighty acts.  5 Of the glorious splendor of your majesty they will speak And on your wonderful works I will meditate.  6 They will speak about your awe-inspiring deeds,* And I will declare your greatness.  7 They will bubble over as they recall your abundant goodness, And they will shout joyfully because of your righteousness.  8 Jehovah is compassionate* and merciful, Slow to anger and great in loyal love.  9 Jehovah is good to all, And his mercy is evident in all his works. 10 All your works will glorify you, O Jehovah, And your loyal ones will praise you. 11 They will proclaim the glory of your kingship And speak about your mightiness, 12 To make known to men your mighty acts And the glorious splendor of your kingship. 13 Your kingship is an eternal kingship, And your dominion endures throughout all generations. 14 Jehovah supports all who are falling And raises up all who are bowed down. 15 All eyes look hopefully to you; You give them their food in its season. 16 You open your hand And satisfy the desire of every living thing. 17 Jehovah is righteous in all his ways And loyal in all that he does. 18 Jehovah is near to all those calling on him, To all who call on him in truth.* 19 He satisfies the desire of those who fear him; He hears their cry for help, and he rescues them. 20 Jehovah guards all those who love him, But all the wicked he will annihilate. 21 My mouth will declare the praise of Jehovah; Let every living thing* praise his holy name forever and ever.

Or “beyond understanding.”

Or “power.”

Or “gracious.”

Or “in sincerity.”

Lit., “all flesh.”

^ par. 4 (Gen. 3:1-5) Now the serpent was the most cautious* of all the wild animals of the field that Jehovah God had made. So it said to the woman: “Did God really say that you must not eat from every tree of the garden?” 2 At this the woman said to the serpent: “We may eat of the fruit of the trees of the garden. 3 But God has said about the fruit of the tree that is in the middle of the garden: ‘You must not eat from it, no, you must not touch it; otherwise you will die.’” 4 At this the serpent said to the woman: “You certainly will not die. 5 For God knows that in the very day you eat from it, your eyes will be opened and you will be like God, knowing good and bad.”

Or “shrewdest; craftiest.”

^ par. 4 (Job 1:9-11) At that Satan answered Jehovah: “Is it for nothing that Job has feared God? 10 Have you not put up a protective hedge around him and his house and everything he has? You have blessed the work of his hands, and his livestock has spread out in the land. 11 But, for a change, stretch out your hand and strike everything he has, and he will surely curse you to your very face.”

^ par. 4 (Job 2:4, 5) But Satan answered Jehovah: “Skin for skin. A man will give everything that he has for his life.* 5 But, for a change, stretch out your hand and strike his bone and flesh, and he will surely curse you to your very face.”

Or “soul.”

^ par. 4 (Rom. 5:8) But God recommends his own love to us in that, while we were yet sinners, Christ died for us.

^ par. 4 (1 John 5:3) For this is what the love of God means, that we observe his commandments; and yet his commandments are not burdensome,

^ ***w04 1/15 p. 11 Jehovah’s Greatness Is Unsearchable***

Examples of God’s Greatness

7. Give a major reason to praise Jehovah.

7 [Psalm 145:3] gives a major reason for praising Jehovah. David sings: “Jehovah is great and very much to be praised, and his greatness is unsearchable.” Jehovah’s greatness is without limits. It cannot be fully searched out, comprehended, or measured by humans. But we will certainly benefit from now considering examples of Jehovah’s unsearchable greatness.

8. What does the universe reveal as to Jehovah’s greatness and power?

8 Try to recall an occasion when you were away from bright city lights and looked up into a cloudless night sky. Were you not amazed at the multitude of stars visible against the blackness of space? Were you not moved to praise Jehovah for his greatness in creating all those celestial bodies? What you saw, however, was but a tiny fraction of the number of stars in the galaxy of which the earth is a part. In addition, there are estimated to be more than a hundred billion galaxies, only three of which can be seen without the aid of a telescope. Indeed, the countless stars and galaxies that make up the immense universe are a testimony to Jehovah’s creative power and unsearchable greatness.—[Isaiah 40:26].

^ par. 7 (Ps. 145:3) Jehovah is great and most worthy of praise; His greatness is unsearchable.*

Or “beyond understanding.”

^ par. 8 (Isa. 40:26) “Lift up your eyes to heaven and see. Who has created these things? It is the One who brings out their army by number; He calls them all by name. Because of his vast dynamic energy and his awe-inspiring power, Not one of them is missing.

^ ***w04 1/15 pp. 14-15 Jehovah’s Greatness Is Unsearchable***

How Great God’s Moral Qualities!

20, 21. (a) Psalm 145:7-9 magnifies Jehovah’s greatness in connection with what qualities? (b) What effect do God’s qualities mentioned here have on all who love him?

20 As we have noted, the first six verses of Psalm 145:1-6 give us sound reasons to praise Jehovah for things associated with his unsearchable greatness. Ps 145 Verses 7 to 9 magnify God’s greatness by referring to his moral qualities. David sings: “With the mention of the abundance of your goodness they will bubble over, and because of your righteousness they will cry out joyfully. Jehovah is gracious and merciful, slow to anger and great in loving-kindness. Jehovah is good to all, and his mercies are over all his works.”

21 Here David first highlights Jehovah’s goodness and righteousness—qualities called into question by Satan the Devil. What effect do these qualities have on all who love God and submit to his rulership? Why, Jehovah’s goodness and his righteous way of ruling bring such joy to his worshipers that they cannot stop bubbling forth his praise. Moreover, Jehovah’s goodness extends “to all.” Hopefully, this will help many more to repent and become worshipers of the true God before it is too late.—Acts 14:15-17.

^ (Ps. 145:7-9) They will bubble over as they recall your abundant goodness, And they will shout joyfully because of your righteousness.  8 Jehovah is compassionate* and merciful, Slow to anger and great in loyal love.  9 Jehovah is good to all, And his mercy is evident in all his works.

Or “gracious.”

^ par. 20 (Ps. 145:1-6) I will exalt you, O my God the King, I will praise your name forever and ever.  2 All day long I will praise you; I will praise your name forever and ever.  3 Jehovah is great and most worthy of praise; His greatness is unsearchable.*  4 Generation after generation will praise your works; They will tell about your mighty acts.  5 Of the glorious splendor of your majesty they will speak And on your wonderful works I will meditate.  6 They will speak about your awe-inspiring deeds,* And I will declare your greatness.

Or “beyond understanding.”

Or “power.”

^ par. 20 (Ps. 145:7-9) They will bubble over as they recall your abundant goodness, And they will shout joyfully because of your righteousness.  8 Jehovah is compassionate* and merciful, Slow to anger and great in loyal love.  9 Jehovah is good to all, And his mercy is evident in all his works.

Or “gracious.”

^ par. 21 (Acts 14:15-17) “Men, why are you doing these things? We too are humans having the same infirmities as you have. And we are declaring the good news to you, for you to turn from these vain things to the living God, who made the heaven and the earth and the sea and all the things in them. 16 In past generations he permitted all the nations to go on in their ways, 17 although he did not leave himself without witness in that he did good, giving you rains from heaven and fruitful seasons, satisfying you with food and filling your hearts with gladness.”

^ ***w04 1/15 pp. 15-16 Jehovah Is Great in Loyal Love***

2. What special aspect of love does Jehovah show for those who are in a dedicated relationship with him?

2 Jehovah shows love for his true worshipers in a precious, lasting way. Such love is denoted by a Hebrew word translated “loving-kindness,” or “loyal love.” King David of ancient Israel deeply appreciated God’s loving-kindness. Because of his personal experience and his meditation on God’s dealings with others, David could confidently sing: “Jehovah is . . . great in loving-kindness [or, “loyal love”].”—[Psalm 145:8].

^ par. 2 (Ps. 145:8) Jehovah is compassionate* and merciful, Slow to anger and great in loyal love.

Or “gracious.”

^ ***w04 1/15 p. 16 Jehovah Is Great in Loyal Love***

Identifying God’s Loyal Ones

3, 4. (a) How does [Psalm 145] help us to identify Jehovah’s loyal ones? (b) How do God’s loyal ones “bless” him?

3 Regarding Jehovah God, the prophet Samuel’s mother, Hannah, said: “The feet of his loyal ones he guards.” ([1 Samuel 2:9]) Who are such “loyal ones”? King David supplies the answer. After extolling Jehovah’s marvelous qualities, he states: “Your loyal ones will bless you.” ([Psalm 145:10]) You may wonder how humans can bless God. They do so primarily by praising him or by speaking well of him.

4 Jehovah’s loyal ones can be identified as those who use their mouths to speak well of him. In social settings and at Christian meetings, what is a common theme of their discussions? Why, it is Jehovah’s Kingdom! God’s loyal servants share the sentiments of David, who sang: “About the glory of your [Jehovah’s] kingship they will talk, and about your mightiness they will speak.”—[Psalm 145:11].

5. How do we know that Jehovah takes note when his loyal ones speak well of him?

5 Does Jehovah take note when his loyal ones praise him? Yes, he pays attention to what they say. In a prophecy relating to true worship in our day, Malachi wrote: “At that time those in fear of Jehovah spoke with one another, each one with his companion, and Jehovah kept paying attention and listening. And a book of remembrance began to be written up before him for those in fear of Jehovah and for those thinking upon his name.” ([Malachi 3:16]) It pleases Jehovah very much when his loyal ones speak well of him, and he remembers them.

6. What activity helps us to identify God’s loyal ones?

6 Jehovah’s loyal servants can also be identified by their courage and initiative in speaking to people who are not worshipers of the true God. Indeed, God’s loyal ones “make known to the sons of men his mighty acts and the glory of the splendor of his kingship.” ([Psalm 145:12]) Do you seek and take full advantage of opportunities to speak to strangers about Jehovah’s kingship? Unlike human governments, which will soon pass away, his kingship is eternal. (1 Timothy 1:17) It is urgent that people learn about Jehovah’s everlasting kingship and take their stand as its supporters. “Your kingship is a kingship for all times indefinite,” sang David, “and your dominion is throughout all successive generations.”—[Psalm 145:13].

^ (Ps. 145:0-21) A praise of David. 145 I will exalt you, O my God the King, I will praise your name forever and ever.  2 All day long I will praise you; I will praise your name forever and ever.  3 Jehovah is great and most worthy of praise; His greatness is unsearchable.*  4 Generation after generation will praise your works; They will tell about your mighty acts.  5 Of the glorious splendor of your majesty they will speak And on your wonderful works I will meditate.  6 They will speak about your awe-inspiring deeds,* And I will declare your greatness.  7 They will bubble over as they recall your abundant goodness, And they will shout joyfully because of your righteousness.  8 Jehovah is compassionate* and merciful, Slow to anger and great in loyal love.  9 Jehovah is good to all, And his mercy is evident in all his works. 10 All your works will glorify you, O Jehovah, And your loyal ones will praise you. 11 They will proclaim the glory of your kingship And speak about your mightiness, 12 To make known to men your mighty acts And the glorious splendor of your kingship. 13 Your kingship is an eternal kingship, And your dominion endures throughout all generations. 14 Jehovah supports all who are falling And raises up all who are bowed down. 15 All eyes look hopefully to you; You give them their food in its season. 16 You open your hand And satisfy the desire of every living thing. 17 Jehovah is righteous in all his ways And loyal in all that he does. 18 Jehovah is near to all those calling on him, To all who call on him in truth.* 19 He satisfies the desire of those who fear him; He hears their cry for help, and he rescues them. 20 Jehovah guards all those who love him, But all the wicked he will annihilate. 21 My mouth will declare the praise of Jehovah; Let every living thing* praise his holy name forever and ever.

Or “beyond understanding.”

Or “power.”

Or “gracious.”

Or “in sincerity.”

Lit., “all flesh.”

^ par. 3 (1 Sam. 2:9) He guards the steps of his loyal ones, But the wicked will be silenced in darkness, For not by power does a man prevail.

^ par. 3 (Ps. 145:10) All your works will glorify you, O Jehovah, And your loyal ones will praise you.

^ par. 4 (Ps. 145:11) They will proclaim the glory of your kingship And speak about your mightiness,

^ par. 5 (Mal. 3:16) At that time those who fear Jehovah spoke with one another, each one with his companion, and Jehovah kept paying attention and listening. And a book of remembrance was written before him for those fearing Jehovah and for those meditating on* his name.

Or “thinking on.” Or possibly, “treasuring.”

^ par. 6 (Ps. 145:12) To make known to men your mighty acts And the glorious splendor of your kingship.

^ par. 6 (1 Tim. 1:17) Now to the King of eternity, incorruptible, invisible, the only God, be honor and glory forever and ever. Amen.

^ par. 6 (Ps. 145:13) Your kingship is an eternal kingship, And your dominion endures throughout all generations.

^ ***w04 1/15 pp. 17-18 Jehovah Is Great in Loyal Love***

10 Of course, some human rulers are sincerely concerned about the welfare of their subjects. But even the most noble among them do not know their subjects intimately. Indeed, we may ask: Is there any ruler who cares for all his subjects so much that he quickly comes to the aid of each one in times of trouble? Yes, there is. David wrote: “Jehovah is giving support to all who are falling, and is raising up all who are bowed down.”—[Psalm 145:14].

11. What trials befall God’s loyal ones, and what help do they have?

11 Many trials and calamities befall Jehovah God’s loyal ones because of their own imperfection and because they live in a world that is lying in the power of Satan, “the wicked one.” ([1 John 5:19;][Psalm 34:19]) Christians experience persecution. Some suffer from chronic illness or because of bereavement. At times, the mistakes of Jehovah’s loyal ones may cause them to ‘bow down’ in discouragement. Whatever trial befalls them, however, Jehovah is always ready to give comfort and spiritual strength to each one of them. The King Jesus Christ has the same loving interest in his loyal subjects.—Psalm 72:12-14.

Satisfying Food in Season

12, 13. How well does Jehovah provide for the needs of “every living thing”?

12 Out of his great loving-kindness, Jehovah provides for all the needs of his servants. This includes satisfying them with nourishing food. King David wrote: “To you [Jehovah] the eyes of all look hopefully, and you are giving them their food in its season. You are opening your hand and satisfying the desire of every living thing.” (Psalm 145:15, 16) Even in times of calamity, Jehovah can maneuver matters so that his loyal ones get “bread for the day.”—[Luke 11:3;][12:29, 30].

13 David mentioned that “every living thing” gets satisfied. That includes the animals. If it were not for earth’s abundant vegetation of the land and plants of the sea, aquatic creatures, birds, and land animals would have no oxygen to breathe or food to eat. ([Psalm 104:14]) However, Jehovah sees to it that all their needs are satisfied.

14, 15. How is spiritual food being provided today?

14 Unlike animals, humans have a spiritual need. ([Matthew 5:3]) How wonderfully Jehovah satisfies the spiritual needs of his loyal ones! Before his death, Jesus promised that “the faithful and discreet slave” would provide Jesus’ followers with spiritual “food at the proper time.” (Matthew 24:45) The remnant of the 144,000 anointed ones make up that slave class today. Through them, Jehovah has indeed provided spiritual food in abundance.

^ par. 10 (Ps. 145:14) Jehovah supports all who are falling And raises up all who are bowed down.

^ par. 11 (1 John 5:19) We know that we originate with God, but the whole world is lying in the power of the wicked one.

^ par. 11 (Ps. 34:19) Many are the hardships* of the righteous one, But Jehovah rescues him from them all.

Or “calamities.”

^ par. 11 (Ps. 72:12-14) For he will rescue the poor who cry for help, Also the lowly one and whoever has no helper. 13 He will have pity on the lowly and the poor, And the lives* of the poor he will save. 14 From oppression and from violence he will rescue them,* And their blood will be precious in his eyes.

Or “souls.”

Or “redeem their souls.”

^ par. 12 (Ps. 145:15, 16) All eyes look hopefully to you; You give them their food in its season. 16 You open your hand And satisfy the desire of every living thing.

^ par. 12 (Luke 11:3) Give us each day our bread according to our daily needs.

^ par. 12 (Luke 12:29, 30) So stop seeking what you will eat and what you will drink, and stop being in anxious suspense; 30 for all these are the things the nations of the world are eagerly pursuing, but your Father knows you need these things.

^ par. 13 (Ps. 104:14) He is making grass grow for the cattle And vegetation for mankind’s use, To grow food from the land

^ par. 14 (Matt. 5:3) “Happy are those conscious of their spiritual need,* since the Kingdom of the heavens belongs to them.

Or “those who are beggars for the spirit.”

^ par. 14 (Matt. 24:45) “Who really is the faithful and discreet* slave whom his master appointed over his domestics, to give them their food at the proper time?

Or “wise.”

^ ***w10 1/15 p. 21 Use Each Day of Your Life for God’s Glory***

“IN THE morning cause me to hear your loving-kindness,” prayed the psalmist David to Jehovah. “Make known to me the way in which I should walk.” ([Ps. 143:8]) When you wake up and thank Jehovah for a new day of life, do you, like David, entreat Jehovah to guide you in making decisions and taking the best course of action? No doubt you do.

As dedicated servants of Jehovah, “whether [we] are eating or drinking or doing anything else,” we strive to “do all things for God’s glory.” ([1 Cor. 10:31]) We realize that the way we live our daily life will either honor or dishonor Jehovah. We also remember that God’s Word states that Satan is accusing Christ’s brothers—and, in fact, all of God’s servants on earth—“day and night.” ([Rev. 12:10]) Therefore, we are determined to give a reply to Satan’s false accusations and to make Jehovah’s heart rejoice by rendering sacred service to our heavenly Father “day and night.”—[Rev. 7:15;][Prov. 27:11].

^ (Ps. 143:8) Let me hear your loyal love in the morning, For I trust in you. Make known to me the way I should walk, For to you I turn.*

Or “For I lift up my soul to you.”

^ (1 Cor. 10:31) Therefore, whether you are eating or drinking or doing anything else, do all things for God’s glory.

^ (Rev. 12:10) I heard a loud voice in heaven say: “Now have come to pass the salvation and the power and the Kingdom of our God and the authority of his Christ, because the accuser of our brothers has been hurled down, who accuses them day and night before our God!

^ (Rev. 7:15) That is why they are before the throne of God, and they are rendering him sacred service day and night in his temple; and the One seated on the throne will spread his tent over them.

^ (Prov. 27:11) Be wise, my son, and make my heart rejoice, So that I can make a reply to him who taunts me.

^ ***it-2 p. 448 Mouth***

MOUTH

An organ designed by God to receive and prepare food for the stomach, also, in humans, for speaking. All speech should result in praise to Him. ([Ps 34:1;][51:15;][71:8;][145:21]) The psalmist declared that everything that has breath will praise Jehovah; therefore humans must use their mouths to do this if they desire to live. The apostle Paul explains that belief in God and his Son, even believing with the heart, is not enough. It has to be accompanied by public declaration in order to bring salvation.—[Ps 150:6;][Ro 10:10].

In harmony with his purpose and his right and power as Creator, Jehovah can put the proper words into the mouth of his servant. In the case of his prophets, he did so miraculously, by inspiration. ([Ex 4:11, 12,][15;][Jer 1:9]) In one instance he caused even a dumb animal, an ass, to speak. ([Nu 22:28,][30;] 2Pe 2:15, 16) Today God’s servants can have his words in their mouths, not by inspiration, but from his inspired written Word, which equips them completely for every good work. ([2Ti 3:16, 17]) They no longer have to wait for Christ to come to provide the good news, nor do they need to go to some other source for what they preach. They have it right before them, ready for them to speak, as they are told: “The word is near you, in your own mouth and in your own heart.”—[Ro 10:6-9;][De 30:11-14].

Can Bring Life or Death. It follows that the proper use of the mouth is vital, and so Jehovah declares it to be. His Word says: “The mouth of the righteous one is a source of life.” ([Pr 10:11]) The mouth, therefore, has to be guarded most carefully ([Ps 141:3;][Pr 13:3;][21:23]), for stupid misuse of it can bring its owner to ruin. ([Pr 10:14;][18:7]) God holds a person accountable for what he brings forth from his mouth. ([Mt 12:36, 37]) A person may speak hastily, making a rash vow. ([Ec 5:4-6]) He may flatter another, to that person’s overthrow and his own condemnation. ([Pr 26:28]) It is especially important to guard one’s mouth when before the wicked, because a slight deviation from what God’s wisdom directs his servant to say can bring reproach on God’s name and may cause that one’s death. ([Ps 39:1]) Jesus gave a fine example of submissiveness to God’s will without complaint or any reviling of his wicked opposers.—[Isa 53:7;][Ac 8:32;][1Pe 2:23].

The Christian must exercise constant vigilance, for he is imperfect; therefore he needs to watch his heart. Jesus said that it is not what goes into the mouth that defiles a man, but what comes forth from the mouth, for “out of the abundance of the heart the mouth speaks.” ([Mt 12:34;][15:11]) Thus one must be careful not to let anything come forth from the mouth without thought, without considering the consequences. This requires that the person use his mind to apply the good things learned from God’s Word.—[Pr 13:3;][21:23].

^ (Ps. 34:1) I will praise Jehovah at all times; His praise will be on my lips constantly.

^ (Ps. 51:15) O Jehovah, open my lips, So that my mouth may declare your praise.

^ (Ps. 71:8) My mouth is filled with your praise; All day long I tell about your splendor.

^ (Ps. 145:21) My mouth will declare the praise of Jehovah; Let every living thing* praise his holy name forever and ever.

Lit., “all flesh.”

^ (Ps. 150:6) Every breathing thing—let it praise Jah. Praise Jah!*

Or “Hallelujah!” “Jah” is a shortened form of the name Jehovah.

^ (Rom. 10:10) For with the heart one exercises faith for righteousness, but with the mouth one makes public declaration for salvation.

^ (Ex. 4:11, 12) Jehovah said to him: “Who made a mouth for man, or who makes them speechless, deaf, clear-sighted, or blind? Is it not I, Jehovah? 12 So go now, and I will be with you as you speak,* and I will teach you what you should say.”

Lit., “with your mouth.”

^ (Ex. 4:15) So you must speak to him and put the words in his mouth, and I will be with you and him as you speak, and I will teach you men what to do.

^ (Jer. 1:9) Then Jehovah stretched out his hand and touched my mouth. And Jehovah said to me: “I have put my words in your mouth.

^ (Num. 22:28) Finally Jehovah caused the donkey to speak,* and it said to Baʹlaam: “What have I done to you to make you beat me these three times?”

Lit., “opened the mouth of the female donkey.”

^ (Num. 22:30) Then the donkey said to Baʹlaam: “Am I not your donkey that you have ridden on all your life until today? Have I ever treated you this way before?” He replied: “No!”

^ (2 Pet. 2:15, 16) Abandoning the straight path, they have been led astray. They have followed the path of Baʹlaam the son of Beʹor, who loved the reward of wrongdoing, 16 but was reproved for his own violation of what was right. A voiceless beast of burden speaking with a human voice hindered the prophet’s mad course.

^ (2 Tim. 3:16, 17) All Scripture is inspired of God and beneficial for teaching, for reproving, for setting things straight,* for disciplining in righteousness, 17 so that the man of God may be fully competent, completely equipped for every good work.

Or “correcting.”

^ (Rom. 10:6-9) But the righteousness resulting from faith says: “Do not say in your heart, ‘Who will ascend into heaven?’ that is, to bring Christ down, 7 or, ‘Who will descend into the abyss?’ that is, to bring Christ up from the dead.” 8 But what does it say? “The word is near you, in your own mouth and in your own heart”; that is, “the word” of faith, which we are preaching. 9 For if you publicly declare with your mouth that Jesus is Lord, and exercise faith in your heart that God raised him up from the dead, you will be saved.

^ (Deut. 30:11-14) “Now this commandment that I am commanding you today is not too difficult for you, nor is it beyond your reach.* 12 It is not in the heavens, so that you have to say, ‘Who will ascend to the heavens and get it for us, so that we may hear it and observe it?’ 13 Nor is it on the other side of the sea, so that you have to say, ‘Who will cross over to the other side of the sea and get it for us, so that we may hear it and observe it?’ 14 For the word is very near you, in your own mouth and in your own heart, so that you may do it.

Lit., “nor is it far away.”

^ (Prov. 10:11) The mouth of the righteous one is a source of life, But the mouth of the wicked conceals violence.

^ (Ps. 141:3) Station a guard for my mouth, O Jehovah, Do set a watch over the door of my lips.

^ (Prov. 13:3) The one guarding his mouth* protects his life,* But the one opening his lips wide will come to ruin.

Or “what he says.”

Or “soul.”

^ (Prov. 21:23) The one guarding his mouth and his tongue Keeps himself* out of trouble.

Or “his soul.”

^ (Prov. 10:14) Those who are wise treasure up knowledge, But the mouth of the fool invites ruin.

^ (Prov. 18:7) The mouth of the stupid is his ruin, And his lips are a snare for his life.*

Or “soul.”

^ (Matt. 12:36, 37) I tell you that men will render an account on Judgment Day for every unprofitable saying that they speak; 37 for by your words you will be declared righteous, and by your words you will be condemned.”

^ (Eccl. 5:4-6) Whenever you make a vow to God, do not delay to pay it, for he finds no pleasure in the stupid ones. What you vow, pay. 5 Better for you not to vow than to vow and not pay. 6 Do not allow your mouth to cause you* to sin, and do not say before the angel* that it was a mistake. Why make the true God indignant over what you say so that he has to destroy the work of your hands?

Lit., “your flesh.”

Or “messenger.”

^ (Prov. 26:28) A lying tongue hates those crushed by it, And a flattering mouth causes ruin.

^ (Ps. 39:1) I said: “I will guard my step To avoid sinning with my tongue. I will guard my mouth with a muzzle As long as anyone wicked is in my presence.”

^ (Isa. 53:7) He was oppressed and he let himself be afflicted, But he would not open his mouth. He was brought like a sheep to the slaughter, Like a ewe that is silent before its shearers, And he would not open his mouth.

^ (Acts 8:32) Now this was the passage of Scripture that he was reading: “Like a sheep he was brought to the slaughter, and like a lamb that is silent before its shearer, so he does not open his mouth.

^ (1 Pet. 2:23) When he was being insulted,* he did not insult* in return. When he was suffering, he did not threaten, but he entrusted himself to the One who judges righteously.

Or “reviled.”

Or “revile.”

^ (Matt. 12:34) Offspring of vipers, how can you speak good things when you are wicked? For out of the abundance of the heart the mouth speaks.

^ (Matt. 15:11) It is not what enters into a man’s mouth that defiles him, but it is what comes out of his mouth that defiles him.”

^ (Prov. 13:3) The one guarding his mouth* protects his life,* But the one opening his lips wide will come to ruin.

Or “what he says.”

Or “soul.”

^ (Prov. 21:23) The one guarding his mouth and his tongue Keeps himself* out of trouble.

Or “his soul.”

^ ***fg lesson 9***

Jehovah created men and women to fill complementary roles in marriage. ([Genesis 2:18]) As family head, a husband should take the lead in providing materially for his family and in teaching them about God. He should be self-sacrificing in his love for his wife. Husbands and wives should love and respect each other. Since all husbands and wives are imperfect, learning to forgive is a key to happiness in marriage.—Read Ephesians 4:31, 32; 5:22-25, 33; 1 Peter 3:7.

^ par. 3 (Gen. 2:18) Then Jehovah God said: “It is not good for the man to continue to be alone. I am going to make a helper for him, as a complement of him.”

^ par. 3 (Eph. 4:31, 32) Put away from yourselves every kind of malicious bitterness, anger, wrath, screaming, and abusive speech, as well as everything injurious. 32 But become kind to one another, tenderly compassionate, freely forgiving one another just as God also by Christ freely forgave you.

^ par. 3 (Eph. 5:22-25) Let wives be in subjection to their husbands as to the Lord, 23 because a husband is head of his wife just as the Christ is head of the congregation, he being a savior of this body. 24 In fact, as the congregation is in subjection to the Christ, wives should also be to their husbands in everything. 25 Husbands, continue loving your wives, just as the Christ also loved the congregation and gave himself up for it,

^ par. 3 (Eph. 5:33) Nevertheless, each one of you must love his wife as he does himself; on the other hand, the wife should have deep respect for her husband.

^ par. 3 (1 Pet. 3:7) You husbands, in the same way, continue dwelling with them according to knowledge.* Assign them honor as to a weaker vessel, the feminine one, since they are also heirs with you of the undeserved favor of life, in order for your prayers not to be hindered.

Or “showing them consideration; understanding them.”

^ ***sn song 99 Praising Earth’s New King***

Song 99

Praising Earth’s New King

(Revelation 7:9)

1. A multitude is gathering

from ev’ry tribe and nation,

Collected by the Christ and his

anointed congregation.

God’s Kingdom has been brought to birth;

His will shall soon be done on earth.

This hope is a gift of priceless worth,

giving joy and consolation.

(CHORUS)

Praise our God, Jehovah;

Praise his Son, Christ Jesus,

Who through the ransom have set us free.

Now we have the hope to live on the earth

And serve God eternally.

2. We hail the Christ, our reigning King,

with sounds of jubilation.

This Prince of Peace shall do God’s will

and bring about salvation.

We see the joys that lie ahead:

An earth released from fear and dread,

The grand resurrection of the dead.

What a time for exultation!

(CHORUS)

Praise our God, Jehovah;

Praise his Son, Christ Jesus,

Who through the ransom have set us free.

Now we have the hope to live on the earth

And serve God eternally.

(See also [Ps. 2:6;][45:1;][Isa. 9:6;][John 6:40].)

^ (Rev. 7:9) After this I saw, and look! a great crowd, which no man was able to number, out of all nations and tribes and peoples and tongues,* standing before the throne and before the Lamb, dressed in white robes; and there were palm branches in their hands.

Or “languages.”

^ (Ps. 2:6) Saying: “I myself have installed my king On Zion, my holy mountain.”

^ (Ps. 45:1) My heart is stirred by something good. I say: “My song is* about a king.” May my tongue be the stylus* of a skilled copyist.*

Lit., “My works are.”

Or “pen.”

Or “scribe.”

^ (Isa. 9:6) For a child has been born to us, A son has been given to us; And the rulership* will rest on his shoulder. His name will be called Wonderful Counselor, Mighty God, Eternal Father, Prince of Peace.

Or “government; princely rule.”

^ (John 6:40) For this is the will of my Father, that everyone who recognizes the Son and exercises faith in him should have everlasting life, and I will resurrect him on the last day.”

^ ***inv p. 2 You Are Invited***

AT OUR PUBLIC MEETINGS

Why attend these programs?

To learn how the Bible relates to our times.

To learn how to apply its teachings in our life.

To strengthen our faith in God.

To enjoy upbuilding association with loving, caring people.

Everyone is welcome, and no collections are taken.

Where and when are the meetings held?

To find a Kingdom Hall near you, go to www.jw.org. (Look under ABOUT US > MEETINGS)

^ ***kr pp. 9-12 “Let Your Kingdom Come”***

When Would God’s Kingdom Be Established?

11. What did Jesus indicate about the establishment of God’s Kingdom?

11 Jesus indicated that the Kingdom would not be established in the first century C.E., despite the expectations of some of his disciples. ([Acts 1:6]) Consider what he said in two different parables given less than two years apart.

12. How does the parable of the wheat and the weeds indicate that the Kingdom was not established in the first century C.E.?

12 The parable of the wheat and the weeds. (Read Matthew 13:24-30.) After relating this parable, perhaps in the spring of 31 C.E., Jesus explained it to his disciples. (Matt. 13:36-43) Here is the gist of the parable and its meaning: Following the death of the apostles, the Devil would sow weeds (imitation Christians) in among wheat (“sons of the Kingdom,” or anointed Christians). Both the wheat and the weeds would be allowed to grow together during a growing season that would continue until the harvest, which is “a conclusion of a system of things.” After the beginning of the harvest season, the weeds would be collected. Then, the wheat would be gathered. The parable thus indicates that the Kingdom would be established, not in the first century C.E., but only after the growing season ended. As matters worked out, the growing season ended and the harvest season began in 1914.

THE WHEAT AND THE WEEDS

(Matt. 13:24-30)

Jesus indicated that the Kingdom would not be established in the first century C.E., despite the expectations of some of his disciples

33 C.E. Sowing Begins

‘A man sowed fine seed in his field’ ([Matt. 13:24])

‘While men were sleeping, the enemy oversowed weeds’ ([Matt. 13:25])

“Both grow together until the harvest” ([Matt. 13:30])

1914 Harvest Season Begins

The weeds are collected and bundled ([Matt. 13:30])

13. How did Jesus illustrate that he would not be installed as Messianic King immediately after his return to heaven?

13 The parable of the minas. (Read Luke 19:11-13.) Jesus gave this parable in 33 C.E. on his way to Jerusalem for the last time. Some of his listeners thought that he would set up his Kingdom as soon as they arrived in Jerusalem. To correct that notion and to show that the establishment of the Kingdom was yet a long way off, Jesus compared himself to “a man of noble birth” who had to travel “to a distant land to secure kingly power.”* In Jesus’ case, the “distant land” was heaven, where he would receive power as King from his Father. But Jesus knew that he would not be installed as Messianic King immediately after his return to heaven. Instead, he would sit at God’s right hand and wait until the appointed time. As it turned out, that wait lasted for many centuries.—Ps. 110:1, 2; Matt. 22:43, 44; Heb. 10:12, 13.

When Will God’s Kingdom Come?

14. (a) How did Jesus answer the question that four of his apostles asked him? (b) What does the fulfillment of Jesus’ prophecy tell us about his presence and the Kingdom?

14 A few days before Jesus was put to death, four of his apostles asked him: “What will be the sign of your presence and of the conclusion of the system of things?” ([Matt. 24:3;][Mark 13:4]) Jesus answered by relating the extensive prophecy that is recorded in Matthew chapters 24 and [25]. Jesus detailed various global events that would serve as a sign identifying a time period called his “presence.” The start of his presence would coincide with the establishment of the Kingdom; and the culmination of his presence, with the coming of the Kingdom. We have ample proof that Jesus’ prophecy has been undergoing fulfillment since 1914.* Hence, that year marked the start of his presence and the establishment of the Kingdom.

15, 16. To whom do the words “this generation” refer?

15 When, though, will God’s Kingdom finally come? Jesus did not reveal exactly when that would happen. ([Matt. 24:36]) But he did say something that should assure us that it is very near indeed. Jesus indicated that the Kingdom would come after “this generation” witnessed the fulfillment of the prophetic sign. (Read Matthew 24:32-34.) To whom does the expression “this generation” refer? Let us take a closer look at Jesus’ words.

16 “This generation.” Did Jesus have in mind unbelievers? No. Consider his audience. Jesus related this prophecy to a few apostles who had “approached him privately.” ([Matt. 24:3]) The apostles would soon be anointed with holy spirit. Note also the context. Before he spoke about “this generation,” Jesus said: “Now learn this illustration from the fig tree: Just as soon as its young branch grows tender and sprouts its leaves, you know that summer is near. Likewise also you, when you see all these things, know that he is near at the doors.” Jesus’ anointed followers—not unbelievers—would see the things he foretold and would discern their significance, namely, that Jesus “is near at the doors.” Therefore, when Jesus spoke of “this generation,” he had in mind his anointed followers.

GENERATION

(Matt. 24:32-34)

Jesus indicated that the Kingdom will come after “this generation” has witnessed the fulfillment of the prophetic sign (See paragraphs 17, 18)

GROUP 1: Anointed ones who saw the beginning of the fulfillment of the sign in 1914

GROUP 2: Anointed ones who were contemporaries of the first group; some of these will live to see the great tribulation

17. What is the meaning of the expressions “generation” and “all these things”?

17 “Will by no means pass away until all these things happen.” How will those words prove true? To answer that, we need to know two things: the meaning both of “generation” and of “all these things.” The term “generation” often refers to people of varying ages whose lives overlap during a particular period of time. A generation is not overly long, and it comes to an end. ([Ex. 1:6]) The expression “all these things” includes all the foretold events during Jesus’ presence, from its beginning in 1914 until its culmination at the “great tribulation.”—[Matt. 24:21].

18, 19. How may we understand Jesus’ words about “this generation,” and what may we conclude?

18 How, then, may we understand Jesus’ words about “this generation”? The generation consists of two overlapping groups of anointed ones—the first is made up of anointed ones who saw the beginning of the fulfillment of the sign in 1914 and the second, anointed ones who for a time were contemporaries of the first group. At least some of those in the second group will live to see the beginning of the coming tribulation. The two groups form one generation because their lives as anointed Christians overlapped for a time.*

19 What may we conclude? Well, we know that the sign of Jesus’ presence in Kingdom power is clearly evident around the globe. We also see that the anointed ones who are still alive and part of “this generation” are getting on in years; yet, they will not all die off before the great tribulation begins. Therefore, we can conclude that very soon indeed God’s Kingdom will come and exercise its rule over the earth! How thrilling it will be to witness the fulfillment of the prayer that Jesus taught us: “Let your Kingdom come”!

20. What vital field of study will be discussed in this publication, and what will be examined in the next chapter?

20 Let us never forget the words that Jehovah himself spoke from heaven regarding his Son: “Listen to him.” As true Christians, we are eager to heed that divine direction. We are keenly interested in everything that Jesus said and taught about God’s Kingdom. What that Kingdom has already accomplished and will do in the future is the vital field of study that will be discussed in this publication. The next chapter will examine the exciting developments that surrounded the birth of God’s Kingdom in heaven.

^ par. 11 (Acts 1:6) So when they had assembled, they asked him: “Lord, are you restoring the kingdom to Israel at this time?”

^ par. 12 (Matt. 13:24-30) He presented another illustration to them, saying: “The Kingdom of the heavens may be likened to a man who sowed fine seed in his field. 25 While men were sleeping, his enemy came and oversowed weeds in among the wheat and left. 26 When the stalk sprouted and produced fruit, then the weeds also appeared. 27 So the slaves of the master of the house came and said to him, ‘Master, did you not sow fine seed in your field? How, then, does it have weeds?’ 28 He said to them, ‘An enemy, a man, did this.’ The slaves said to him, ‘Do you want us, then, to go out and collect them?’ 29 He said, ‘No, for fear that while collecting the weeds, you uproot the wheat with them. 30 Let both grow together until the harvest, and in the harvest season, I will tell the reapers: First collect the weeds and bind them in bundles to burn them up; then gather the wheat into my storehouse.’”

^ par. 12 (Matt. 13:36-43) Then after dismissing the crowds, he went into the house. His disciples came to him and said: “Explain to us the illustration of the weeds in the field.” 37 In response he said: “The sower of the fine seed is the Son of man; 38 the field is the world. As for the fine seed, these are the sons of the Kingdom, but the weeds are the sons of the wicked one, 39 and the enemy who sowed them is the Devil. The harvest is a conclusion of a system of things,* and the reapers are angels. 40 Therefore, just as the weeds are collected and burned with fire, so it will be in the conclusion of the system of things.* 41 The Son of man will send his angels, and they will collect out from his Kingdom all things that cause stumbling and people who practice lawlessness, 42 and they will pitch them into the fiery furnace. There is where their weeping and the gnashing of their teeth will be. 43 At that time the righteous ones will shine as brightly as the sun in the Kingdom of their Father. Let the one who has ears listen.

Or “an age.” See Glossary.

Or “the age.” See Glossary.

^ (Matt. 13:24-30) He presented another illustration to them, saying: “The Kingdom of the heavens may be likened to a man who sowed fine seed in his field. 25 While men were sleeping, his enemy came and oversowed weeds in among the wheat and left. 26 When the stalk sprouted and produced fruit, then the weeds also appeared. 27 So the slaves of the master of the house came and said to him, ‘Master, did you not sow fine seed in your field? How, then, does it have weeds?’ 28 He said to them, ‘An enemy, a man, did this.’ The slaves said to him, ‘Do you want us, then, to go out and collect them?’ 29 He said, ‘No, for fear that while collecting the weeds, you uproot the wheat with them. 30 Let both grow together until the harvest, and in the harvest season, I will tell the reapers: First collect the weeds and bind them in bundles to burn them up; then gather the wheat into my storehouse.’”

^ (Matt. 13:24) He presented another illustration to them, saying: “The Kingdom of the heavens may be likened to a man who sowed fine seed in his field.

^ (Matt. 13:25) While men were sleeping, his enemy came and oversowed weeds in among the wheat and left.

^ (Matt. 13:30) Let both grow together until the harvest, and in the harvest season, I will tell the reapers: First collect the weeds and bind them in bundles to burn them up; then gather the wheat into my storehouse.’”

^ (Matt. 13:30) Let both grow together until the harvest, and in the harvest season, I will tell the reapers: First collect the weeds and bind them in bundles to burn them up; then gather the wheat into my storehouse.’”

^ par. 13 (Luke 19:11-13) While they were listening to these things, he told another illustration, because he was near Jerusalem and they thought that the Kingdom of God was going to appear instantly. 12 So he said: “A man of noble birth traveled to a distant land to secure kingly power for himself and to return. 13 Calling ten of his slaves, he gave them ten miʹnas* and told them, ‘Do business with these until I come.’

A Greek mina weighed 340 g (10.9 oz t) and was reckoned to be worth 100 drachmas. See App. B14.

^ par. 13 (Ps. 110:1, 2) Jehovah declared to my Lord: “Sit at my right hand Until I place your enemies as a stool for your feet.”  2 Jehovah will extend the scepter of your power out of Zion, saying: “Go subduing in the midst of your enemies.”

^ par. 13 (Matt. 22:43, 44) He asked them: “How is it, then, that David under inspiration calls him Lord, saying, 44 ‘Jehovah* said to my Lord: “Sit at my right hand until I put your enemies beneath your feet”’?

See App. A5.

^ par. 13 (Heb. 10:12, 13) But this man offered one sacrifice for sins for all time and sat down at the right hand of God, 13 from then on waiting until his enemies should be placed as a stool for his feet.

^ par. 14 (Matt. 24:3) While he was sitting on the Mount of Olives, the disciples approached him privately, saying: “Tell us, when will these things be, and what will be the sign of your presence* and of the conclusion of the system of things?”*

See Glossary.

Or “the age.” See Glossary.

^ par. 14 (Mark 13:4) “Tell us, when will these things be, and what will be the sign when all these things are to come to a conclusion?”

^ par. 14 (Matt. 24:1-51) Now as Jesus was departing from the temple, his disciples approached to show him the buildings of the temple. 2 In response he said to them: “Do you not see all these things? Truly I say to you, by no means will a stone be left here upon a stone and not be thrown down.” 3 While he was sitting on the Mount of Olives, the disciples approached him privately, saying: “Tell us, when will these things be, and what will be the sign of your presence* and of the conclusion of the system of things?”* 4 In answer Jesus said to them: “Look out that nobody misleads you, 5 for many will come on the basis of my name, saying, ‘I am the Christ,’ and will mislead many. 6 You are going to hear of wars and reports of wars. See that you are not alarmed, for these things must take place, but the end is not yet. 7 “For nation will rise against nation and kingdom against kingdom, and there will be food shortages and earthquakes in one place after another. 8 All these things are a beginning of pangs of distress. 9 “Then people will hand you over to tribulation and will kill you, and you will be hated by all the nations on account of my name. 10 Then, too, many will be stumbled and will betray one another and will hate one another. 11 Many false prophets will arise and mislead many; 12 and because of the increasing of lawlessness, the love of the greater number will grow cold. 13 But the one who has endured* to the end will be saved. 14 And this good news of the Kingdom will be preached in all the inhabited earth for a witness to all the nations, and then the end will come. 15 “Therefore, when you catch sight of the disgusting thing that causes desolation, as spoken about by Daniel the prophet, standing in a holy place (let the reader use discernment), 16 then let those in Ju·deʹa begin fleeing to the mountains. 17 Let the man on the housetop not come down to take the goods out of his house, 18 and let the man in the field not return to pick up his outer garment. 19 Woe to the pregnant women and those nursing a baby in those days! 20 Keep praying that your flight may not occur in wintertime nor on the Sabbath day; 21 for then there will be great tribulation such as has not occurred since the world’s beginning until now, no, nor will occur again. 22 In fact, unless those days were cut short, no flesh would be saved; but on account of the chosen ones those days will be cut short. 23 “Then if anyone says to you, ‘Look! Here is the Christ,’ or, ‘There!’ do not believe it. 24 For false Christs and false prophets will arise and will perform great signs and wonders so as to mislead, if possible, even the chosen ones. 25 Look! I have forewarned you. 26 Therefore, if people say to you, ‘Look! He is in the wilderness,’ do not go out; ‘Look! He is in the inner rooms,’ do not believe it. 27 For just as the lightning comes out of the east and shines over to the west, so the presence* of the Son of man will be. 28 Wherever the carcass is, there the eagles will be gathered together. 29 “Immediately after the tribulation of those days, the sun will be darkened, and the moon will not give its light, and the stars will fall from heaven, and the powers of the heavens will be shaken. 30 Then the sign of the Son of man will appear in heaven, and all the tribes of the earth will beat themselves in grief, and they will see the Son of man coming on the clouds of heaven with power and great glory. 31 And he will send out his angels with a great trumpet sound, and they will gather his chosen ones together from the four winds, from one extremity of the heavens to their other extremity. 32 “Now learn this illustration from the fig tree: Just as soon as its young branch grows tender and sprouts its leaves, you know that summer is near. 33 Likewise also you, when you see all these things, know that he is near at the doors. 34 Truly I say to you that this generation will by no means pass away until all these things happen. 35 Heaven and earth will pass away, but my words will by no means pass away. 36 “Concerning that day and hour nobody knows, neither the angels of the heavens nor the Son, but only the Father. 37 For just as the days of Noah were, so the presence* of the Son of man will be. 38 For as they were in those days before the Flood, eating and drinking, men marrying and women being given in marriage, until the day that Noah entered into the ark, 39 and they took no note until the Flood came and swept them all away, so the presence of the Son of man will be. 40 Then two men will be in the field; one will be taken along and the other abandoned. 41 Two women will be grinding at the hand mill; one will be taken along and the other abandoned. 42 Keep on the watch, therefore, because you do not know on what day your Lord is coming. 43 “But know one thing: If the householder had known in what watch* the thief was coming, he would have kept awake and not allowed his house to be broken into. 44 On this account, you too prove yourselves ready, because the Son of man is coming at an hour that you do not think to be it. 45 “Who really is the faithful and discreet* slave whom his master appointed over his domestics, to give them their food at the proper time? 46 Happy is that slave if his master on coming finds him doing so! 47 Truly I say to you, he will appoint him over all his belongings. 48 “But if ever that evil slave says in his heart, ‘My master is delaying,’ 49 and he starts to beat his fellow slaves and to eat and drink with the confirmed drunkards, 50 the master of that slave will come on a day that he does not expect and in an hour that he does not know, 51 and he will punish him with the greatest severity and will assign him his place with the hypocrites. There is where his weeping and the gnashing of his teeth will be.

See Glossary.

Or “the age.” See Glossary.

Or “who endures.”

See Glossary.

See Glossary.

Or “at what time of night.”

Or “wise.”

^ par. 14 (Matt. 25:1-46) “Then the Kingdom of the heavens may be likened to ten virgins who took their lamps and went out to meet the bridegroom. 2 Five of them were foolish, and five were discreet.* 3 For the foolish took their lamps but took no oil with them, 4 whereas the discreet took oil in their flasks along with their lamps. 5 While the bridegroom was delaying, they all became drowsy and fell asleep. 6 Right in the middle of the night there was a shout: ‘Here is the bridegroom! Go out to meet him.’ 7 Then all those virgins got up and put their lamps in order. 8 The foolish said to the discreet, ‘Give us some of your oil, because our lamps are about to go out.’ 9 The discreet answered, saying: ‘Perhaps there may not be enough for both us and you. Go instead to those who sell it, and buy some for yourselves.’ 10 While they were going off to buy it, the bridegroom came. The virgins who were ready went in with him to the marriage feast, and the door was shut. 11 Afterward, the rest of the virgins also came, saying, ‘Sir, Sir, open to us!’ 12 In answer he said, ‘I tell you the truth, I do not know you.’ 13 “Keep on the watch, therefore, because you know neither the day nor the hour. 14 “For it is just like a man about to travel abroad who summoned his slaves and entrusted his belongings to them. 15 He gave five talents* to one, two to another, and one to still another, to each according to his own ability, and he went abroad. 16 Immediately the one who received the five talents went and did business with them and gained five more. 17 Likewise, the one who received the two gained two more. 18 But the slave who received just one went off and dug in the ground and hid his master’s money.* 19 “After a long time, the master of those slaves came and settled accounts with them. 20 So the one who had received the five talents came forward and brought five additional talents, saying, ‘Master, you entrusted five talents to me; see, I gained five talents more.’ 21 His master said to him: ‘Well done, good and faithful slave! You were faithful over a few things. I will appoint you over many things. Enter into the joy of your master.’ 22 Next the one who had received the two talents came forward and said, ‘Master, you entrusted two talents to me; see, I gained two talents more.’ 23 His master said to him: ‘Well done, good and faithful slave! You were faithful over a few things. I will appoint you over many things. Enter into the joy of your master.’ 24 “Finally the slave who had received the one talent came forward and said: ‘Master, I knew you to be a demanding man, reaping where you did not sow and gathering where you did not winnow. 25 So I grew afraid and went and hid your talent in the ground. Here, you have what is yours.’ 26 In reply his master said to him: ‘Wicked and sluggish slave, you knew, did you, that I reaped where I did not sow and gathered where I did not winnow? 27 Well, then, you should have deposited my money* with the bankers, and on my coming I would have received it back with interest. 28 “‘Therefore, take the talent away from him and give it to the one who has the ten talents. 29 For to everyone who has, more will be given, and he will have an abundance. But the one who does not have, even what he has will be taken away from him. 30 And throw the good-for-nothing slave out into the darkness outside. There is where his weeping and the gnashing of his teeth will be.’ 31 “When the Son of man comes in his glory, and all the angels with him, then he will sit down on his glorious throne. 32 All the nations will be gathered before him, and he will separate people one from another, just as a shepherd separates the sheep from the goats. 33 And he will put the sheep on his right hand, but the goats on his left. 34 “Then the King will say to those on his right: ‘Come, you who have been blessed by my Father, inherit the Kingdom prepared for you from the founding of the world. 35 For I became hungry and you gave me something to eat; I was thirsty and you gave me something to drink. I was a stranger and you received me hospitably; 36 naked* and you clothed me. I fell sick and you looked after me. I was in prison and you visited me.’ 37 Then the righteous ones will answer him with the words: ‘Lord, when did we see you hungry and feed you, or thirsty and give you something to drink? 38 When did we see you a stranger and receive you hospitably, or naked and clothe you? 39 When did we see you sick or in prison and visit you?’ 40 In reply the King will say to them, ‘Truly I say to you, to the extent that you did it to one of the least of these my brothers, you did it to me.’ 41 “Then he will say to those on his left: ‘Go away from me, you who have been cursed, into the everlasting fire prepared for the Devil and his angels. 42 For I became hungry, but you gave me nothing to eat; and I was thirsty, but you gave me nothing to drink. 43 I was a stranger, but you did not receive me hospitably; naked, but you did not clothe me; sick and in prison, but you did not look after me.’ 44 Then they too will answer with the words: ‘Lord, when did we see you hungry or thirsty or a stranger or naked or sick or in prison and did not minister to you?’ 45 Then he will answer them, saying: ‘Truly I say to you, to the extent that you did not do it to one of these least ones, you did not do it to me.’ 46 These will depart into everlasting cutting-off,* but the righteous ones into everlasting life.”

Or “wise.”

A Greek talent equaled 20.4 kg (654 oz t). See App. B14.

Lit., “silver.”

Lit., “silver.”

Or “not sufficiently dressed.”

That is, from life. Lit., “lopping off; pruning.”

^ par. 15 (Matt. 24:36) “Concerning that day and hour nobody knows, neither the angels of the heavens nor the Son, but only the Father.

^ par. 15 (Matt. 24:32-34) “Now learn this illustration from the fig tree: Just as soon as its young branch grows tender and sprouts its leaves, you know that summer is near. 33 Likewise also you, when you see all these things, know that he is near at the doors. 34 Truly I say to you that this generation will by no means pass away until all these things happen.

^ par. 16 (Matt. 24:3) While he was sitting on the Mount of Olives, the disciples approached him privately, saying: “Tell us, when will these things be, and what will be the sign of your presence* and of the conclusion of the system of things?”*

See Glossary.

Or “the age.” See Glossary.

^ (Matt. 24:32-34) “Now learn this illustration from the fig tree: Just as soon as its young branch grows tender and sprouts its leaves, you know that summer is near. 33 Likewise also you, when you see all these things, know that he is near at the doors. 34 Truly I say to you that this generation will by no means pass away until all these things happen.

^ par. 17 (Ex. 1:6) Joseph eventually died, and also all his brothers and all that generation.

^ par. 17 (Matt. 24:21) for then there will be great tribulation such as has not occurred since the world’s beginning until now, no, nor will occur again.

^ par. 13 Jesus’ parable may well have reminded his listeners of Archelaus, a son of Herod the Great. Before Herod died, he designated Archelaus as heir to rulership over Judea and other areas. However, before he could begin ruling, Archelaus first had to make the long journey to Rome in order to secure the approval of Augustus Caesar.

^ par. 14 For more information, see chapter 9 of the book What Does the Bible Really Teach?

^ par. 18 Anyone who was anointed after the death of the last of the anointed ones in the first group—that is, after those who witnessed the “beginning of pangs of distress” in 1914—would not be part of “this generation.”—[Matt. 24:8].

^ (Matt. 24:8) All these things are a beginning of pangs of distress.

^ ***kr p. 10 “Let Your Kingdom Come”***

THE WHEAT AND THE WEEDS

(Matt. 13:24-30)

Jesus indicated that the Kingdom would not be established in the first century C.E., despite the expectations of some of his disciples

33 C.E. Sowing Begins

‘A man sowed fine seed in his field’ ([Matt. 13:24])

‘While men were sleeping, the enemy oversowed weeds’ ([Matt. 13:25])

“Both grow together until the harvest” ([Matt. 13:30])

1914 Harvest Season Begins

The weeds are collected and bundled ([Matt. 13:30])

^ (Matt. 13:24-30) He presented another illustration to them, saying: “The Kingdom of the heavens may be likened to a man who sowed fine seed in his field. 25 While men were sleeping, his enemy came and oversowed weeds in among the wheat and left. 26 When the stalk sprouted and produced fruit, then the weeds also appeared. 27 So the slaves of the master of the house came and said to him, ‘Master, did you not sow fine seed in your field? How, then, does it have weeds?’ 28 He said to them, ‘An enemy, a man, did this.’ The slaves said to him, ‘Do you want us, then, to go out and collect them?’ 29 He said, ‘No, for fear that while collecting the weeds, you uproot the wheat with them. 30 Let both grow together until the harvest, and in the harvest season, I will tell the reapers: First collect the weeds and bind them in bundles to burn them up; then gather the wheat into my storehouse.’”

^ (Matt. 13:24) He presented another illustration to them, saying: “The Kingdom of the heavens may be likened to a man who sowed fine seed in his field.

^ (Matt. 13:25) While men were sleeping, his enemy came and oversowed weeds in among the wheat and left.

^ (Matt. 13:30) Let both grow together until the harvest, and in the harvest season, I will tell the reapers: First collect the weeds and bind them in bundles to burn them up; then gather the wheat into my storehouse.’”

^ (Matt. 13:30) Let both grow together until the harvest, and in the harvest season, I will tell the reapers: First collect the weeds and bind them in bundles to burn them up; then gather the wheat into my storehouse.’”

^ ***kr p. 12 “Let Your Kingdom Come”***

GENERATION

(Matt. 24:32-34)

Jesus indicated that the Kingdom will come after “this generation” has witnessed the fulfillment of the prophetic sign (See paragraphs 17, 18)

GROUP 1: Anointed ones who saw the beginning of the fulfillment of the sign in 1914

GROUP 2: Anointed ones who were contemporaries of the first group; some of these will live to see the great tribulation

^ (Matt. 24:32-34) “Now learn this illustration from the fig tree: Just as soon as its young branch grows tender and sprouts its leaves, you know that summer is near. 33 Likewise also you, when you see all these things, know that he is near at the doors. 34 Truly I say to you that this generation will by no means pass away until all these things happen.

^ ***snnw song 145 Preparing to Preach***

Song 145

Preparing to Preach

Download:

Lyrics Only

Lead Sheet

(Jeremiah 1:17)

Morning comes.

Soon we will be

On our way to preach good news.

But it’s dark outside,

And the rain starts to fall.

It would be easy to stay inside,

sleepy-eyed.

(CHORUS)

Positive thoughts and preparation,

Praying that we’ll succeed;

This can provide the inspiration,

We’ll surely need.

We’re not alone; the angels guide us.

Jesus commands them all.

And with a loyal friend beside us,

We’ll never fall.

Soon we’ll see

Joy come our way

If these things we keep in mind.

And Jehovah sees

Ev’ry effort we make,

And he remembers the love we show;

this we know.

(CHORUS)

Positive thoughts and preparation,

Praying that we’ll succeed;

This can provide the inspiration,

We’ll surely need.

We’re not alone; the angels guide us.

Jesus commands them all.

And with a loyal friend beside us,

We’ll never fall.

(See also [Eccl. 11:4;][Matt. 10:5,][7;][Luke 10:1;][Titus 2:14].)

^ (Jer. 1:17) But you should prepare for action,* And you must stand up and tell them everything that I command you. Do not be terrified of them, So that I do not terrify you before them.

Lit., “gird up your hips.”

^ (Eccl. 11:4) The one who watches the wind will not sow seed, and the one who looks at the clouds will not reap.

^ (Matt. 10:5) These 12 Jesus sent out, giving them these instructions: “Do not go off into the road of the nations, and do not enter any Sa·marʹi·tan city;

^ (Matt. 10:7) As you go, preach, saying: ‘The Kingdom of the heavens has drawn near.’

^ (Luke 10:1) After these things the Lord designated 70 others and sent them out by twos ahead of him into every city and place where he himself was to go.

^ (Titus 2:14) who gave himself for us to set us free* from every sort of lawlessness and to cleanse for himself a people who are his own special possession, zealous for fine works.

Lit., “to ransom us; to redeem us.”

^ (Pss. 142:0-150:6) Masʹkil.* Of David when he was in the cave. A prayer. 142 With my voice I call to Jehovah for help; With my voice I plead with Jehovah for favor.  2 Before him I pour out my concern; Before him I tell about my distress  3 When my spirit* fails within me. Then you watch my roadway. In the path where I walk, They hide a trap for me.  4 Look at my right hand and see That no one cares about* me. There is nowhere I can flee; No one is concerned about me.*  5 I call to you, O Jehovah, for help. I say: “You are my refuge, All I have* in the land of the living.”  6 Pay attention to my cry for help, For I have been brought very low. Rescue me from my persecutors, For they are stronger than I am.  7 Bring me* out of the dungeon To praise your name. May the righteous gather around me Because you deal kindly with me.

A melody of David. 143 O Jehovah, hear my prayer; Listen to my plea for help. In your faithfulness and in your righteousness, answer me.  2 Do not enter into judgment with your servant, For no one living can be righteous before you.  3 For the enemy pursues me;* He has crushed my life into the ground. He has caused me to dwell in darkness like those long dead.  4 My spirit* is failing; My heart is numb within me.  5 I remember the days of old; I meditate on all your activity; I eagerly ponder over* the work of your hands.  6 I spread out my hands to you; I am* like a parched land that thirsts for you. (Selah)  7 Do answer me quickly, O Jehovah; My strength* has come to an end. Do not hide your face from me, Or I will be like those going down into the pit.*  8 Let me hear your loyal love in the morning, For I trust in you. Make known to me the way I should walk, For to you I turn.*  9 Rescue me from my enemies, O Jehovah. I seek your protection. 10 Teach me to do your will, For you are my God. Your spirit is good; May it lead me on level ground.* 11 For the sake of your name, O Jehovah, preserve me alive. In your righteousness, rescue me* from distress. 12 In your loyal love, put an end to* my enemies; Destroy all those harassing me,* For I am your servant.

Of David. 144 May Jehovah, my Rock, be praised, Who trains my hands for battle, My fingers for warfare.  2 He is my loyal love and my stronghold, My secure refuge* and my rescuer, My shield and the One in whom I have taken shelter, The One subduing peoples under me.  3 O Jehovah, what is man that you should notice him, The son of mortal man that you should pay attention to him?  4 Man resembles a mere breath; His days are like a passing shadow.  5 O Jehovah, lower* your heavens and descend; Touch the mountains and make them smoke.  6 Make lightning flash and scatter the enemy; Shoot your arrows and throw them into confusion.  7 Stretch out your hands from above; Rescue me and save me from the surging waters, From the hand* of the foreigners,  8 Whose mouths speak lies And who raise their right hand to swear to what is false.*  9 O God, I will sing to you a new song. I will sing praises* to you, accompanied by a ten-stringed instrument, 10 To the One who gives victory* to kings, The One rescuing his servant David from the deadly sword. 11 Rescue me and save me from the hand of the foreigners, Whose mouths speak lies And who raise their right hand to swear to what is false. 12 Then our sons will be like young plants that grow up quickly, Our daughters like corner pillars carved for a palace. 13 Our storehouses will overflow with every kind of produce; Our flocks in our fields will multiply by the thousands, by the tens of thousands. 14 Our cattle, heavy with young, will suffer no mishap* or miscarriage; There will be no cry of distress in our public squares. 15 Happy is the people for whom it is this way! Happy is the people whose God is Jehovah!

A praise of David. 145 I will exalt you, O my God the King, I will praise your name forever and ever.  2 All day long I will praise you; I will praise your name forever and ever.  3 Jehovah is great and most worthy of praise; His greatness is unsearchable.*  4 Generation after generation will praise your works; They will tell about your mighty acts.  5 Of the glorious splendor of your majesty they will speak And on your wonderful works I will meditate.  6 They will speak about your awe-inspiring deeds,* And I will declare your greatness.  7 They will bubble over as they recall your abundant goodness, And they will shout joyfully because of your righteousness.  8 Jehovah is compassionate* and merciful, Slow to anger and great in loyal love.  9 Jehovah is good to all, And his mercy is evident in all his works. 10 All your works will glorify you, O Jehovah, And your loyal ones will praise you. 11 They will proclaim the glory of your kingship And speak about your mightiness, 12 To make known to men your mighty acts And the glorious splendor of your kingship. 13 Your kingship is an eternal kingship, And your dominion endures throughout all generations. 14 Jehovah supports all who are falling And raises up all who are bowed down. 15 All eyes look hopefully to you; You give them their food in its season. 16 You open your hand And satisfy the desire of every living thing. 17 Jehovah is righteous in all his ways And loyal in all that he does. 18 Jehovah is near to all those calling on him, To all who call on him in truth.* 19 He satisfies the desire of those who fear him; He hears their cry for help, and he rescues them. 20 Jehovah guards all those who love him, But all the wicked he will annihilate. 21 My mouth will declare the praise of Jehovah; Let every living thing* praise his holy name forever and ever.

146 Praise Jah!* Let my whole being* praise Jehovah.  2 I will praise Jehovah all my life. I will sing praises* to my God as long as I live.  3 Do not put your trust in princes* Nor in a son of man, who cannot bring salvation.  4 His spirit* goes out, he returns to the ground; On that very day his thoughts perish.  5 Happy is the one who has the God of Jacob as his helper, Whose hope is in Jehovah his God,  6 The Maker of heaven and earth, Of the sea, and of all that is in them, The One who always remains faithful,  7 The One securing justice for those defrauded, The One giving bread to the hungry. Jehovah is releasing the prisoners.*  8 Jehovah is opening the eyes of the blind; Jehovah is raising up those bowed down; Jehovah loves the righteous.  9 Jehovah is protecting the foreign residents; He sustains the fatherless child and the widow, But he thwarts the plans of the wicked.* 10 Jehovah will be King forever, Your God, O Zion, for generation after generation. Praise Jah!*

147 Praise Jah!* It is good to sing praises* to our God; How pleasant and fitting it is to praise him!  2 Jehovah is building Jerusalem; He gathers together the dispersed ones of Israel.  3 He heals the brokenhearted; He binds up their wounds.  4 He counts the number of the stars; He calls all of them by name.  5 Our Lord is great and is mighty in power; His understanding is beyond measure.  6 Jehovah raises up the meek, But he hurls the wicked to the ground.  7 Sing to Jehovah with thanksgiving; Sing praises to our God, accompanied by the harp,  8 The One who covers the heavens with clouds, The One providing rain for the earth, The One making grass sprout on the mountains.  9 To the animals he gives food, To the young ravens that call out for it. 10 He does not delight in the power of the horse; Nor is he impressed by the strong legs of a man. 11 Jehovah finds pleasure in those who fear him, In those waiting for his loyal love. 12 Glorify Jehovah, O Jerusalem. Praise your God, O Zion. 13 He makes the bars of your city gates strong; He blesses your sons within you. 14 He brings peace to your territory; He satisfies you with the finest* wheat. 15 He sends his command to the earth; His word runs swiftly. 16 He sends the snow like wool; He scatters the frost just like ashes. 17 He hurls down his hailstones* like morsels of bread. Who can withstand his cold? 18 He sends out his word, and they melt. He makes his wind blow, and the waters flow. 19 He declares his word to Jacob, His regulations and judgments to Israel. 20 He has not done so with any other nation; They know nothing about his judgments. Praise Jah!*

148 Praise Jah!* Praise Jehovah from the heavens; Praise him in the heights.  2 Praise him, all his angels. Praise him, all his army.  3 Praise him, sun and moon. Praise him, all shining stars.  4 Praise him, O highest heavens* And waters above the heavens.  5 Let them praise the name of Jehovah, For he commanded, and they were created.  6 He keeps them established forever and ever; He has issued a decree that will not pass away.  7 Praise Jehovah from the earth, You great sea creatures and all deep waters,  8 You lightning and hail, snow and thick clouds, You storm wind, carrying out his word,  9 You mountains and all you hills, You fruit trees and all you cedars, 10 You wild animals and all you domestic animals, You creeping things and winged birds, 11 You kings of the earth and all you nations, You princes and all you judges of the earth, 12 You young men and young women,* Old men and young together.* 13 Let them praise the name of Jehovah, For his name alone is unreachably high. His majesty is above earth and heaven. 14 He will exalt the strength* of his people, For the praise of all his loyal ones, Of the sons of Israel, the people close to him. Praise Jah!*

149 Praise Jah!* Sing to Jehovah a new song; Praise him in the congregation of the loyal ones.  2 Let Israel rejoice in its Grand Maker; Let the sons of Zion be joyful in their King.  3 Let them praise his name with dancing And sing praises* to him, accompanied by the tambourine and the harp.  4 For Jehovah takes pleasure in his people. He adorns the meek with salvation.  5 Let the loyal ones exult in glory; Let them shout for joy upon their beds.  6 Let the songs praising God be in their throat, And a two-edged sword be in their hand,  7 To execute vengeance on the nations And punishment on the peoples,  8 To bind their kings with shackles And their nobles with iron fetters,  9 To execute the judgment written against them. This honor belongs to all his loyal ones. Praise Jah!*

150 Praise Jah!* Praise God in his holy place. Praise him in the expanse of* his strength.  2 Praise him for his mighty works. Praise him for his exceeding greatness.  3 Praise him with the sounding of the horn. Praise him with the stringed instrument and the harp.  4 Praise him with the tambourine and the circle dance. Praise him with strings and the flute.*  5 Praise him with ringing cymbals. Praise him with crashing cymbals.  6 Every breathing thing—let it praise Jah. Praise Jah!*

See Glossary.

Or “strength.”

Lit., “recognizes.”

Or “my soul.”

Lit., “My share.”

Or “my soul.”

Or “my soul.”

Or “strength.”

Or “study.”

Or “My soul is.”

Lit., “spirit.”

Or “grave.”

Or “For I lift up my soul to you.”

Or “in the land of uprightness.”

Or “my soul.”

Lit., “silence.”

Or “my soul.”

Or “secure height.”

Or “bend.”

Or “grip.”

Lit., “And their right hand is a right hand of falsehood.”

Or “make music.”

Or “salvation.”

Or “rupture.”

Or “beyond understanding.”

Or “power.”

Or “gracious.”

Or “in sincerity.”

Lit., “all flesh.”

Or “Hallelujah!” “Jah” is a shortened form of the name Jehovah.

Or “my soul.”

Or “make music.”

Or “nobles.”

Or “breath.”

Lit., “bound ones.”

Or “makes the way of the wicked crooked.”

Or “Hallelujah!” “Jah” is a shortened form of the name Jehovah.

Or “Hallelujah!” “Jah” is a shortened form of the name Jehovah.

Or “make music.”

Lit., “the fat of.”

Or “ice.”

Or “Hallelujah!” “Jah” is a shortened form of the name Jehovah.

Or “Hallelujah!” “Jah” is a shortened form of the name Jehovah.

Lit., “heavens of the heavens.”

Lit., “virgins.”

Or “Old and young together.”

Lit., “the horn.”

Or “Hallelujah!” “Jah” is a shortened form of the name Jehovah.

Or “Hallelujah!” “Jah” is a shortened form of the name Jehovah.

Or “make music.”

Or “Hallelujah!” “Jah” is a shortened form of the name Jehovah.

Or “Hallelujah!” “Jah” is a shortened form of the name Jehovah.

Or “the sky that bears witness to.”

Or “pipe.”

Or “Hallelujah!” “Jah” is a shortened form of the name Jehovah.

^ ***jl lesson 5 What Will You Experience at Our Christian Meetings?***

LESSON 5

What Will You Experience at Our Christian Meetings?

Many people have stopped attending religious services because they find no spiritual guidance or comfort. Why, then, should you attend the Christian meetings organized by Jehovah’s Witnesses? What will you find there?

The joy of being among loving and caring people. In the first century, Christians were organized into congregations, and they held meetings to worship God, to study the Scriptures, and to encourage one another. (Hebrews 10:24, 25) Gathered in a loving atmosphere, they felt that they were among true friends—their spiritual brothers. (2 Thessalonians 1:3;[3 John 14]) We follow the same pattern and experience similar joy.

The benefit of learning how to apply Bible principles. As was true in Bible times, men, women, and children all meet together. Qualified teachers use the Bible to help us discern how to apply its principles in our daily life. (Deuteronomy 31:12; Nehemiah 8:8) All may participate in audience discussions and in singing, allowing us to express our Christian hope.—Hebrews 10:23.

The blessing of having your faith in God strengthened. The apostle Paul told one of the congregations in his day: “I am longing to see you, . . . that we may have an interchange of encouragement by one another’s faith, both yours and mine.” (Romans 1:11, 12) At meetings, our regular contact with fellow believers strengthens our faith and determination to live a Christian life.

Why not accept this invitation to attend our congregation’s next meeting and experience these things for yourself? You will be warmly welcomed. All meetings are free—no collections are ever taken.

On what pattern are our congregation meetings based?

How can we benefit ourselves by attending Christian meetings?

FIND OUT MORE

If you would like to see inside the local Kingdom Hall before you attend one of our meetings, ask one of Jehovah’s Witnesses to take you there and show you around.

^ (Heb. 10:24, 25) And let us consider* one another so as to incite* to love and fine works, 25 not forsaking our meeting together, as some have the custom, but encouraging one another, and all the more so as you see the day drawing near.

Or “be concerned about; pay attention to.”

Or “motivate; stir up.”

^ (2 Thess. 1:3) We are obligated always to give thanks to God for you, brothers. This is fitting, because your faith is growing exceedingly and the love of each and every one of you is increasing toward one another.

^ (3 John 14) However, I am hoping to see you soon, and we will speak face-to-face. May you have peace. The friends send you their greetings. Give my greetings to the friends by name.

^ (Deut. 31:12) Gather the people together, the men, the women, the children,* and your foreign resident who is within your cities,* in order that they may listen and learn about and fear Jehovah your God and take care to carry out all the words of this Law.

Lit., “little ones.”

Lit., “gates.”

^ (Neh. 8:8) And they continued reading aloud from the book, from the Law of the true God, clearly explaining it and putting meaning into it; so they helped the people to understand what was being read.*

Or “they gave understanding in the reading.”

^ (Heb. 10:23) Let us hold firmly the public declaration of our hope without wavering, for the one who promised is faithful.

^ (Rom. 1:11, 12) For I am longing to see you, that I may impart some spiritual gift to you for you to be made firm; 12 or, rather, that we may have an interchange of encouragement by one another’s faith, both yours and mine.

^ ***jl lesson 7 What Are Our Meetings Like?***

LESSON 7

What Are Our Meetings Like?

Early Christian meetings consisted mainly of songs, prayers, and the reading and discussing of the Scriptures—all free of any ritual. (1 Corinthians 14:26) You can expect something very similar at our meetings.

The instruction is Bible-based and practical. On the weekend, each congregation meets to hear a 30-minute Bible discourse on how the Scriptures relate to our lives and to the times we live in. All of us are encouraged to follow along in our own Bible. After the discourse, there is a one-hour “Watchtower” Study, in which members of the congregation are welcome to participate in a discussion of an article from the study edition of The Watchtower. This discussion helps us to apply the Bible’s guidance in our lives. The same material is studied in every one of our more than 110,000 congregations earth wide.

We are helped to improve our teaching skills. We also meet together on a midweek evening for a three-part program entitled Our Christian Life and Ministry, based on material provided in a monthly Life and Ministry Meeting Workbook. The first part of this meeting, Treasures From God’s Word, helps us to become familiar with a portion of the Bible that the congregation has read in advance. Next, Apply Yourself to the Field Ministry includes demonstrations of how to discuss the Bible with others. A counselor makes observations that help us improve our reading and speaking skills. (1 Timothy 4:13) The last part, Living as Christians, considers the practical application of Bible principles in day-to-day life. This includes a question-and-answer discussion that deepens our understanding of the Bible.

When you attend our meetings, you will no doubt be impressed by the quality of Bible education that you are receiving.—[Isaiah 54:13].

What can you expect to hear at the meetings of Jehovah’s Witnesses?

Which of our weekly meetings would you like to attend next?

FIND OUT MORE

Examine some of the material that will be discussed at the next few meetings. Note what you will be able to learn from the Bible that can be useful in your everyday life.

^ (1 Cor. 14:26) What is to be done, then, brothers? When you come together, one has a psalm, another has a teaching, another has a revelation, another has a tongue, and another has an interpretation. Let all things take place for building up.

^ (1 Tim. 4:13) Until I come, continue applying yourself to public reading, to exhortation,* to teaching.

Or “encouragement.”

^ (Isa. 54:13) And all your sons* will be taught by Jehovah, And the peace of your sons* will be abundant.

Or “children.”

Or “children.”